<debate duration="6571" url="https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/america-cannot-and-will-not-succeed-afghanistanpakistan"><speakers><speaker name="Steven Clemons" position="for"><description>Directs the American Strategy Program at the New America Foundation</description><bio>Clemons directs the American Strategy Program at the New America Foundation, which aims to promote a new American internationalism that combines a... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Patrick Lang" position="for"><description>Retired Senior Officer of U.S. Military Intelligence and U.S. Army Special Forces (The Green Berets)</description><bio>Lang is a retired senior officer of U.S. Military Intelligence and U.S. Army Special Forces (The Green Berets). He served in the Department of Defense... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Ralph Peters" position="for"><description>Retired Army Officer</description><bio>Peters is a retired Army officer who rose from the enlisted ranks. As a soldier or civilian, he has experience in over 70 countries.Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="James Shinn" position="against"><description>Assistant Secretary of Defense for Asia in 2007-2008</description><bio>Shinn was assistant secretary of defense for Asia in 2007-2008. Before the Pentagon he served as the national intelligence officer for East Asia in... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="John Nagl" position="against"><description>President of the Center for a New American Security</description><bio>Nagl is president of the Center for a New American Security and a visiting professor in the War Studies Department at Kings College of London. Nagl... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Steve Coll" position="against"><description>President and CEO of New America Foundation</description><bio>Coll is president and CEO of New America Foundation, and a staff writer at the New Yorker magazine. Previously he spent 20 years as a foreign correspondent... Read More</bio></speaker></speakers><results><result against="25" for="48" submitters="live" undecided="27" when="before" /><result against="45" for="43" submitters="live" undecided="12" when="after" /><result for="100" submitters="online" when="before" /><result for="100" submitters="online" when="after" /></results><transcript /></debate>