<debate duration="6261" url="https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/america-blame-mexicos-drug-war"><speakers><speaker name="Andres Martinez" position="for"><description>Director, The New America Foundation's Bernard L. Schwartz Fellows Program.</description><bio>Directs the New America Foundation's Bernard L. Schwartz Fellows Program. He was the editorial page editor of the Los Angeles Times from 2004-2007... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Jeffrey Miron" position="for"><description>Senior Lecturer, Harvard University</description><bio>is senior lecturer and director of Undergraduate Studies in the Department of Economics at Harvard University. Miron holds a B.A. from Swarthmore... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Fareed Zakaria" position="for"><description>Editor, Newsweek International</description><bio>Was named editor of Newsweek International in October 2000, overseeing all Newsweek&#146;s editions abroad. The magazine has an audience of over 24 million... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Asa Hutchinson" position="against"><description>Former Administrator, Drug Enforcement Administration</description><bio>Asa Hutchinson is CEO of Hutchinson Group, a homeland security consulting firm, and practices law in Northwest Arkansas.  Hutchinson was the... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Chris W. Cox" position="against"><description>Executive Director, the NRA Institute for Legislative Action (ILA)</description><bio>Is the executive director of the NRA Institute for Legislative Action (ILA), the lobbying arm of the National Rifle Association of America. Cox oversees... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Jorge Castaneda" position="against"><description>Former Foreign Minister of Mexico</description><bio>Was foreign minister of Mexico from 2000 to 2003. Casta&#241;eda is a renowned public intellectual, political scientist, and prolific writer, with an... Read More</bio></speaker></speakers><results><result against="22" for="43" submitters="live" undecided="35" when="before" /><result against="22" for="72" submitters="live" undecided="6" when="after" /><result for="100" submitters="online" when="before" /><result for="100" submitters="online" when="after" /></results><transcript /></debate>