<debate duration="5964" url="https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/art-market-less-ethical-stock-market"><speakers><speaker name="Richard Feigen" position="for"><description>Founder of Richard L. Feigen &amp; Co. art dealers, Art Collector and Author</description><bio>Richard is an active collector of early Italian and Baroque paintings, English landscapes, surrealists, Max Beckmann and contemporary art. He founded... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Michael Hue-Williams" position="for"><description>Owner and CEO of Albion Gallery</description><bio>Micheal is owner and CEO of Albion Gallery. Albion is the only gallery in London to incorporate a major global program that represents leading international... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Adam Lindemann" position="for"><description>Investor, Entrepreneur, Art Collector and Author</description><bio>Adam is an investor and entrepreneur with a background in industries from energy and communications to real estate and asset management. He has re-launched... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Amy Cappellazzo" position="against"><description>International Co-Head of Post-War and Contemporary Art and Deputy Chairman at Christie's</description><bio>Amy was appointed deputy chairman at Christie's in January of 2008 and has been the international co-head of Post-War and Contemporary Art since 2001... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Chuck Close" position="against"><description>Artist</description><bio>Chuck's work has been the subject of more than 150 solo exhibitions including many major museum retrospectives, and he has participated in almost... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Jerry Saltz" position="against"><description>Senior Art Critic for New York magazine</description><bio>Saltz is a two-time finalist for the Pulitzer Prize in criticism. He has lectured at Harvard, The Museum of Modern Art, the Whitney Museum of American... Read More</bio></speaker></speakers><results><result against="30" for="32" submitters="live" undecided="18" when="before" /><result against="33" for="35" submitters="live" undecided="12" when="after" /><result for="50" submitters="online" undecided="50" when="before" /><result for="100" submitters="online" when="after" /></results><transcript /></debate>