<debate duration="6193" url="https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/blame-washington-more-wall-street-financial-crisis"><speakers><speaker name="Niall Ferguson" position="for"><description>Laurence A. Tisch Professor of History at Harvard University, a senior research fellow of Jesus College, Oxford University, and a senior fellow of the Hoover Institution, Stanford University</description><bio>The bestselling author of Paper and Iron, The House of Rothschild, The Pity of War, The Cash Nexus, Empire, Colossus (2002) and The War of the World... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="John Steele Gordon" position="for"><description>Lifelong Author and Commentator on New York's Business and Financial History</description><bio>Gordon's books include Hamilton's Blessing: the Extraordinary Life and Times of Our National Debt (1997), The Great Game: The Emergence of Wall Street... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Nouriel Roubini" position="for"><description>Professor, Economics and International Business, Stern School of Business, New York University.</description><bio>Is a professor of economics and international business at the Stern School of Business, New York University, and co-founder and chairman of RGE Monitor... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Alex Berenson" position="against"><description>Investigative Reporter for the New York Times</description><bio>Alex has been a business investigative reporter for the New York Times since 2000. He is the author of three novels and one non-fiction book, The... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Jim Chanos" position="against"><description>Founder and Managing Partner of Kynikos Associates</description><bio>As the largest exclusive short selling investment firm, Kynikos provides investment management services for both domestic and offshore clients. Chanos... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Nell Minow" position="against"><description>Editor and Co-Founder of The Corporate Library</description><bio>Nell is the editor and co-founder of The Corporate Library, an independent corporate governance research firm. Previously, Minow was a Principal of... Read More</bio></speaker></speakers><results><result against="30" for="42" submitters="live" undecided="11" when="before" /><result against="31" for="43" submitters="live" undecided="9" when="after" /><result against="100" submitters="online" when="before" /><result against="100" submitters="online" when="after" /></results><transcript /></debate>