<debate duration="5808" url="https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/blame-big-pharma-out-control-health-care-costs"><speakers><speaker name="Dr. Ezekiel J. Emanuel" position="for"><description>Bioethicist &amp; Vice Provost for Global Initiatives, University of Pennsylvania</description><bio>Ezekiel J. Emanuel, M.D., is an oncologist, author, and a senior fellow at the Center for American Progress. He was founding chair of the Department... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Neera Tanden" position="for"><description>President and CEO, Center for American Progress</description><bio>Neera Tanden is the president and CEO of the Center for American Progress and the Center for American Progress Action Fund. Tanden has served in both... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Lori Reilly" position="against"><description>Executive VP for Policy, Research, and Membership, PhRMA</description><bio>Lori M. Reilly is executive vice president for policy, research and membership at the Pharmaceutical Research and Manufacturers of America (PhRMA)... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Paul Howard" position="against"><description>Director of Health Policy, Manhattan Institute</description><bio>Paul Howard is a senior fellow at the Manhattan Institute, director of health policy, and a member of Project FDA, an MI initiative. He is a contributor... Read More</bio></speaker></speakers><results><result against="28" for="33" submitters="live" undecided="39" when="before" /><result against="48" for="42" submitters="live" undecided="10" when="after" /><result against="22" for="59" submitters="online" undecided="15" when="before" /><result against="31" for="57" submitters="online" undecided="8" when="after" /></results><transcript><p end="459" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="396">He's only joking, just to be clear.</p><p end="459" is_meta="true" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="396">laughter</p><p end="517" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="459">I think that means that I am full of sweetness and light.</p><p end="517" is_meta="true" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="459">laughter</p><p end="517" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="459">Absolutely.</p><p end="517" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="459">Well, like all big institutions it tends to be pretty risk averse and more worried about bad things happening than making good things happen faster.</p><p end="578" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="517">Lori Reilly.</p><p end="578" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="517">On this topic, I would say that the conversation has been minimal, at best. And I think it could be improved with a more informed debate.</p><p end="645" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="578">Good evening, everyone. It's a great honor to be here to talk about one of the most important issues, I think, we face in the healthcare system. And it -- there are many issues that aren't getting proper discussion in our presidential debate, but this is one that has actually united those candidates. Candidates who rarely agree on anything have actually both talked about this challenge. And as we think about this debate tonight, and this conversation, I wanted to start off with where I think this debate really should start off.</p><p end="756" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="645">Which is with consumers, and people affected by high drug prices. I just want us all to keep in mind throughout this evening, moms who are working hard every day, moms like Lauren Bauman [spelled phonetically], who has had cancer for 10 years and relies on a daily dose of Gleevec, a cancer drug whose price has more than tripled since 2001. Even with insurance, her co-pay is as high as $2,200 a month. $2,200 a month. That has driven her family into bankruptcy and forced her and her 9-year-old daughter to move out of their house. And she says she has no choice, because without this pill, she will die.</p><p end="756" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="645">That's -- that is a terrible, terrible story. But there are stories like that throughout our country. Stories of 70-year-old diabetes patients who rely on insulin and whose price has tripled in a decade; the mom and her son who both need -- who have severe allergies and both need an Epi-Pen, and have to split it between the two of them. Now, we're going to hear a lot tonight about who is responsible for these situations. I have to remind everyone that pharmaceutical costs in the United States are higher than in any developed country. What does that mean? Consumers around the world are paying much less than consumers in the United States. Why is that? That's because pharmaceutical companies charge us for higher costs.</p><p end="878" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="756">They charge us more than they charge anyone else. Now, their response is usually that we need innovation, and that's what's driving costs. But when you really look at it, the truth is that pharmaceutical companies -- the vast majority of pharmaceutical companies are spending more on marketing than they are on research. They're spending, in fact, much more, usually, on marketing than on research. And let me remind everyone that the American consumer: Lauren, that the grandparent, the child who needs these drugs -- all of us as consumers are paying twice. We pay high drug prices, but we also, as taxpayers, pay for the National Institutes of Health, the research to fund pharmaceutical companies. So, the American consumer is really bearing this price on both ends. We are paying high prices, higher than anyone else in the world.</p><p end="878" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="756">And we are paying for the research. More research is done in the United States, federal investment, than elsewhere. And that's why, I think, this has become such a critical issue in this election and at a time when there is so much disagreement on so many issues. We are seeing Republicans and Democrats support strong action to reign in the price of pharmaceuticals. And the reason why is that pharmaceuticals aren't like any other issue. They're not like -- it's not a normal market. Pharmaceuticals are -- pharmaceutical companies are able to price -- to basically charge a monopoly price and rely on numerous insurance companies who don't have that pricing power to just pay what they can charge. And that is why you're seeing this outrage around the country. You're seeing this outrage because there is only one Epi-pen.</p><p end="945" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="878">There is only one drug. And essentially, the pharmaceutical company is saying, I'm not going to charge you the value of this drug. I'm going to charge you whatever I can. And in a healthcare system, that's not right. In a system where people need these drugs to live, that's not right. So, we'll get into more solutions as we go this evening. But I'd just like to say -- leave you with the words of one healthcare observer who recently said, "Imagine if Jonas Salk would have priced the polio vaccine like today's drug companies. We'd still have polio." So, with that, I will turn it over to the other side.</p><p end="1062" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="945">Thank you, John, and good evening. My role here tonight probably seems like a steep uphill climb. I think that for most people in the audience you probably feel the same way about the pharmaceutical company as you do about a pat down at the TSA. And not all of that skepticism is unwarranted. Some patients, particularly those with serious chronic illnesses, are paying too much out of pocket for their medicines, and we need to find a solution for that. So I'm not here to defend the industry or any part of the industry. What I am here to do is to defend the policies that keep Americans healthy and provide hope in the face of a devastating diagnosis. Lori is going to talk about how we can do that in a few minutes -- about how we can balance innovation and access.</p><p end="1062" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="945">But the important thing is to continue innovation and expand access, because if we go down the road that other nations have gone down and use price controls to control investment in innovation in the industry, make no mistake, we will have fewer medicines, people will suffer and die unnecessarily. And if we step back and take a look at the big picture, not the headlines of the moment, not last year's data, but decades of data and evidence, we'll see that medicines properly used are the things that keep us out of the most expensive parts of the healthcare system; that's hospital beds and nursing homes.</p><p end="1062" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="945">After you hear Lori and I speak, you're going to join us in voting against the motion that we should blame big pharma for runaway healthcare costs because they are not the biggest costs we face. It's not the suffering from Alzheimer's or diabetes. It's not the prolonged disability and premature death that's being driven by medicines.</p><p end="1179" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="1062">That is what they are meant to cure. Zeke and Neera are going to be arguing that drug costs, not hospital costs, not nursing homes, not physician visits, are going to sink the economy unless we empower a committee of government regulators to step in and set prices and profits for medicines. If you think that the core problem with American healthcare today is that we don't have enough bureaucrats and committees, then I'd encourage you to accept their plan. If, on the other hand, you want innovation that moves at the pace of 21st century technology, I have an alternative for you that focuses on competition, innovation, and, of course, containing total healthcare costs. The problem with our debates around drugs is that the prices of drugs are very easy to see. They come with sticker prices. The benefits can be harder to see because they accrue over years and decades.</p><p end="1179" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="1062">Let me give you just three examples. From 1969 to 2013, mortality from cardiovascular disease declined by nearly 70 percent thanks to medicines that were highly effective for high cholesterol and high blood pressure. For HIV/AIDS, mortality has declined by 85 percent. And today, some patients can keep their disease in check with a single pill. Even a disease as complex as cancer, we've seen gains; 20 percent over the past 20 years, a reduction in mortality and with better treatments coming online every day. Remember, none of these developments were inevitable. If we had handled the prescription drug challenge the way many other countries do and the way our opponents tonight suggest, we would see fewer innovations, and we'd wait longer for them. Now, apply that analysis to the future and think about what it means. There are new technologies on the way that promise to do even more to lower medical costs and improve health.</p><p end="1303" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="1179">Gene therapies that can restore sight to blind children, stem cell therapies that can restore a working pancreas to a diabetic woman who no longer has to rely on insulin. Shouldn't we be doing everything possible to bring those technologies to patients as quickly and safely as possible?</p><p end="1303" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="1179">Let me close with a few basic facts about why you should vote against the motion tonight. First, government actuaries and independent analysts agree the total level of spending we're going to be devoting to medicines is going to stay level for the next decade, at about 16 percent of total spending. About 85 percent of that spending is coming from somewhere else. To put it another way, we're going to spend more on physicians and hospitals -- a trillion dollars more, over the next decade. Second, it's essential to remember that effective prescription drugs can actually reduce other healthcare costs. So, the Alzheimer's association projects that if we had a treatment by 2025 that just delayed, not cured --</p><p end="1303" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="1179">-- just delayed Alzheimer's by five years, over the next decade, Medicare would save close to $350 billion, and patients would be saving more than $220 billion in out-of-pocket costs. So when we look at the total cost of care, how much is devoted to medicines, how much of the increase is somewhere else, we see a very different picture, because sometimes a drug that looks expensive is going to wind up being the cheapest option for treating that condition we have. And those expensive medicines don't stay expensive forever. Patents expire, prices plummet. Doctors, MRIs and hospital beds start expensive, and they stay expensive. If we're serious about slowing runaway healthcare costs, what we need to do is not focus on the sticker price of the drug but of the total price of delivering better health. We need business models that reward doctors and hospitals for delivering better care and reducing costs. The overarching principle is simply this: More experiments, more competition, and fewer attempts to micromanage innovation because we don't know --</p><p end="1352" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="1303">-- because a venture capitalist who has billions of dollars at stake doesn't know what the technology is that's going to be best positioned to improve our health a decade from now. So please join me in voting against the motion: Blame big pharma for runaway healthcare costs. Thank you.</p><p end="1779" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="1720">Thank you. In the 1990s, HIV-AIDS was feared not just because of the human toll it was taking on society. It was also feared because of the strong financial impact it was having on our healthcare system. But in the mid-1990s, combination therapy treatments came to market. And since that time, HIV-AIDS death rates have fallen by 86 percent in this country.</p><p end="1844" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="1779">Today, it's chronic disease and treating patients with chronic disease that are responsible for 90 percent of all healthcare costs. Just one of these -- diabetes -- is responsible for $245 billion in costs. We have medicines to treat patients with diabetes. We know how to treat them and we have guidelines that tell us how to treat them, but yet only one in three patients today is adequately treated for their diabetes. If we did more to get those patients treated and have them adherent to their medicines, we would save $19 billion in this country. But the real tsunami, in terms of healthcare costs, is coming in the not-too-distant future, when we can anticipate spending a trillion dollars to care for patients with Alzheimer's disease. If we do nothing to address those costs, they're coming. I don't know of any other way to address those costs, other than innovation. And the good news is that we're making strong progress in our science.</p><p end="1844" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="1779">Today, immunotherapy medicines that are hitting the market are using the body's own immune system to fight back against hard-to-treat cancers.</p><p end="1903" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="1844">And we're seeing that progress already, with cancer death rates falling 23 percent just since 1991. When we talk about health care costs, though -- and Zeke mentioned it -- Hepatitis C is one that comes to mind. But what people don't often talk about is that before these new, innovative treatments hit the market, we were spending $30 billion a year in this country to treat patients with Hepatitis C, and those costs were projected to climb to $80 billion in 20 years. But again, innovation happened. New medicines hit the market that took a disease that killed five times as many people as HIV-AIDS does in this country and cured it in eight to 12 weeks of time. And something else happened. In under a year, we had two additional Hepatitis C medicines that came to market, and the price of those medicines fell by 40 to 60 percent, in terms of what they cost before. From a clinical perspective, we've cured a million patients from Hepatitis C in two-and-a-half years.</p><p end="2022" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="1903">That's more than the previous 20 years combined. While it's clear that the launch of those medicines in 2014 caused prescription drug spending to grow, and we hit a high-water mark of 12.5 percent in 2014, the government actuaries, though, predict over the next decade, spending for medicines will be in line with all other forms of healthcare spending costs. Why should we believe the actuaries? Well, let me explain. The system in our country works like this. When a brand name medicine gets approved, it can expect to get competition from another brand name medicine in under two years of time. And the example I just used, with Hepatitis C, that competition happened in less than a year. When that competition happened, prices fall.</p><p end="2022" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="1903">In addition, we have generic entry. And when generic entry happens, typically, 10 to 12 years after a product hits the market, 80 percent of costs drop for that product.</p><p end="2022" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="1903">Market share shifts overnight. Today, 90 percent of all medicines used in this country are generic. And we have something also very different. Neera mentioned in her opening that we have all of these different payers, and they don't have enough pull to get -- to actually negotiate with our companies. Well, that's untrue. There are three large pharmacy benefit managers in this country that buy on behalf of 75 percent of all prescription drugs. And they use that leverage extensively to drive big discounts and big rebates from companies, to the tune of $115 billion last year.</p><p end="2022" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="1903">So, to say that there's not competition in our marketplace is factually incorrect. And the difference between medicines and all other forms of healthcare is that our costs do fall over time. We don't have generic hospitals or generic doctors. The cost of procedures, like an angioplasty, have gone up 66 percent, and there is no signs that it will ever fall.</p><p end="2086" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="2022">But the price of medicines does fall over time. I'm not going to sit here and argue, though, that solving the healthcare challenges that we face are somebody else's problem. We all share in trying to get to a better system, and we do believe that there are solutions that can be out there that will address some of the cost challenges we face. Paul mentioned the need to reform the FDA.</p><p end="2086" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="2022">Today, there are 4,000 drugs sitting at the Food and Drug Administration, generic drugs, waiting to get approval. The average time to get a generic drug approved at the FDA today is four years. That's too long. Getting generic medicines to the market sooner increases competition. We also need to ensure that the FDA can keep pace with the regulatory science and the new advances we're making so that they can review brand name drugs quicker and get those to market so that they compete with other brand name drugs. And we also need to address the challenges to moving towards a value-based healthcare system. We embrace the movement towards moving towards a value-based healthcare system, but we also need to recognize that today there are challenges that make it difficult to do so.</p><p end="2145" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="2086">The need for future innovation is clear. Drug costs, though, are not unsustainable. Disease and the costs associated with disease in this country is what is unsustainable. While the solutions that you're going to hear espoused by my opponents tonight attempt to glorify some of the systems that we see abroad, they typically fail to acknowledge the real consequences when governments seek to set prices, intervene in markets, and determine the value a given medicine has. Those decisions are best left to patients and providers. I urge you to vote against the motion tonight. Thank you.</p><p end="2383" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="2324">I want some more of whatever Zeke's drinking.</p><p end="2443" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="2383">Look, I mean, the dissonance here is this: They're pointing to individual drug prices and saying they're going up, up, up, up. And we're pointing out that, look, there are powerful negotiators, these large insurers that are standing between consumers and getting enormous rebates that last year cut drug price increases from around 12 percent down to a net 2.8 percent. Zeke had pointed to specialty drugs and saying, that's where the cost is going, funnily --</p><p end="2443" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="2383">Well, funnily enough, it doesn't keep going up, up, up forever, because what happens is biosimilars, the generic versions of these expensive injectable drugs, enter the market and compete. Now, look, there's not an infinite amount of complexity here. We saw, during the 1990s, people really -- and Lori spoke to this -- saying, oh, my God, how are we going to afford all these statins or HIV drugs? The market adapted, and we did, and drug prices fell. Commercial spending fell as early as 2000 -- as late as 2012.</p><p end="2443" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="2383">So there is just two facts here that I would like spell out, just to remind everyone. We don't -- we can all have estimates of the future.</p><p end="2561" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="2443">The reality is, in 2014 alone, just to reiterate, prescription drug prices -- all prescription drug prices, not just specialty drugs -- that all prescription drug prices increased by 12.2 percent. It was 8 percent last year, but that, of course, in both years is the fastest rate of growth for any part of the health care system. When you look at Medicare -- the Medicare actuary, Medicare officials see prescription drug prices as the fastest growing part of the health care system. We can have projections into the future, but this is our lived experience. And one of the reasons why you see Republicans and Democrats naming prescription drug prices as their top concern on health care issues, finding a rare area of bipartisan support is because we are living this experience of paying exorbitant prices for drugs.</p><p end="2561" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="2443">Exorbitant prices that people in other countries don't pay and still have access to quality drugs.</p><p end="2561" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="2443">Thank you. What Neera quoted was actually not price growth. That was spending growth. And spending growth is the combination of price times volume. So she's right that in 2014 we did see spending growth increase. And a large part of the reason that we had that, again, was new treatments for hepatitis C that are curing a disease that kills five times as many people as HIV/AIDS, that was going to cost our health care system $80 billion over the next 20 years' time. If you look back at the entire last decade in terms of spending growth for prescription medicines, we were less; less in terms of spending growth compared to hospitals, compared to doctors, compared to home health care. If you look going forward over the next decade, we're expected to spend $2.4 trillion more on health care in this country.</p><p end="2626" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="2561">85 percent of that additional 2.4 trillion is attributable to hospitals, doctors, home health, nursing homes, everyone but prescription drugs. We're about 15 percent of that increase going forward.</p><p end="2684" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="2626">Thank you. Part of the issue that Zeke is pointing out has to do with how insurance companies treat cost sharing for medicines relative to any other part of the health care system. Today patients are asked to pay on average 20 percent out of pocket for their prescription medicines. Compare that to hospital costs out of pocket, 4 percent. Physicians under 10 percent.</p><p end="2803" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="2684">So it's no surprise that when patients go to the pharmacy counter, they're asked to pay more for their medicine out of their own pocket and that's how our insurance system works today. Zeke mentioned list price growth, and that's an important thing to remember here. List price growth is not the price that a PBM, one of those three large PBMs pays for a product. He specifically mentioned insulin prices. The net prices for insulin are cheaper today than they were three years ago. Cheaper today than they were three years ago, but part of the problem in our health care system is that we have a rise in high deductible health plans where today patients are being asked to pay out of pocket that list price. The payers, the health plans, are not providing those discounts back to the individual patient. Something's wrong with that system when a patient is asked to pay full price for something when the payer or plan gets it for 50 percent off. That's what's wrong with our health care system and that's what we need to focus on, and I would just say one more thing, which is in regards to Zeke mentioned statins.</p><p end="2803" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="2684">I want to talk about hepatitis C since it was recent. As soon as the introduction of Hep C --</p><p end="2803" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="2684">[unintelligible] 40 to 60 percent --</p><p end="2803" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="2684">Okay.</p><p end="2803" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="2684">Yeah. I think we should really take on -- I want to take on both of these points. I -- you know, I'm no great fan of the insurance companies for sure, but we should recognize here that one of the reasons why people don't really have access to good data around list prices is because pharmaceutical companies aren't transparent about prices. A great way for us to instill some competition into the pharmaceutical market is for us to all as consumers have an assessment of these prices, what's going into them, how much research dollars are driving into the cost, how much marketing dollars are driving into the cost, but they won't share that information with us because they think that's information only they should have.</p><p end="2867" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="2803">If you believe in markets you should believe in transparency and if you believe in transparency you should believe that consumers should be able to evaluate that. But one of the reasons why I don't think they want to drive to a value-based system is because there are so many costs unrelated to the value of the drug that are driving this, marketing and sadly, high profitability. Again, pharmaceutical companies are the highest profit margin companies in the --</p><p end="2867" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="2803">-- much more than insurance companies to which I agree we could have a lot more competition there as well.</p><p end="2867" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="2803">Well, the thing I find kind of amusing of Neera and Zeke's point, especially Neera, is, you know, what's the right profit?</p><p end="2922" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="2867">I guess you know. I mean, maybe it's the automotive industry's 6 percent. How about fast food, 2 percent? What other industry do you want to be more profitable than the one that's attempting to get a cure for HIV? I mean, the challenge that we're talking about here is that we actually want two things. We want R&amp;D to be as inexpensive as possible so many more people can bring medicines to market and compete and then primary care indications we do see prices fall after these rebates that the insurers get. We want to make sure those are passed along to patients. So, the challenge here is look, if you want to see someone else -- if you want to see investors send their money somewhere else into a less risky industry, maybe software, the next Snapchat, by all means, cut the profits for the pharmaceutical industry. Those investors in those companies can send their money elsewhere.</p><p end="2922" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="2867">I need to respond.</p><p end="2990" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="2922">No. The number is what is it that you need to get? What is the profit margin you need to get to reward your investors? And that's --</p><p end="2990" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="2922">[laughs] Okay.</p><p end="2990" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="2922">-- for the risk that they bear.</p><p end="2990" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="2922">I'm so loving this. So &#8211;</p><p end="2990" is_meta="true" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="2922">laughter</p><p end="2990" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="2922">-- I think I'm so pleased that you mentioned venture capital, right? Because I think -- the kind of prototypical example people have today is not the traditional pharmaceutical company that's plowing so much money. But we know it's -- this does not really happen, but there's the theory that they're plowing so much money into research, and they're basically doing that in order to find that miracle drug, which we all hope they do. But what's actually -- the biggest change in the pharmaceutical market is the rise of the Martin Shkrelis of the world, which is an essential -- you could call it "venture capital," you could call it "vulture capital," but the idea of it &#8211;</p><p end="2990" is_meta="true" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="2922">laughter</p><p end="2990" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="2922">-- is essentially to use the monopoly power of particular drugs to drive the highest prices to -- for individuals, and basically live off the system to extract profits.</p><p end="3104" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="2990">That is the newest innovation. And truly, like, existing pharmaceutical companies recognize that as a challenge. And that is -- in a system where you do not have true competition -- is a challenge. And I appreciate -- I do not want to set the profit margin for a company. But when there is a drug that people literally have to choose between bankruptcy and paying -- even when they have health insurance -- I'm sorry to say, I think 55 percent might be something you might bat an eye at. I'm not saying I'm going to set that price. But we live in a world where at least you could admit -- at least you could admit that should trouble you.</p><p end="3104" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="2990">Well, it does trouble me, because I view that as a failure of the health care system, Neera. You know, the purpose of insurance is to spread risk across large populations.</p><p end="3104" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="2990">So, to the extent that you have a patient who is sick and needs expensive care -- whether it's a medicine or whether it's a surgical procedure -- that insurance -- that's the purpose of insurance, to be there to help pay for those instances. With regards to profitability, I want to come back, because I think we always cite profitability be -- profitability of the companies that we've all heard of, right? You'll trounced out Gilead's profitability or Pfizer's profitability. But the reality is, 90 percent of the 1,200 biopharmaceutical companies that exist today make zero profit. You've cherry-picked the 10 percent of them that do. But the hope is &#8211;</p><p end="3104" is_meta="true" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="2990">laughter</p><p end="3104" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="2990">-- it's true, Zeke. The hope is that -- all of them. And you know, bringing up Martin Shkreli, I'll be the first to say what he did was shameful. But what he did was take advantage of a system where that --</p><p end="3104" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="2990">Absolutely.</p><p end="3104" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="2990">-- product was off-patent --</p><p end="3104" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="2990">Absolutely. Took advantage of the system --</p><p end="3104" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="2990">-- off-patent --</p><p end="3104" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="2990">-- [inaudible] --</p><p end="3104" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="2990">-- had no generic available. We do need to find opportunities to make sure &#8211;</p><p end="3164" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="3104">-- if we've got 90 percent of drugs on the market today are the generic, let's make sure that we have a competitive market for generics, too, when drugs go off-patent.</p><p end="3226" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="3164">Yeah.</p><p end="3226" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="3164">Absolutely. So, $50 billion dollar is what was spent on biopharmaceutical research to bring a Hepatitis C medicine to market. And that $50 billion -- 99 percent of what was done failed, never got to market.</p><p end="3284" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="3226">Gilead was successful in bringing the first product to market to treat Hepatitis C. It was launched at a price that was neutral to existing treatment. And just to give you an idea of what the existing treatment was, it was a drug -- three drugs, actually, that had to be taken for almost an entire year, that worked in less than half of the patients, that made patients so sick they typically stopped taking the medicine. And then a new medicine came along, cured the disease for 95 percent of patients in eight to 12 weeks of time. And in less than one year, we had competition from two additional products, and the price of those products have dropped 40 to 60 percent. So we can talk about hepatitis C, but to me, it is a good example of how competition in our marketplace works, and it works very, very quickly.</p><p end="3284" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="3226">Just under that example, I will remind the audience, Gilead made back its huge profit margin in a year, right?</p><p end="3346" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="3284">And the competition -- the competition that came in under your fact scenario, two competing drugs came in a year in, right? So the issue there is, why does Gilead have to charge that high a price --</p><p end="3346" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="3284">-- to begin with?</p><p end="3346" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="3284">You think you can. Look, Zeke has written about this. Zeke, you've written that you think actually the Hepatitis C Sovaldi is a good deal, right? Look, you're cherry-picking in a different sense. There was another drug, Incivek from Vertex, that was launched I think in 2011 that had a 75 percent cure rate that then got withdrawn from the market because Sovaldi was so much better. So there are all these examples. And we can talk about the NIH.</p><p end="3346" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="3284">Look, 88 percent of drugs that go into clinical trials fail, right? The entire biotech industry until just a few years ago was in the red. So we can look around and see, oh, my gosh, there's some remarkably profitable products here. But actually a lot of what they do is fail.</p><p end="3416" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="3346">And Gilead is under, you know, stock pressure right now because they're looking around at their competitors, they're taking huge decreases in their profitability because they're facing competition. You can't look at a snapshot in time.</p><p end="3416" is_meta="true" speaker="Paul Howard" start="3346">talking simultaneously</p><p end="3527" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="3416">I'm happy to respond to it. You know, I think we all want every part of the health care system and there -- to reduce costs, and it's absolutely the case that prescription drugs, when it replaces a -- you know, a surgery or a longer form of cure, that's important, absolutely. But I think the thing we have to remember is the question here is, can we do it at higher value for you the consumer? That is the question.</p><p end="3527" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="3416">You know, if you argue that over the long run, value will go up, then there's no argument against any higher price for any drug. And the question is, that's not how any other industry works. You know, when we're thinking about the iPhone or a new car, it's not like, oh, the thing is -- it's replacing something in the future.</p><p end="3527" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="3416">They are facing competition right now. And the one thing I just would like to say before we get to questions is to remind everyone here that we're also in a world in which this is not a traditional market because everyone here is subsidizing this industry with the research we pay for. It is a massive subsidy in a sense to the pharmaceutical industry which then turns around and charges all of us who are subsidizing them through our taxpayer dollars, the highest price they can charge.</p><p end="3527" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="3416">Sure. I mean, look, I think one of the problems that Neera's pointing toward, which I actually think there's a version of truth in that is, when align all the costs and say, for this person, what's the best way to keep them healthy for as long as possible? The technology that does that the best is going to be, in many cases, an effective prescription medicine, sometimes a generic, sometimes a branded drug.</p><p end="3586" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="3527">But then if you say to the doctor, &#8220;Here you go, here's your bundle, you use the thing that's most important to keeping this person healthy and keeping costs down,&#8221; that is the right alignment here. But you guys are singling out drugs like they're widgets. So let's just push down the price here on this thing, and it could turn out that then someone is in worse health later because you're not using the technology that's most efficient to get to where you say you want to --</p><p end="3586" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="3527">We want them to --</p><p end="3753" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="3650">Well, first of all, I would say just because the government isn't in the business of setting prices -- although I would say for a lot of our market they do because we pay a very -- 60 percent rebate in Medicaid. We pay a 50 percent coverage discount in Medicare part B. We pay 30 -- 340B discounts at half of the hospitals in this country. So there are a number of our prices that are regulated by the government. But I would say just because in the commercial private sector side that the government hasn't stepped in to control the prices, don't confuse that with there isn't cost containment in our sector. To the contrary. We have essentially three purchasers that are buying our drugs. They have huge leverage. One of them buys on behalf of more people that are the entire country of France.</p><p end="3753" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="3650">What does that mean? They have a "take it or leave it" policy. Just this past week, one of our companies who makes insulin announced that they're cutting 1,000 employees as a result of the fact that the competition in the insulin marketplace is driving further and further in deeper discounts. And it's because of that leverage that they have, it does keep costs in check. Yes, 2014 was a big year. I am not going to sit here and deny that. But what I ask you to look at is, look at the last past 10 years. The spending growth for drugs was below virtually every other type of health care, meaning every other form of health care spending was growing higher. Go forward the next decade. We're in line with where spending is expected to be for virtually every other segment of the health care system. So, we do have costs containment in the health care sector, in the prescription drug sector. Just because it isn't the government deciding how much to pay for something doesn't mean that there aren't --</p><p end="3753" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="3650">-- other powerful purchase --</p><p end="3816" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="3753">Could I just come back to that, because I --</p><p end="3816" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="3753">-- didn't touch the piece on returns. When it comes -- when an individual makes an investment in a biopharmaceutical company, they're making that investment knowing that almost 90 percent of what we put into an FDA lab is going to fail. So, they're betting on the chance that maybe that money that they're putting in is going to be one of the successful ones. So, as a result, they expect to get a return for that investment. So it's not to say that companies would entirely go out of business, but I think it does deter companies, and it deters investors when you're told, &#8220;Oh, that expectation of a return, it isn't going to be that anymore.&#8221;</p><p end="3875" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="3816">Actually, I think they make that investment because you have a 55 percent profit margin, which is why they can't get anywhere else in any other industry.</p><p end="3875" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="3816">But Neera, Neera, we don't have a 55 percent profit margin and you know better.</p><p end="3875" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="3816">It's 15 percent across the --</p><p end="3875" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="3816">No, it's not.</p><p end="3875" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="3816">Zeke said --</p><p end="3875" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="3816">No.</p><p end="3875" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="3816">Fifty-five in one industry, 15 across. One company, 55 percent -- 15 across, 55 percent in one company.</p><p end="3875" is_meta="true" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="3816">laughter</p><p end="3875" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="3816">To be fair, the congressional budget office, which is the scorekeeper for Congress looked at this I think back in 2005 and said look, compared to other high tech industries -- compared to other high tech industries, the pharmaceutical industry gets above average returns, but it's probably normal when you look at the risks that they face. When you think to that investor am I going to wait 10 years, have an 88 percent failure rate, or am I going to go somewhere else, commercial real estate --</p><p end="3972" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="3875">The profit margin is what you need to reward someone for taking risk.</p><p end="3972" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="3875">Yes, the question -- I'll take that first initially. The question is our pharmaceutical companies responsible for high drug prices and do -- should we find that to be something that's problematic? And so that's why we are looking at the profitability of pharmaceutical companies and when you try to avert the role of pharmaceutical companies by pointing the finger at insurance companies or pointing the finger at hospitals, I think it is relevant that those systems have much less profitability in them.</p><p end="4031" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="3972">And that is the reason why we are raising the issue of profitability. If you -- if there was very low profitability we would all recognize that that would probably be an indication of price.</p><p end="4031" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="3972">But that variability is why I think there is a lot of anger at high drug prices.</p><p end="4031" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="3972">Well, I mean, we should return, of course, to the question of the debate, which is should we be blaming pharma for runaway drug -- runaway health care costs.</p><p end="4031" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="3972">Right. Right. Out of control. Out of control, running away. So, look, it's 16 percent. It's going to stay at around 15, 16 percent. Look, 500,000 people were hired in the health care sector last quarter. It's not the profitability, it's the base spending that you're talking about and we're spending much more on hospitals and physician services so even if the lower rate of increase on a bigger base turns out to be more money, that's why it stays level over time.</p><p end="4096" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4031">This is him well behaved, just for the record.</p><p end="4153" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4096">Yeah. Well, I would challenge the notion that companies aren't willing to pay and have -- be paid based on value. Just yesterday, there was a major deal announced between AETNA and Merck for their diabetes drug, where those drugs will be tied towards value-based outcomes. Amgen and Pilgrim entered into a contract just a few months ago on their new PCSK9.</p><p end="4153" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4096">I --</p><p end="4153" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4096">And add in there, price transparency.</p><p end="4153" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4096">I would argue -- well, let's get transparency narrowed that patients want --</p><p end="4153" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4096">I would agree that most --</p><p end="4153" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4096">-- that drugs today &#8211;</p><p end="4153" is_meta="true" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4096">laughter</p><p end="4153" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4096">-- Zeke -- drugs today, more than any other part of the health care system, are, in part, based on value.</p><p end="4210" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4153">We have to do lengthy clinical trials where the safety and efficacy products of our medicines are put to the test.</p><p end="4210" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4153">Two-thirds of all drugs submitted to the FDA have comparator data submitted with them today. We then have to go in front of the payers and demonstrate to them the value that our medicines will provide to them. They don't have to cover our medicines if they don't want to. But I will say --</p><p end="4210" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4153">-- our system -- Zeke --</p><p end="4210" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4153">Zeke --</p><p end="4210" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4153">We are moving towards a system of value. And a number of our companies have stepped forward and said, "We're willing to engage in contracts that are focused on outcomes." Is it easy to do? I'll be honest, it's not. And part of the reason it's not is government regulation. Government regulation is stuck in a fee-for-service world, and we're moving towards a value-based system. So, I would hope -- and ask you if you would agree with us that changing some of the current government regulations about how we communicate about our products, what we can do to support patients and insure their adherence are addressed so that we can move more rapidly to that system.</p><p end="4246" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4210">Well --</p><p end="4246" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4210">Zeke --</p><p end="4246" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4210">-- you're talking about cost-effectiveness, and that's a whole other --</p><p end="4246" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4210">-- can of worms. That's not value-based pricing.</p><p end="4292" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4246">I will get it there.</p><p end="4292" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4246">I'm happy to get it to that, though --</p><p end="4292" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4246">-- [inaudible] --</p><p end="4292" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4246">So, the reason that -- it might be a minute.</p><p end="4349" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4292">The reason --</p><p end="4349" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4292">That seems kind of mean.</p><p end="4349" is_meta="true" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4292">laughs</p><p end="4349" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="4292">Do we have equal time?</p><p end="4349" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4292">So the issue here is -- this, I think, is really relevant to how much pharmaceuticals are driving it in the United States, because when you look at other countries, they are paying dramatically less for -- lower prices. The reason why they are drive -- having lower prices is because you have someone -- not necessarily the government. In many countries, it's a private actor that has market power for many, many consumers -- not just insurance companies -- multi-consumers. It has that market power to negotiate a lower drug price. And I think that is an indication as to why monopoly power in the United States is really on one end.</p><p end="4412" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4349">We are paying higher than any other country because you can say there's three PBNs, there is a Medicare system, there is multiple insurers that are paying. There -- we have a much more fragmented system, and that is why this is an indication as said precisely why, in the United States, pharmaceutical companies are driving that price up, because they never charge this much anywhere else in the world.</p><p end="4412" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="4349">I think that was more than 30 seconds, though.</p><p end="4412" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="4349">So, look, the U.S. is the world's medicine chest. So we produce far more drugs, far more drug research, Silicon Valley, all of that stuff. And once you produce the drug, the company -- it's like a plane that takes off. The people who are paying first class and people who are sitting in coach, but everybody gets to the same place. But once the U.S. companies produce those products, they have every financial incentive to sell them even though they're taking a massive haircut on the price.</p><p end="4472" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="4412">Now, economists are unanimous that R &amp; D -- global R &amp; D, depends on global revenues. So those countries are free riding on our investments in research and development, and there'd be more medicines available to everyone if they were paying U.S. prices.</p><p end="4472" is_meta="true" speaker="Paul Howard" start="4412">applause</p><p end="4472" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4412">Yes. And perhaps if we -- what that means is we are very much subsidizing on both ends. We're paying for high research dollars, and we're paying high consumer dollars, right? So maybe we could have a system where we pay less, other countries pay more. I'm definitely for that.</p><p end="4472" is_meta="true" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4412">applause</p><p end="4472" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4412">Can I address the NIH point, because it's come up many times.</p><p end="4472" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4412">Quickly? Okay.</p><p end="4472" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4412">And we can do that by Medicare and negotiating drug prices.</p><p end="4472" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4412">The National Institutes of Health does spend money on research and development, but their entire budget last year was $30 billion. The entire budget for biopharmaceutical research and development was over 75 billion.</p><p end="4534" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4472">Not all of the NIH budget goes to research. And in fact, a few years ago, Congress asked NIH to do a study, and it said, "Do us a favor. Look at the top 50 drugs that are sold in this country and tell us how many of them had a connection back to NIH funding." They ended up looking at 47 drugs and found that four of them had a connection back to the NIH, not insignificant at all. And we know that the role that the NIH plays is extremely important. It helps fund a lot of the basic research. But to say that NIH funding is a substitute for the risk that happens by biopharmaceutical companies to bring a new medicine to market significantly undervalues the role that biopharmaceuticals play.</p><p end="4534" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4472">No one is saying it's a substitute. I just want to be clear about that.</p><p end="4534" is_meta="true" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4472">applause</p><p end="4534" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4472">It's for you, Zeke.</p><p end="4639" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4578">I do think there --</p><p end="4639" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4578">I do think there does need to be more done to address some of the challenges that patients are paying when they go to the pharmacy counter. I don't think it's right that insurance companies treat patients that have diseases like HIV/AIDS or rheumatoid arthritis or MS differently than they treat someone who has to go into the hospital and have a surgical procedure. But they do today. Patients today are punished based on their biology. If you need a medicine, you can expect to pay more out of pocket for it relative to a procedure that might cost exactly the same if you need it in the hospital setting.</p><p end="4698" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4639">And that's wrong. I think in our system that's wrong. We've also seen a growing shift in terms of really high deductible plans. You know, it used to be the case, when you went to the pharmacy counter January 1, you had insurance coverage from day one. Well, now what's happening is that they're saying, no, drugs are part of this really big deductible, maybe 3, 4, $5,000 deductible. And those discounts and rebates that I talked about earlier, the payers and the PBMs, they're not passing those discounts on to patients at point of sale, and that's wrong. No patient should ever be paying more for a medicine than their insurance company paid for that medicine.</p><p end="4698" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4639">I just -- no disagreement there. I'd say one quick thing about this, which is, if you have insurance companies insulate the price of drugs, which is what you're calling for, if you say, you know, helping for surgeries, you only pay 4 percent.</p><p end="4755" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4698">For drugs you only pay 4 percent. What that's saying is just, your premium will rise with high drug prices, and you will just not see it in the drug price.</p><p end="4755" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4698">Neera, I --</p><p end="4755" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4698">So that is -- but no, no.</p><p end="4755" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4698">Neera --</p><p end="4755" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4698">I just want to be clear -- just want to be clear about this. If the system works as it does, and -- and you -- and you have that -- I mean, I hear what you're saying about the rebates in particular. I get that. What's really happening is that they are driving that price down and that is also being -- that rebate is being reflected in your premium. I guess you don't -- you don't want to say that, but that is true.</p><p end="4755" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4698">Can we talk about the premiums?</p><p end="4815" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4755">I --</p><p end="4815" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="4755">Look, get the government out of the way. There is something called Medicaid best price that limits the ability of insurers and companies to come together and say, hey, pay for performance. We're going to save you money, we're going to improve that patient's health, and that puts the onus on the drug manufacturer to perform, and lowers the barriers facing patients.</p><p end="4875" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="4815">I would say, there seems to be an assumption from the other side that anytime spending on medicines goes up, it's automatically a bad thing. But if spending goes up because we're curing disease and we're bringing new breakthrough treatments, that doesn't seem like a bad thing to me, particularly if these medicines can prevent the need to use other more costly health care services. But it seems like, from your side, that seems like a bad thing.</p><p end="4875" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4815">No --</p><p end="4936" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4875">And I -- I think we'd all agree -- and maybe we could all agree as a group, we definitely want more high value in the system. We definitely want drugs that work for --</p><p end="4936" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="4875">Look, you want the iPhone. You don't want the first cell phone. There's going to be incremental improvements. There are going to be things that are not perfect cures, and you want to pay for them too, right? You want people to have advantages and get better. You're not going to say to them, "Wait until there's a cure, and until then, we're not going to treat you."</p><p end="5056" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4936">I want to thank everyone for this fantastic debate and thank the folks who we are arguing vigorously with. I think we come back -- come to a place where we all want higher value in the system, but we have essential questions like how do we have a system in which a drug, the drug price, goes up over time, not goes down. We've looked at these very famous cases recently, and I think that tells you that when a drug has existed for a while, it's been on the market, it gets a new company entering in, buying it, and then driving up the price, not driving down the price.</p><p end="5056" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4936">And I appreciate that is not -- that is an exception, that's not the rule, but that exception tells you this market is not working properly. And from a market perspective, we do need to figure out a strategy to ensure that pharmaceutical companies who are responsible for these high prices that we are seeing in drugs have more competition, have more incentive, have more of the structure to not basically drive the highest price they can get away with, which is fueling the bipartisan concern we see on this issue.</p><p end="5056" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="4936">There is almost no issue I agree with Donald Trump on, but even he has called for Medicare negotiating drug prices because of the anger and the issue that people are seeing with this.</p><p end="5126" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="5056">Every other country has that level of negotiation. We are the only country that doesn't, and that is why I hope you will vote for the motion that shows that pharma is responsible for drug prices being so high.</p><p end="5126" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="5056">Thank you. I'm going to ask you for a moment to pretend that you're a billionaire. Your name is Mark Cuban. You're on "Shark Tank." And someone comes to you and they're pitching a new idea. It's a parking app. It'll cost them $100,000. They'll hire some coders and they'll be on the iTunes store in a year, maybe two years tops. There's no barrier to enter. You can get right out there and start earning money. The next person to pitch you is somebody who has a new idea for a drug, and it's going to cost them let's say $50 to $100,000,000 just to get through human clinical trials for the FDA and then there is an 88 percent chance that in 10 years it'll be a flop.</p><p end="5200" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="5126">Which investment are you going to make? That is the challenge that we're facing. Look, the FDA is the biggest barrier here. It's the barrier in generic drugs. It's a barrier to more innovative medicines. We need to find ways to bring more effective medicines to market less expensively so we can have both incremental and breakthrough innovations and more of all of the above and then tie them to the performance in the market. Because our biggest problem, as I spoke at the beginning, is not the drug price, it is the illness and the death and the disability that we all grapple with. And so the fact that we have very low Alzheimer's drug spending right now because we have no effective treatments is not a cause for celebration. It should be a cause for alarm. So, I agree with Zeke that we need to tie more to value, but so many of our federal regulations prohibit pricing to value.</p><p end="5200" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Howard" start="5126">Micromanage who gets what price and who can do what, and that is one of the biggest things standing in front of us, especially the FDA's drug regulations that make it so difficult to innovate and so expensive to innovate. And if we change pricing without changing how we innovate, all we're going to wind up is with fewer drugs and a drug that you don&#8217;t have for a serious disease is infinitely expensive because you can't buy it.</p><p end="5418" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="5346">Thank you, and thank you for having me tonight. I want to reiterate; drug spending is not the reason why we're seeing large increases in health care spending. Over the next decade, we're expected to spend an additional $2.4 trillion on health care. That's a lot of money. 15 percent of that is expected to be as a result of drugs. But in that next decade, it's possible that we're going to see new medicines come to market that, for the first time, actually treat Alzheimer's disease. We're going to see medicines that add to our war chest of medicines in oncology. The progress that we can make over the next decade is significant, and I would argue, it's worth that 15 extra percent in health spending costs. Why is it worth it? Because today, there are millions of patients today that are clinging on hope. They're clinging that -- hoping that our industry is able to bring something to market for a disease that ails them.</p><p end="5486" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="5418">Two years ago, I lost my mother to ALS, it&#8217;s a devastating disease, where there is no treatment, there is no cure -- and quite honestly, today, there is no hope. And for patients, whether they have ALS, or Parkinson's, or Alzheimer's, or cancer -- I don't know another solution than innovation progressing in the future. We have done that in HIV-AIDS. We've done it in Hepatitis C. And we're now at a point -- and we're on the cusp of doing it in many other areas. But we have to have the ability to move on. I think 15 percent of our health care dollar devoted to some of the biggest and boldest advancements we see in health care is well-worth it. We talked today a lot about prescription drug spending growth. We didn't talk at all about the 85 percent of health spending growth in every other area of our health care sector. We didn't question why the cost of a procedure goes up year after year after year.</p><p end="5486" is_meta="false" speaker="Lori Reilly" start="5418">That's a worthwhile debate to have. I'm not afraid to talk about drug costs, but let's talk about all health care costs, and how do we get to real solutions.</p><p end="5578" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="5545">Oh, no.</p><p end="5578" is_meta="false" speaker="Neera Tanden" start="5545">No.</p></transcript></debate>