<debate duration="6286" url="https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/buy-americanhire-american-policies-will-backfire"><speakers><speaker name="Jagdish Bhagwati" position="for"><description>University Professor of Economics and Law, at Columbia University and Senior Fellow in International Economics at the Council on Foreign Relations</description><bio>Bhagwati is a University Professor of Economics and Law, at Columbia University and senior fellow in International Economics at the Council on Foreign... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Douglas Irwin" position="for"><description>Robert E. Maxwell Professor of Arts and Sciences in the Department of Economics at Dartmouth College</description><bio>Douglas is the Robert E. Maxwell Professor of Arts and Sciences in the Department of Economics at Dartmouth College.Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Susan Schwab" position="for"><description>United States Trade Representative (USTR) from 2006-2009</description><bio>Schwab served as United States Trade Representative (USTR) from 2006-2009. As USTR, Ambassador Schwab was a member of President George W. Bush's cabinet... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Jeff Madrick" position="against"><description>Leading Economic Analyst and Editor of Challenge Magazine</description><bio>A former economics columnist for The New York Times, and current Editor of Challenge Magazine, Jeff Madrick is a regular contributor to The New York... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="John R. MacArthur" position="against"><description>President and Publisher of Harper's Magazine</description><bio>John is president and publisher of Harper's Magazine, the oldest continuously published monthly magazine in America. He has served in this role since... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Leo Gerard" position="against"><description>International President of the United Steelworkers</description><bio>Leo is International President of the United Steelworkers, the dominant union in paper, forestry products, steel, aluminum, tire and rubber, glass... Read More</bio></speaker></speakers><results><result against="20" for="56" submitters="live" undecided="23" when="before" /><result against="14" for="71" submitters="live" undecided="14" when="after" /><result for="100" submitters="online" when="before" /><result for="100" submitters="online" when="after" /></results><transcript /></debate>