<debate duration="5919" url="https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/courts-not-campuses-should-decide-sexual-assault-cases"><speakers><speaker name="Jed Rubenfeld" position="for"><description>Professor, Yale Law School</description><bio>Jed Rubenfeld is the Robert R. Slaughter Professor of Law at Yale Law School. His subjects are constitutional law, privacy, First Amendment, and criminal... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Jeannie Suk" position="for"><description>Professor, Harvard Law School</description><bio>Jeannie Suk is a professor of law at Harvard Law School, with expertise in criminal law and procedure, sexual assault, and Title IX. She has published... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Michelle Anderson" position="against"><description>Dean, CUNY School of Law</description><bio>Michelle Anderson, dean at CUNY School of Law, is a leading scholar on rape law. A member of the American Law Institute, she is an adviser to its... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Stephen Schulhofer" position="against"><description>Professor, NYU School of Law</description><bio>Stephen Schulhofer, the Robert B. McKay Professor of Law at New York University School of Law, is one of the nation&#146;s most distinguished scholars... Read More</bio></speaker></speakers><results><result against="12" for="56" submitters="live" undecided="32" when="before" /><result against="31" for="56" submitters="live" undecided="13" when="after" /><result for="87" submitters="online" undecided="12" when="before" /><result against="49" for="50" submitters="online" when="after" /></results><transcript><p end="600" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="544">Well, I actually don't think so. No. But look, this is an issue that everybody feels very</p><p end="600" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="544">strongly and personally about.</p><p end="664" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="600">I'm the father of two girls on college campuses. I feel strongly about it too. That's why</p><p end="664" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="600">it's so important to have debates like this one.</p><p end="664" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="600">My partner is professor of law at Harvard University, Jeannie Suk.</p><p end="664" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="600">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="664" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="600">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="664" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="600">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 6 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="664" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="600">They feel very personally about it. It's also very political for them. And it's also about the</p><p end="664" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="600">institutions that they inhabit, so that's a recipe for very strong feelings and very strong</p><p end="664" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="600">disagreements.</p><p end="719" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="664">I think it does. Over the past decade, the uniform code of military justice has had three</p><p end="719" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="664">versions of a definition of rape and sexual assault. So, this is a very complex issue.</p><p end="719" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="664">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="719" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="664">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="719" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="664">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 7 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="719" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="664">The brilliant Stephen Schulhofer.</p><p end="784" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="719">Sure, Title IX is the federal law that requires colleges and universities that receive</p><p end="784" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="719">federal funds to prevent racial and sexual harassment of their students. And that's why</p><p end="784" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="719">colleges have an obligation to address racial and sexual violence against students on</p><p end="784" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="719">their campuses.</p><p end="784" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="719">Sorry.</p><p end="784" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="719">It's a part of it. Yes.</p><p end="899" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="843">Thank you. And welcome to the second most important debate happening in America</p><p end="899" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="843">tonight.</p><p end="899" is_meta="true" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="843">laughter</p><p end="899" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="843">It's a -- it's a deep honor to be here, and I want to thank the organizers and also you, the</p><p end="899" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="843">audience, for coming. So, yes, one of my daughters is a college sophomore.</p><p end="961" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="899">The other just started law school. I'm very concerned about keeping our campuses safe</p><p end="961" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="899">from sexual assault. That's a goal that everyone on this stage shares. But the way to</p><p end="961" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="899">achieve that goal is not by having colleges conduct rape trials when they're incompetent</p><p end="961" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="899">to do it. I'm about to use some strong words. I wouldn't do it except that this is the</p><p end="961" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="899">reality, and we need to face it. As the result of campus sexual assault trials, actual</p><p end="961" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="899">rapists all over the country are going free to rape again, while innocent people -- it's</p><p end="961" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="899">impossible to know how many. But I'm talking about people who haven't committed</p><p end="961" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="899">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="961" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="899">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="961" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="899">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 9 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="961" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="899">any sexual assault at all -- are being found guilty and having their lives wrecked by an</p><p end="961" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="899">error ridden, unreliable process that's filled with conflicts of interest and violations of</p><p end="961" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="899">due process, all of it covered by a thick layer of non-transparency. Now, my partner,</p><p end="961" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="899">Jeannie, is going to cover the serious due process violations, so I'm going to talk to you</p><p end="961" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="899">about the basic competency and neutrality and transparency issues. But there's</p><p end="961" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="899">something extremely important to both Jeannie and me.</p><p end="1020" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="961">I want to say it first, that this is not, for us, a debate between the rights of the accused</p><p end="1020" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="961">versus the rights of the victim. An incompetent process produces errors on both</p><p end="1020" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="961">sides. It's unfair to both victims and the accused. The errors run in both directions, and</p><p end="1020" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="961">I will give you examples of those in a moment. But first, just some quick background on</p><p end="1020" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="961">how we got to where we are today. In 2011, the federal government sent a letter to</p><p end="1020" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="961">every college and university in the country telling them that if they didn't start trying</p><p end="1020" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="961">rape cases they would lose hundreds of millions of dollars in defunding penalties, and</p><p end="1020" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="961">forcing us to comply with a set of procedures dictated by the government, including, for</p><p end="1020" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="961">example, lowering the standard of proof. Now, I'm sure this letter was well</p><p end="1020" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="961">intentioned. But the problem is that college trials totally lack the necessary expertise,</p><p end="1020" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="961">neutrality and transparency. Let me start with competence. The primary forensic tool</p><p end="1020" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="961">in a rape case -- you've probably heard of it -- it's a rape kit. It's basically a medical</p><p end="1020" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="961">forensic examination of the victim.</p><p end="1081" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1020">Now, most college personnel don't even know what a rape kit is. Or say a woman</p><p end="1081" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1020">believes she was the victim of a date rape drug. Say she was the victim. That kind of</p><p end="1081" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1020">case requires a laboratory toxicology result. That's how you make that case. Most</p><p end="1081" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1020">colleges do not run such laboratories and can't do that. A recent college rape case was</p><p end="1081" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1020">decided by a panel of three judges, one person from engineering, one from food</p><p end="1081" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1020">services, and one foreign exchange student. In another case, an accused male student</p><p end="1081" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1020">was essentially acquitted not because he was found innocent, but because he broke</p><p end="1081" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1020">down at the hearing and admitted his alcoholism problem. The woman accuser was</p><p end="1081" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1020">stunned to see her rapist sitting in class with her the next week. At Stanford, the</p><p end="1081" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1020">teaching manual for rape judges includes an article saying that if the accused act -- if the</p><p end="1081" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1020">accused acts as if he's the victim, that's an indicator of guilt. Another indicator of guilt is</p><p end="1081" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1020">if he, quote, "Acts logical and persuasive." This kind of --</p><p end="1081" is_meta="true" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1020">laughter</p><p end="1081" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1020">I'm not kidding.</p><p end="1141" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1081">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="1141" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1081">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="1141" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1081">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 10 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="1141" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1081">This kind of incompetent decision making is leading to miscarriages of justice of a kind</p><p end="1141" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1081">you wouldn't imagine in America. And how about impartiality? In our courts, we have a</p><p end="1141" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1081">process we've worked out for centuries to ensure that our judges and juries are</p><p end="1141" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1081">disinterested, that they don't know the parties, don't know anybody who does know the</p><p end="1141" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1081">parties, that they're not subject to rumors and pressures. In college rape trials, it's the</p><p end="1141" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1081">opposite. These are people from the same community. They are subject to</p><p end="1141" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1081">pressures. They sometimes know the parties. They sometimes know people who do</p><p end="1141" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1081">know the parties. Athlete -- athletic coaches decide if athletes committed</p><p end="1141" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1081">rape. Students decide cases involving students. Now, again, these conflicts, they hurt</p><p end="1141" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1081">victims and accused alike. In some cases, colleges have a huge incentive to sweep rape</p><p end="1141" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1081">cases under the rug, to cover them up. And that can lead to guilty people being found</p><p end="1141" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1081">innocent. In other cases, it's the opposite. Especially today, colleges are feeling a lot of</p><p end="1141" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1081">pressure under threat from the federal government to show how seriously they take</p><p end="1141" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1081">these cases and to make an example.</p><p end="1203" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1141">And that can lead to innocent people being found guilty, to be expelled, and if their</p><p end="1203" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1141">names leak out, to be branded with a stigma that they have no way to ever clear</p><p end="1203" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1141">themselves of. Compare this to what happens when a murder takes place on a college</p><p end="1203" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1141">campus. We don't hold campus homicide trials. We all expect the police, the DA, the</p><p end="1203" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1141">FBI and the courts to take charge. Rape is a crime as serious as homicide. It's not like</p><p end="1203" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1141">plagiarism or cheating on an exam. That's the kind of thing college disciplinary panels</p><p end="1203" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1141">are good at. We should treat rape with the same seriousness as we do other major</p><p end="1203" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1141">crimes. But worst of all, I haven't even gotten to the worst thing of all. What happens</p><p end="1203" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1141">when the college rape trial works just the way it's supposed to work; when an actual</p><p end="1203" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1141">rapist is found guilty? What happens next? Let me ask you a question. If you had proof</p><p end="1203" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1141">that somebody in your neighborhood had committed an act of rape, what was the --</p><p end="1203" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1141">what's the worst possible thing you could do? Here's the worst thing: Push that person</p><p end="1203" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1141">out of your neighborhood, but never tell anybody else what happened.</p><p end="1261" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1203">Keep his name confidential. That literally is what colleges do in these cases. They expel</p><p end="1261" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1203">the student but keep his identity a total secret because the college process, unlike a</p><p end="1261" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1203">court, has no transparency. It's all covered with confidentiality. And I can't stress how</p><p end="1261" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1203">important this is. Some empirical studies out there have suggested that up to 90</p><p end="1261" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1203">percent of college rapes are being committed by fewer than 5 percent of college men, a</p><p end="1261" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1203">relative handful of serial rapists, averaging over six rapes each. Yet colleges, when they</p><p end="1261" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1203">catch these serial rapists, simply push them out of their neighborhood, leaving them</p><p end="1261" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1203">free to commit sexual assault elsewhere, their secret kept safe within the college</p><p end="1261" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1203">bureaucracy. That's why we need courts to handle these cases. Now finally, it's critical</p><p end="1261" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1203">to acknowledge that the courts are far from perfect, the police are far from perfect. Too</p><p end="1261" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1203">often in the past they have failed victims of sexual assault.</p><p end="1261" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1203">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="1261" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1203">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="1261" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1203">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 11 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="1323" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1261">We can do better. We have to do better. And in the end, it's not courts or colleges, one</p><p end="1323" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1261">or the other. That's a kind of debating artificiality. We all know that both have a role to</p><p end="1323" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1261">play. There's a huge amount colleges can do, but they should be focused on education</p><p end="1323" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1261">and prevention, which they can do well, not on adjudication which they can't. Ideally,</p><p end="1323" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1261">we bridge the gap. Get colleges and police working together. That's what I've</p><p end="1323" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1261">advocated, and it's happening. Here in New York, there's just been the creation of a</p><p end="1323" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1261">special sexual assault enforcement unit, first of its kind in the country. It's specifically</p><p end="1323" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1261">designed to go out and work with both colleges and local police to help them get</p><p end="1323" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1261">together and do their jobs better. But the primary responsibility for investigating and</p><p end="1323" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1261">trying rape cases has to be with police and courts. That's what we're asking you to vote</p><p end="1323" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1261">for. A vote for our side of this debate is a vote that not campuses, but courts should be</p><p end="1323" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1261">the primary place where rape trials are conducted. And we urge you --</p><p end="1323" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="1261">-- to vote that way.</p><p end="1380" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1323">Courts should decide sexual assault cases when a victim reports to the police, when the</p><p end="1380" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1323">police take it seriously and investigate, when a prosecutor takes it seriously and pursues</p><p end="1380" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1323">it, and the case finally lands in a court of law. In these circumstances, courts should</p><p end="1380" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1323">decide sexual assault cases. No one disagrees. The only thing this debate is about is</p><p end="1380" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1323">between two commas, "Not campuses." The resolution strips jurisdiction from</p><p end="1380" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1323">campuses to also decide sexual assault cases.</p><p end="1380" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1323">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="1380" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1323">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="1380" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1323">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 12 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="1443" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1380">That's what we're talking about tonight. Now, colleges and universities exist to</p><p end="1443" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1380">generate and transmit knowledge. And they cannot do that job unless they have a safe</p><p end="1443" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1380">learning environment in which to do it. They also cannot single out sexual assault cases</p><p end="1443" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1380">and push them to the criminal courts, unlike all the other cases they deal with, without</p><p end="1443" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1380">harming the learning environment and without violating the civil rights of students. My</p><p end="1443" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1380">colleague, Stephen Schulhofer will talk about the problems that happen when cases are</p><p end="1443" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1380">pushed to the criminal law involuntarily. For now, I'll just note that there's a reason why</p><p end="1443" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1380">95 percent of sexual assault victims on campus never report to the police. They do not</p><p end="1443" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1380">believe that justice will be served. A college student reported having been raped to the</p><p end="1443" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1380">New York City police department. The officer scoffed. "You invited him into your dorm</p><p end="1443" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1380">room. That's not the legal definition of rape." Another officer chimed in. "For every</p><p end="1443" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1380">single rape I've had, I've had 20 reports that are total bullshit."</p><p end="1504" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1443">That's not from 1970. That story is from 2014. The fact is that bias against victims of</p><p end="1504" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1443">sexual assault has a well-documented, 200 year history in the criminal justice</p><p end="1504" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1443">system. But even when the system harbors no bias whatsoever, campuses must be able</p><p end="1504" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1443">to decide sexual assault cases. Courts and campuses have different interests in these</p><p end="1504" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1443">cases and different remedies. Let me explain. When a campus sexual assault happens,</p><p end="1504" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1443">a victim needs immediate safety and protection. Campuses can take protective</p><p end="1504" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1443">measures to ensure a safe educational environment; stagger classes, move someone</p><p end="1504" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1443">from a dorm, issue reprimands, suspend students. These remedies are not available in</p><p end="1504" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1443">the court. The university's role is unavoidable because campuses must preserve</p><p end="1504" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1443">students' ability to learn. Since the early part of the 19th century, colleges and</p><p end="1504" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1443">universities have always disciplined students independent of the criminal law.</p><p end="1560" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1504">They've had to. Throughout time, students incite riots, they assault, they plagiarize,</p><p end="1560" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1504">they harass. Some of these acts are criminal, some are not. But just to clarify,</p><p end="1560" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1504">campuses are not prosecuting criminal charges in trials. They're pursuing violations of</p><p end="1560" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1504">their own disciplinary codes, which do not lead to criminal convictions or</p><p end="1560" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1504">imprisonment. And colleges cannot wait around to see if the police are interested in the</p><p end="1560" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1504">case. Let me give you an example. In 2013 a college fraternity hazing ritual in</p><p end="1560" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1504">Pennsylvania ended in the death of a pledge by blunt force trauma to the head. The</p><p end="1560" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1504">coroner ruled the death a homicide, but the prosecutor did not pursue charges until</p><p end="1560" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1504">Monday, almost two years later. Now, the university had an independent interest in the</p><p end="1560" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1504">case. It pursued immediate disciplinary action against the students who hazed and</p><p end="1560" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1504">killed the other student. And it suspended them.</p><p end="1560" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1504">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="1560" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1504">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="1560" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1504">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 13 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="1624" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1560">Now, fraternity hazing and homicide are serious crimes, just like rape is a serious crime,</p><p end="1624" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1560">but no one in that case said, "Oh, the courts should be the only one to handle the</p><p end="1624" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1560">case. The colleges should get out of the way." Whether or not criminal charges ever</p><p end="1624" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1560">emerge in a case, colleges must decide cases to maintain a safe learning environment,</p><p end="1624" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1560">even more so with sexual assault. Title IX is a federal civil rights statute that prohibits</p><p end="1624" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1560">gender discrimination in educational institutions. And campus sexual assault is a form</p><p end="1624" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1560">of discrimination that denies a victim an equal education. Many sexual assault victims</p><p end="1624" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1560">suffer serious consequences, depression, eating disorders, suicidal ideation, social</p><p end="1624" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1560">withdrawal. These reactions impair their ability to attend class and focus, to pass their</p><p end="1624" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1560">classes, to maintain their time in school, to remain in school. As a result, the United</p><p end="1624" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1560">States Department of Education's Office for Civil Rights requires schools to take</p><p end="1624" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1560">immediate and effective steps to end sexual violence.</p><p end="1685" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1624">It requires equal treatment of accuser and accused and demands adequate, reliable, and</p><p end="1685" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1624">impartial investigation of complaints. Since 2011, campuses have begun pursuing these</p><p end="1685" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1624">cases in earnest. Most colleges are working to implement Title IX in a fair and equitable</p><p end="1685" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1624">way. You don't hear about them. Some campuses are failing, however. They're either</p><p end="1685" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1624">denying victims their rights under Title IX to an equitable education or they're actually</p><p end="1685" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1624">violating students' due process during the disciplinary proceedings in ways that Title IX</p><p end="1685" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1624">does not require and the Constitution will not stand. In these later cases, students are</p><p end="1685" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1624">suing, as you heard. Where colleges have gone wrong, these young men are</p><p end="1685" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1624">winning. And these process issues can be worked out intelligently through the courts</p><p end="1685" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1624">without taking a meat cleaver to the problem and abolishing or cutting off campus</p><p end="1685" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1624">jurisdiction entirely.</p><p end="1749" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1685">Let's circle back to the differences between the criminal justice system and Title IX</p><p end="1749" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1685">quickly. The criminal justice system is focused on punishment, incarceration,</p><p end="1749" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1685">retribution. Title IX by contrast is a civil rights statute. And like most civil rights</p><p end="1749" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1685">statutes, it's focused on equality, in this case, educational equality. The criminal justice</p><p end="1749" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1685">system cannot insure equality, and it cannot remedy inequality. Campuses have to</p><p end="1749" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1685">insure equality. They must provide a safe learning environment to generate and</p><p end="1749" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1685">transmit knowledge. Now, I want to end by noting that this debate resolution is actually</p><p end="1749" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1685">worse than the House Republican bill that is pending right now in Congress with the</p><p end="1749" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1685">Orwellian title, "The Safe Campus Act." That bill would prohibit campuses from</p><p end="1749" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1685">investigating sexual assault unless the victim reports to the police, and it's being heavily</p><p end="1749" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1685">promoted by fraternities. The bill has received near universal opposition from groups</p><p end="1749" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1685">that work with actual sexual assault victims as well as opposition from many groups that</p><p end="1749" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1685">represent colleges and universities, like the Association of American Universities.</p><p end="1749" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1685">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="1749" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1685">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="1749" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1685">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 14 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="1807" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1749">The American Council on Education has expressed grave reservation about any</p><p end="1807" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1749">legislation that would limit our ability to insure a safe campus. The effect of this</p><p end="1807" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1749">resolution is to eviscerate colleges' ability to insure a safe campus. It would also violate</p><p end="1807" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="1749">students' civil rights, and it has to be wrong. Please vote, "No." Thank you.</p><p end="1807" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1749">I think it's important for us to see that tonight's debate is not just about courts versus</p><p end="1807" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1749">campuses.</p><p end="1865" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1807">And it's not just about sexual assault. It is a debate about the equality of men and</p><p end="1865" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1807">women in our society. In college, I was a rape counselor and an activist, and I've spent</p><p end="1865" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1807">my entire life as a feminist on campuses. I have a daughter and a son. And I was</p><p end="1865" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1807">optimistic to see colleges take sexual assault more seriously than they had in the past.</p><p end="1865" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1807">But the disaster we have seen unfolding around us has made me lose faith. My points</p><p end="1865" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1807">tonight will focus on fairness, process, and the connection to equality. What campuses</p><p end="1865" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1807">are doing under pressure from the Department of Education is hurting the cause of</p><p end="1865" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1807">gender equality. Campus tribunals use procedures that lack basic fairness and often</p><p end="1865" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1807">reach inaccurate outcomes. What happens? You're told there's a sexual misconduct</p><p end="1865" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1807">complaint against you. But they don't say what it's about or show you the complaint.</p><p end="1922" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1865">They don't tell you the evidence or the facts that they're gathering, who the witnesses</p><p end="1922" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1865">are, or what they've said. If you're allowed to bring an attorney, which you might not be,</p><p end="1922" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1865">your lawyer is barred from speaking. If they give you a live hearing, which they may not,</p><p end="1922" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1865">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="1922" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1865">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="1922" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1865">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 15 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="1922" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1865">you can't question the accuser or witnesses. People who weren't even there are asked</p><p end="1922" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1865">to give opinions on what happened. Terribly leading questions are asked. And when</p><p end="1922" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1865">your attorney objects, she is told that if she speaks again, she'll be ejected. After you're</p><p end="1922" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1865">found responsible and suspended, they don't give you a copy of the investigative report,</p><p end="1922" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1865">saying that they can't because of student privacy. The investigation and the adjudication</p><p end="1922" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1865">may be handled by the same person, and the appeal is to that person's boss. So,</p><p end="1922" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1865">everyone is invested in defending the previous actions of the school. When you appeal,</p><p end="1922" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1865">you're told you can't challenge the panel's factual findings.</p><p end="1982" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1922">And all this is happening because if you're not found guilty, the school fears that the</p><p end="1982" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1922">Department of Education will open an investigation that would cost a lot of money to</p><p end="1982" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1922">deal with and jeopardize its federal funding. In just the past three months, no fewer</p><p end="1982" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1922">than five different courts have ruled for students on claims that their school used unfair</p><p end="1982" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1922">procedures, including things that I've just described. The shocking disregard for what</p><p end="1982" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1922">Americans know are essentials of fair process deeply harms the cause of taking sexual</p><p end="1982" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1922">violence seriously. It reinforces society's skepticism toward rape victims. It causes</p><p end="1982" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1922">everyone to doubt that men disciplined for sexual assault are actually guilty. That</p><p end="1982" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1922">aggravates the serious problem that we all want to address. And it harms the fight for</p><p end="1982" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1922">gender equality. To make matters worse, many schools are now stretching the concept</p><p end="1982" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1922">of what sexual assault is far beyond reasonable recognition.</p><p end="2042" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1982">If you have sexual contact without an explicit agreement for every stage of a sexual</p><p end="2042" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1982">interaction, that might be considered non-consensual. It's a great idea to make sure that</p><p end="2042" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1982">each partner is excited about going forward, but move from kissing to touching without</p><p end="2042" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1982">pausing for an explicit agreement -- and it can be sexual assault, even if the other</p><p end="2042" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1982">person is equally participating in it. Some schools even define consent to mean not only</p><p end="2042" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1982">affirmative, but enthusiastic -- even "creative" and "imaginative" agreement. It may be</p><p end="2042" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1982">funny, but anything else is sexual assault. It's obvious that sex with a person</p><p end="2042" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1982">incapacitated by alcohol is rape. That is obvious. But schools are now disciplining</p><p end="2042" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1982">students when the sexual contact is under the influence of alcohol. All this means that</p><p end="2042" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="1982">most sexual encounters are violating the rules.</p><p end="2107" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2042">So, when one person is kicked out for this and branded a rapist, it feels arbitrary to both</p><p end="2107" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2042">men and to women. It is truly bizarre to lump these cases together with rapes and treat</p><p end="2107" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2042">them as sexual assaults. Yet, these are most of the cases that colleges are adjudicating</p><p end="2107" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2042">today. This came about because of a desire to protect women from coercion. The idea</p><p end="2107" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2042">was that men should seek permission, not just wait for women to object to sex. But</p><p end="2107" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2042">schools are sending all the wrong messages about women's capacity to be equal,</p><p end="2107" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2042">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="2107" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2042">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="2107" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2042">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 16 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="2107" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2042">mature, and independent. We can date these ideas to about 1880. Women are timid;</p><p end="2107" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2042">women are fragile. In the name of protecting college women and making campuses</p><p end="2107" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2042">safe, schools are signaling loudly that they do not see women as capable. I don't want</p><p end="2107" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2042">my daughter educated to think of herself that way. We need to refocus on what's</p><p end="2107" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2042">wrong with sexual violence and refuse these ancient ideas of women's incapacity.</p><p end="2170" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2107">Watered-down procedures and overly broad definitions of non-consent make a mockery</p><p end="2170" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2107">of a very serious problem and dishonor victims. Our opponents must convince you that</p><p end="2170" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2107">a rape on campus is different from a rape anywhere else. It is not. Criminal sexual</p><p end="2170" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2107">conduct anywhere deserves criminal response. And our opponents want you to accept</p><p end="2170" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2107">that a civil rights option means that it's okay to have lesser procedures. Even if the</p><p end="2170" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2107">stakes were civil, the process must be fair, and the stakes are effectively criminal. There</p><p end="2170" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2107">is, in fact, so much that campuses should do. It's disturbing to see the bulk of resources</p><p end="2170" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2107">going to pseudo investigations and trials. Schools should direct those resources to</p><p end="2170" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2107">working with law enforcement. The safety measures that Michelle was talking about,</p><p end="2170" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2107">those do not necessarily go hand in hand with an investigation and adjudication, a</p><p end="2170" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2107">decision about the responsibility and guilt of a party for committing a crime.</p><p end="2222" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2170">You can take safety measures, and campuses do all the time, without having pseudo</p><p end="2222" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2170">criminal trials. Schools can engage in rape education, they can address alcohol</p><p end="2222" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2170">consumption, and they can work hard to support victims. The answer to shame or</p><p end="2222" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2170">stigma about sexual assault is not a campus tribunal mired in secrecy and severe</p><p end="2222" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2170">conflicts of interest that is the confidence of nobody. We're going to look back on this</p><p end="2222" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2170">period as a mass panic when many people together lost their ability to think clearly</p><p end="2222" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2170">about sexual assault and squandered opportunities for promoting gender</p><p end="2222" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2170">equality. Campuses should not do shoddily what our courts have been designed over</p><p end="2222" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2170">generations to do; decide questions of responsibility and guilt for a crime based on</p><p end="2222" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2170">evidence.</p><p end="2280" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2222">You should not accept it. You should vote for the motion. Courts, not campuses should</p><p end="2280" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2222">decide sexual assault cases.</p><p end="2280" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2222">Thank you very much. Courts are certainly finding due process violations all over the</p><p end="2280" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2222">place. A lot of colleges have really botched this problem. But I'm very surprised to hear</p><p end="2280" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2222">professor Suk cite that as a reason for precluding campus discipline in all these</p><p end="2280" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2222">cases. We don't shut down the criminal courts just because appellate courts are finding</p><p end="2280" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2222">due process violations in criminal trials. And that happens a lot. So, these decisions</p><p end="2280" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2222">show that the system is working.</p><p end="2344" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2280">The Department of Education has overreached. Many colleges have overreached, and</p><p end="2344" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2280">courts are pushing back. The question we have to decide -- and we all agree that many</p><p end="2344" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2280">colleges have done a very poor job. The question that we're debating is whether to fix</p><p end="2344" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2280">the problem by requiring the colleges to do better or whether to prevent all campuses</p><p end="2344" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2280">from deciding these cases no matter how careful they are. The resolution would make a</p><p end="2344" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2280">criminal complaint the victim's only option, even when she doesn't want to go through</p><p end="2344" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2280">the stress of the criminal process herself and even when she doesn't want to impose</p><p end="2344" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2280">that on a classmate who may have mistreated her, but she doesn't want to see that</p><p end="2344" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2280">classmate convicted of a crime. Taking away the option of a campus remedy is</p><p end="2344" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2280">obviously bad for sexual assault victims. I don't think there's any possible question</p><p end="2344" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2280">about that. And what people are missing here is that sending all these cases to the</p><p end="2344" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2280">criminal courts is going to work out very badly for the accused students as well.</p><p end="2401" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2344">Suppose a student claims that one of her classmates pushed her onto a sofa, ignored</p><p end="2401" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2344">her protests and penetrated her? If a campus panel accepts her story, her classmate</p><p end="2401" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2344">might be suspended or even expelled. That could have life-altering consequences. But</p><p end="2401" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2344">expulsion is nothing compared to the impact of a criminal conviction for a sex</p><p end="2401" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2344">offense. The resolution seems to assume that a criminal conviction requires very clear</p><p end="2401" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2344">proof. The reality is actually not so reassuring. Trial lawyers know that proof beyond a</p><p end="2401" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2344">reasonable doubt isn't all it's cracked up to be. Victim testimony no longer requires any</p><p end="2401" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2344">corroboration or any proof of physical coercion. If the complainant testifies that she</p><p end="2401" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2344">said no, and the jury believes her, that's enough. That is proof beyond a reasonable</p><p end="2401" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2344">doubt. Of course, the jury has to be unanimous to convict. But it also has to be</p><p end="2401" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2344">unanimous to acquit.</p><p end="2401" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2344">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="2401" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2344">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="2401" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2344">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 18 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="2464" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2401">That's one reason why prosecutors typically file multiple charges, from rape down to</p><p end="2464" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2401">sexual contact, attempted contact and maybe a few more. So some jurors may have</p><p end="2464" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2401">doubts, others don't. And you typically see a compromised verdict. Jurors convict on a</p><p end="2464" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2401">minor charge, not even realizing that their verdict can still trigger a harsh sentence. But</p><p end="2464" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2401">it gets worse. Most criminal cases end in a plea bargain. And one reason is that a rape</p><p end="2464" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2401">conviction can mean more than 15 years in prison. If the prosecutor will accept a plea</p><p end="2464" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2401">to attempted rape or sexual contact, the sentence drops to only a year or two in</p><p end="2464" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2401">jail. That's a hard offer to refuse, even if the chance of conviction on that top count is</p><p end="2464" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2401">only 20 or 30 percent. So technically, you can't get a criminal conviction on a mere</p><p end="2464" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2401">preponderance of the evidence. But if the odds of a 15-year sentence are 50/50, that</p><p end="2464" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2401">becomes a pretty strong reason to plead guilty to the lesser offense.</p><p end="2530" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2464">And bingo, the student who might have faced discipline in a college proceeding, might</p><p end="2530" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2464">have been required to change his dorm or even leave school for a semester. That</p><p end="2530" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2464">student is now getting jail time and a criminal record without having any court hear any</p><p end="2530" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2464">evidence at all. That's the reality for the great majority of cases in our criminal</p><p end="2530" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2464">courts. What about less serious cases? Suppose a young man stares at a sophomore in</p><p end="2530" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2464">his calculus class, and he keeps making comments about her body? One day, he grabs</p><p end="2530" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2464">her butt in the hallway outside of class. That is sexual assault. But sending a contact</p><p end="2530" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2464">case like that to the police normally means complete inaction. I hope that's not the</p><p end="2530" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2464">resolution's hidden agenda, a world where a lesser sexual assault allegations aren't</p><p end="2530" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2464">pursued. But anyone supporting the allegation for that reason is going to get a rude</p><p end="2530" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2464">surprise if it were adopted, because if DAs didn't pursue these cases, which is what</p><p end="2530" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2464">usually happens now, how can colleges respond to disruption and sexual harassment?</p><p end="2578" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2530">It's not clear to me what the supporters of this resolution have in mind. When you put</p><p end="2578" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2530">thousands of adolescents together with raging hormones, poor judgment and easy</p><p end="2578" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2530">access to alcohol, some of them are going to be rude and aggressive. You can talk about</p><p end="2578" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2530">prevention programs, and I'm in favor of them too. But misconduct in that environment</p><p end="2578" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2530">is going to happen. And how exactly is a college supposed to respond to stupid, boorish</p><p end="2578" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2530">behavior, which is going to happen? Could the college suspend the student for his rude</p><p end="2578" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2530">comments because that's not a crime, but not be allowed to suspend him for actually</p><p end="2578" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2530">groping her? It doesn't make any sense. But otherwise, unless the DA pursues the case,</p><p end="2578" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2530">there couldn't be any sanction at all.</p><p end="2644" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2578">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="2644" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2578">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="2644" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2578">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 19 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="2644" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2578">And if the college can't discipline its students directly, it will have to pressure police and</p><p end="2644" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2578">local prosecutors to press criminal charges. So students who would never face the</p><p end="2644" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2578">criminal courts today, adolescents guilty of immaturity and poor judgment would find</p><p end="2644" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2578">themselves with a criminal record. No one should want that. But colleges will have to</p><p end="2644" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2578">insist on prosecution because they'd have no other basis for imposing sanctions. I think</p><p end="2644" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2578">professor Suk said, well, of course, the college can take some action. But does that</p><p end="2644" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2578">mean the college is going to be taking action without deciding what happened? That's a</p><p end="2644" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2578">kind of odd situation if you're opposing -- if you're supporting the resolution that</p><p end="2644" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2578">colleges can't decide these cases, but they can take action without deciding the case,</p><p end="2644" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2578">that's even worse than the situation we have now. And I haven't even mentioned sex</p><p end="2644" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2578">offender registration. Federal statute called SORNA establishes a national registry with</p><p end="2644" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2578">a current address, place of employment and photograph of every convicted sex</p><p end="2644" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2578">offender.</p><p end="2705" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2644">And it's readily available on the internet, and it's a federal felony for a sex offender to</p><p end="2705" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2644">fail to notify local police within three days of every change in residence. People assume</p><p end="2705" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2644">these laws only apply to predators who abuse little children, but they cover all sex</p><p end="2705" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2644">offenses, even low-level misdemeanors. So this resolution would be a disaster, not only</p><p end="2705" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2644">for colleges, but for accused students. They would get less due process in the criminal</p><p end="2705" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2644">courts, and we'd see more convictions with consequences far more severe than a</p><p end="2705" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2644">college disciplinary record. So that's why it's very important to vote against this</p><p end="2705" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2644">resolution. Thank you.</p><p end="2823" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="2771">Well, the college system has the advantage that it's not the police, and the public record</p><p end="2823" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="2771">of the --</p><p end="2823" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="2771">-- yeah, yeah.</p><p end="2882" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="2823">Right.</p><p end="2882" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="2823">Well, it's an important advantage. And campus systems vary quite a bit across the</p><p end="2882" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="2823">country. So some campuses will provide -- the main advantage for victims for the</p><p end="2882" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="2823">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="2882" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="2823">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="2882" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="2823">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 21 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="2882" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="2823">campus process is immediate process or fairly rapid, prompt process, and also a variety</p><p end="2882" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="2823">of remedies that are otherwise not available in court. So I emphasize that they can</p><p end="2882" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="2823">immediately change class schedules or move someone out of a dorm, essentially</p><p end="2882" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="2823">separating people who -- where there's an allegation of sexual assault, and they can do</p><p end="2882" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="2823">the kind of remedies that campuses can't engage -- or that courts can't engage in.</p><p end="2882" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2823">Yes, those are real things in terms of moving class schedules and dorm</p><p end="2882" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2823">arrangements. Actually, colleges are doing that even before the adjudication</p><p end="2882" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2823">investigations are completed.</p><p end="2939" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2882">That shows you that colleges feel empowered to just do that for the sake of student</p><p end="2939" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2882">safety or just to preserve good relations in the dorm or for the -- just in the best</p><p end="2939" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2882">interests of the students who are involved. They have all kinds of reasons to do things,</p><p end="2939" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2882">like, say, you can't go to this dorm, you have to move, and I think that, that shows you</p><p end="2939" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2882">it's not connected to whether the college is then going to have a -- an investigation, a</p><p end="2939" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2882">trial, a tribunal, and go through that whole --</p><p end="2939" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2882">I have to say, Jeannie -- I'm sorry to jump in here --</p><p end="2939" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2882">-- but I have to say I'm very confused about this. If I'm living in a dorm and I don't like</p><p end="2939" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2882">my roommate, I can't go to the college and say, "I want this person kicked out of the</p><p end="2939" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2882">dorm." You have to have a reason for that, and colleges can't be requiring a student to</p><p end="2939" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2882">drop a chemistry class or move out of his dorm or leave campus for a semester unless</p><p end="2939" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2882">they decide that there is a reason. So if --</p><p end="2939" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="2882">And that, that reason is credible.</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2939">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2939">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2939">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 22 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2939">-- exactly, that it's credible -- so they had -- if you're saying campuses should not decide</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2939">these cases but they should take action against the accused without making any</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="2939">decision and without having any process at all, that seems rather an odd idea to me.</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2939">I think there are lots of different ways to make decisions. I think there are decisions</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2939">made for all kinds of reasons. One -- the decision that we're talking about in this</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2939">debate, decide sexual assault cases, is a determination of responsibility and guilt for</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2939">what could be a crime. People do have disputes, like you're talking about, in their</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2939">dorms. They do go to their resident advisor and say, "I'm having a problem," and</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2939">sometimes they're brought in to have a mediation, to have a talk, to resolve, and they</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2939">could -- colleges can advise and guide. And actually the Department of Education says,</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2939">when it comes to the sexual misconduct matters, that's not even allowed. You have to</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="2939">go through some kind adjudicative process to decide the guilt of the party.</p><p end="3063" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3001">Sure. Well, I guess I'm just wondering, why is sexual assault different than any other</p><p end="3063" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3001">offense that's committed on campus? In other words, these kinds of offenses routinely</p><p end="3063" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3001">go through adjudicative processes. And there's no reason to pull sexual assault as</p><p end="3063" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3001">opposed to any number of other kinds of cases, and say, "Well, that particular one has</p><p end="3063" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3001">to go to the criminal courts, but the hazing case that led to the death of a student, or</p><p end="3063" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3001">the plagiarism case, or an assault case, those can be adjudicated through a disciplinary</p><p end="3063" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3001">process that is routine?"</p><p end="3063" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3001">Well, I don't think that's a fair characterization, Michelle. Look, it's really rare -- really</p><p end="3063" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3001">rare to have colleges adjudicate a homicide. That almost never happens. It's really rare -</p><p end="3063" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3001">- almost never happens for colleges to try and adjudicate an act of arson. Rape is as</p><p end="3063" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3001">serious a crime as homicide and arson. We do not typically -- we have never typically</p><p end="3063" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3001">adjudicated major serious crimes like that.</p><p end="3117" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3063">Plagiarism, yes, of course. Colleges are good at that. They know about that. Hazing?</p><p end="3117" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3063">Hazing, fraternity stuff, that's a college problem. It makes sense for colleges to deal with</p><p end="3117" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3063">hazing. But we are talking about treating rape very differently through this Title IX</p><p end="3117" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3063">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="3117" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3063">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="3117" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3063">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 23 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="3117" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3063">process, not treating it the same. Treating it the same would be an expectation that the</p><p end="3117" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3063">police, and the courts, and the Das, and the FBI come in an investigate this. And I do -- I</p><p end="3117" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3063">need to say one more thing about our resolution. It's very important. For some reason,</p><p end="3117" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3063">the other side is trying to characterize the resolution before you as barring colleges from</p><p end="3117" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3063">doing anything about this, barring them from hearing these kind of claims. That's not</p><p end="3117" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3063">true. That's not what the resolution does. The resolution says, "Courts, not campuses,</p><p end="3117" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3063">should decide." Not barring them. The question is for you all to send a message that the</p><p end="3117" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3063">body that should decide these cases are courts, not campuses, for all the reasons we</p><p end="3117" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3063">have said.</p><p end="3179" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3117">It's -- as John said at the beginning of this debate, the question before you, "Is it</p><p end="3179" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3117">preferable for courts to be deciding?" And in an ideal world, if colleges could do it just as</p><p end="3179" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3117">well, fine. But unfortunately, it's been a disaster. And the right answer is that courts</p><p end="3179" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3117">should be the ones deciding.</p><p end="3179" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3117">Yeah. I think that we read the resolution slightly differently. And I think that as a</p><p end="3179" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3117">normative matter, the victim should decide whether or not she or he wishes to pursue a</p><p end="3179" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3117">criminal claim with the police. And that is what should happen. And when the victim</p><p end="3179" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3117">feels that she will be received or he will be received appropriately, and the justice can</p><p end="3179" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3117">be served through the criminal justice system, that's the appropriate route for it to go.</p><p end="3179" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3117">But there should also be an option for the victim to receive different kinds of redress</p><p end="3179" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3117">through the campus justice system and through a process that provides different</p><p end="3179" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3117">remedies and allows for immediate safety on campus.</p><p end="3243" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3179">If I might add, there also -- I -- Professor Rubenfeld really lost me there completely,</p><p end="3243" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3179">because if all the -- all that you're arguing in favor of is that courts should do it, but</p><p end="3243" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3179">you're not opposed to campuses doing it, I don't understand your opening remarks with</p><p end="3243" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3179">all the criticism of the lack of due process, and the conflicts of interest, and everything</p><p end="3243" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3179">else. We acknowledge that that happens. And we think it should be fixed. But I think the</p><p end="3243" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3179">thrust of your arguments is that campuses have no business deciding these cases. And</p><p end="3243" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3179">we think that they -- not only they do have a business. They must deal with the situation</p><p end="3243" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3179">where, for example, a student in our chemistry lab keeps getting groped by someone at</p><p end="3243" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3179">the next lab table. They have to deal with that. And it's not desirable to send that case</p><p end="3243" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3179">to a criminal court, where some immature adolescent is going to wind up on a sex</p><p end="3243" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3179">offender registry --</p><p end="3243" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3179">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="3243" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3179">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="3243" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3179">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 24 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="3243" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3179">Well, Stephen, if I might, you know, I was really -- no, the resolution is that courts should</p><p end="3243" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3179">be doing it, because they're the ones that have the competence--</p><p end="3243" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3179">I think -- but if I could respond to the --</p><p end="3306" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3243">If I could add about the groping problem.</p><p end="3306" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3243">This is the problem of mixing together -- look, by sexual assault, this term, I understand</p><p end="3306" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3243">to mean rape, okay?</p><p end="3359" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3306">What I have said throughout all my arguments, and this is what Jeannie was saying, too,</p><p end="3359" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3306">is those are the cases the courts should be trying, not campuses. Now, what's</p><p end="3359" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3306">happening is that this term is getting expanded, as Jeannie was saying to mean -- cover a</p><p end="3359" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3306">whole lot of other things. And Stephen's argument about this groping thing is, you</p><p end="3359" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3306">wouldn't want that in a criminal court. Police aren't going to prosecute. If courts -- if</p><p end="3359" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3306">campuses want to have a code against offensive touching, sexual misconduct, sexual</p><p end="3359" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3306">harassment, sure, those are things that campuses could do well. And they should be</p><p end="3359" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3306">able to do that. We are talking about sexual assault here. Let's not expand that term so</p><p end="3359" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3306">that it means all kinds of things -- other things and confuse the issue.</p><p end="3422" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3359">Well, sure. I think, first, I don't want to quibble about terminology or cite a statute. But</p><p end="3422" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3359">any criminal lawyer will tell you that if a young woman on the subway is groped in the</p><p end="3422" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3359">butt or in the breasts, any unwanted touching like that is a sexual assault. There is no</p><p end="3422" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3359">question about that.</p><p end="3422" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3359">That is a crime.</p><p end="3422" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3359">She could go to the cops.</p><p end="3422" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3359">That is a terrific question, John. It's a terrific question, and it's crucial to all of this,</p><p end="3422" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3359">because on campus, you're talking about the victim's ability to pursue her education in a</p><p end="3422" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3359">safe environment. And if the person who's -- on the subway, you can get off the subway</p><p end="3422" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3359">and hopefully in a city of 8 million people, you won't see the person again.</p><p end="3482" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3422">But when he's in your chemistry class --</p><p end="3482" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3422">Yes. I think you summarized their argument accurately, and I think it's a straw man,</p><p end="3482" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3422">complete --</p><p end="3482" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3422">-- straw man. Because conflicts of interest are intolerable. They should never be</p><p end="3482" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3422">permitted. And the courts are striking them down. Professor Suk mentioned a whole</p><p end="3482" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3422">series of cases which are striking these things down, as they should. They're fixing</p><p end="3482" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3422">it. But we shouldn't, because of a few colleges, or many colleges mishandling these</p><p end="3482" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3422">cases, we shouldn't say that no colleges should ever do it.</p><p end="3482" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3422">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="3482" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3422">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="3482" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3422">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 27 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="3544" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3482">It is not in any way the exception. The -- if you talk to people who are involved in this</p><p end="3544" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3482">field -- and I myself have participated in and witnessed some of these things that I was</p><p end="3544" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3482">talking about -- it is not in any way the exception. And it is -- and it's good. I agree with</p><p end="3544" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3482">Stephen that the courts have noticed and said, this is not okay. The conflicts of interest,</p><p end="3544" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3482">though, that we're talking about are not just one-off conflicts of interest. We're talking</p><p end="3544" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3482">about structural conflict of interest, where we're talking about a Title IX officer who is</p><p end="3544" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3482">charged with compliance with the Department of Education's dictates. And they are</p><p end="3544" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3482">terrified about what's going to happen if they don't find a certain way, they don't do</p><p end="3544" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3482">things a certain way. And how can that really lead to a neutral decision about the guilt</p><p end="3544" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3482">or innocence of the party before them when they're thinking, oh, my God, am I going to</p><p end="3544" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3482">have -- my school have funding taken away?</p><p end="3604" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3544">Or even if they're not ultimately going to have funding taken away, if, say --</p><p end="3604" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3544">Can I -- can I just --</p><p end="3604" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3544">-- if their is an investigation against the school, then that's going to cost a hundred --</p><p end="3604" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3544">several hundred thousand dollars to even just deal with, even if at the end of the</p><p end="3604" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3544">day. So when you're thinking like that, how can you be neutral about the guilt or</p><p end="3604" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3544">innocence or about the facts of what happened?</p><p end="3604" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3544">Can I just ask whether Jeannie and --</p><p end="3604" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3544">So the question of the incentive structure that -- that campuses face right now I think is</p><p end="3604" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3544">an important one. Historically, before the Department of Education strongly</p><p end="3604" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3544">encouraged mandated that courts get -- that campuses get involved in these cases, the</p><p end="3604" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3544">incentives for campuses were to sweep these cases under the rug. Let's not -- we don't</p><p end="3604" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3544">want the bad publicity. Let's put it under the rug. Today, however, the incentive</p><p end="3604" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3544">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="3604" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3544">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="3604" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3544">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 28 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="3604" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3544">structure is very different. The Department of Education mandates that campuses get</p><p end="3604" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3544">involved and equitably and promptly adjudicate these cases. On the -- so that's</p><p end="3604" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3544">powerful incentive to pursue these cases.</p><p end="3661" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3604">However, on the other side, you've got all of these claims brought by accused students,</p><p end="3661" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3604">indicate -- claiming that their due process rights were violated. That's powerful</p><p end="3661" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3604">incentive the other way to provide due process. So you have two kinds of incentives on</p><p end="3661" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3604">both sides. And that will lead to more equitable and fair outcomes. If there were no</p><p end="3661" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3604">incentives to pursue these cases, campuses would not pursue them, and they would</p><p end="3661" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3604">sweep them under the rug in the way that they have historically. If there were only</p><p end="3661" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3604">pressure one way and no pushback by the accused students when their rights have been</p><p end="3661" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3604">violated, you'd have a problem. But you have pressure on both sides. And campuses</p><p end="3661" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3604">are responding, as they must, to these federal cases that are --</p><p end="3661" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3604">-- coming down.</p><p end="3661" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3604">Well, I think Michelle's exactly right. We've seen an era when colleges, the big incentive</p><p end="3661" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3604">was to sweep them under the rugs -- under the rug now. The incentive has</p><p end="3661" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3604">changed. That is not the way, as Jeannie is saying, to get conflicts of interest out of a</p><p end="3661" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3604">process.</p><p end="3725" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3661">That's the way to inject conflict of interest into a process. You don't want to give</p><p end="3725" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3661">colleges an incentive to find a certain way, either way. And today, now they have this</p><p end="3725" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3661">incentive to make examples, to show how seriously they're taking these things. And you</p><p end="3725" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3661">can't say, well, now they've got pressures on both sides and it'll come out fine. No. Two</p><p end="3725" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3661">conflicts of interest don't equal impartiality.</p><p end="3725" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3661">So what's the alternative, Jed?</p><p end="3725" is_meta="true" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3661">applause</p><p end="3725" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3661">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="3725" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3661">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="3725" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3661">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 29 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="3725" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3661">So -- so the alternative -- so the alternative is the era before, where campuses swept</p><p end="3725" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3661">these cases under the rug. What's the alternative? Sending these cases, pulling these</p><p end="3725" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3661">cases out alone and saying, if it were sexual assault, you want a difference between</p><p end="3725" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3661">sexual assault and rape. If it were rape, that needs to go to the criminal court. But if it</p><p end="3725" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3661">were sexual misconduct or groping or sexual assault, then campuses can adjudicate</p><p end="3725" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="3661">that. How does that make even sense?</p><p end="3725" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3661">The alternative is just to do with rape what we do with murder and arson. The</p><p end="3725" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3661">alternative is you call the police, you expect them to do a professional, proper</p><p end="3725" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3661">investigation, and you encourage students to report to the police.</p><p end="3779" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3725">We heard earlier tonight that only about 5 percent of college women students who are</p><p end="3779" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3725">victims are reporting. That's a huge problem. The alternative is to work better between</p><p end="3779" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3725">colleges and the police to encourage reporting, to get these cases into the criminal</p><p end="3779" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3725">justice system where rapists can get the punishment that they should get, and we can</p><p end="3779" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="3725">make our campuses and communities safer.</p><p end="3779" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3725">John --</p><p end="3779" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3725">Yes, thanks.</p><p end="3847" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3779">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="3847" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3779">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="3847" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3779">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 30 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="3847" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3779">I just was hoping to get some clarification about whether Professor Rubenfeld and</p><p end="3847" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3779">Professor Suk are really in agreement, because as I heard Professor Rubenfeld, he was</p><p end="3847" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3779">saying, well, what sexual assault means for purposes of this resolution is not what it</p><p end="3847" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3779">means in the criminal law. What it means is rape. And rape should go to the criminal</p><p end="3847" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3779">courts because that's a very serious crime. But if it's groping, some woman who can't</p><p end="3847" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3779">do her lab work because the guy next to her is just some immature jerk, if that's all it is,</p><p end="3847" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3779">then the campus can adjudicate that. As I understood Professor Suk, she was saying</p><p end="3847" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3779">that the conflicts of interest are endemic and insoluble. And Professor Rubenfeld</p><p end="3847" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3779">actually said that you can't solve one conflict -- offset one conflict with another. So to --</p><p end="3847" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3779">you know, I think got great responsiveness from the audience. But what are we saying</p><p end="3847" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3779">about -- I mean, is it the case that campuses are just completely unable to fix the</p><p end="3847" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3779">problems, and therefore they can't decide any of these cases, and that woman just has</p><p end="3847" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3779">to tough it out?</p><p end="3902" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3847">So I have prosecuted that case here in Manhattan. There were people being groped</p><p end="3902" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3847">every day in Times Square. And it is incorrect, as was suggested earlier --</p><p end="3902" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3847">Yeah.</p><p end="3902" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3847">Yes, exactly. So that -- that's a crime just like it was in -- if it was in Times Square, it's a</p><p end="3902" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3847">crime. And if it happens in a chemistry lab, it's also a crime. At that point, like any</p><p end="3902" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3847">victim, this victim has the discretion whether to report to the police or not to the police.</p><p end="3902" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3847">Many of us have been victims of crimes. Many of us have made a decision whether</p><p end="3902" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3847">what -- whatever kind of crime it was, whether it was worth it to us to pursue the crime</p><p end="3902" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3847">or not.</p><p end="3964" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3902">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="3964" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3902">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="3964" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3902">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 31 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="3964" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3902">I think that would be the situation for that victim. And she -- in my opinion, if I were her</p><p end="3964" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3902">advisor, I would say, "Go to the police because this is a crime, and a crime has been</p><p end="3964" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3902">committed against you, the person will be arrested."</p><p end="3964" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3902">Well, if we were living in a reasonable world with a reasonable department of</p><p end="3964" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3902">education, what would actually happen, what could happen is the possibility that short</p><p end="3964" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3902">of an -- a police-like investigation and a law-like court type of tribunal, you would have</p><p end="3964" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3902">some reasonable parties get involved, talk to the people, and say, you know, "What's</p><p end="3964" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3902">going on here? This is not acceptable. Bad, bad, bad person. Don't do that. Don't do it</p><p end="3964" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3902">anymore." And, you know, as Stephen suggested, these are adolescents with raging</p><p end="3964" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3902">hormones and exercising bad judgment. There are some cases like that. But what Jed</p><p end="3964" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3902">was talking about was serious cases of rape and sexual assault.</p><p end="4016" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3964">Now, "sexual assault" is an ambiguous term because it includes rape and in some</p><p end="4016" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3964">jurisdictions it includes other things. In other jurisdictions, sexual assault is separate</p><p end="4016" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3964">from rape. So there's a little bit of an ambiguity about what we're talking about. But</p><p end="4016" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="3964">what we are talking about essentially is serious crimes involving sex such as rape.</p><p end="4016" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3964">Well, I think that we still need to know how to deal with this groping case, and we still</p><p end="4016" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3964">need to know -- Professor Rubenfeld said, "Let's encourage women to take all this to the</p><p end="4016" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3964">criminal courts." I do not want to do that. I do not want to see this immature</p><p end="4016" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="3964">adolescent put on a sex offender registry for the rest of his life.</p><p end="4084" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4016">I think there's a ton to learn.</p><p end="4084" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4016">So in -- if this happened in the workplace, the federal law called Title VII would provide a</p><p end="4084" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4016">way for that person to sue their employer for failing to prevent or to address a hostile</p><p end="4084" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4016">work environment. Now, Title IX also is a law that one could use to sue one&#8217;s school for</p><p end="4084" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4016">failing to address a hostile environment.</p><p end="4142" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4084">Now, there are many ways to address a hostile environment. Do they all involve an</p><p end="4142" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4084">investigation and an adjudication and a kind of tribunal like that? No. There are many</p><p end="4142" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4084">ways to do the work that an educational institution, consistent with this pedagogical</p><p end="4142" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4084">mission, to educate its students, to nurture them, to promote a kind of culture where</p><p end="4142" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4084">sexual harassment is not considered acceptable.</p><p end="4142" is_meta="true" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4084">applause</p><p end="4142" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4084">Well, I must say -- and I appreciate the response, that resonates with the audience -- but</p><p end="4142" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4084">I must say that in the workplace we don't just say, "Well, the employer has to hold</p><p end="4142" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4084">sensitivity training for his employees." If the -- if, in fact, there was groping, then the</p><p end="4142" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4084">employee has to be -- the employee who did it has to be disciplined and know if an</p><p end="4142" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4084">employer can't get away with his responsibility by just saying, "I'm going to ramp up my</p><p end="4142" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4084">sensitivity training."</p><p end="4200" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4142">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="4200" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4142">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="4200" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4142">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 33 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="4200" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4142">And I think your question is excellent because it is exactly analogous, unlike the subway</p><p end="4200" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4142">situation, the woman who's trying to pursue a career in the workplace cannot do that in</p><p end="4200" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4142">a safe environment if she's subject to that kind of misbehavior. And there has to be a</p><p end="4200" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4142">remedy. And there can't be a remedy without deciding what happened. We can't allow</p><p end="4200" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4142">a woman or a man to say, "This person's sexually harassing me, so get rid of him." We</p><p end="4200" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4142">can't just -- and this is where I part company with our opponents. I totally am unable to</p><p end="4200" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4142">understand how they can say that schools can take action and impose remedies without</p><p end="4200" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4142">deciding whether the allegations ever happened or not.</p><p end="4265" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4200">I think it's crucial to remember that the objectives of these two different systems are</p><p end="4265" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4200">different. First of all, the colleges are responsible, unless you want to say that -- repeal</p><p end="4265" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4200">Title IX.</p><p end="4322" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4265">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="4322" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4265">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="4322" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4265">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 34 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="4322" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4265">Colleges are responsible for protecting racial minorities and women from sexual and</p><p end="4322" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4265">racial harassment. And that includes not only things that are crimes. You could have a</p><p end="4322" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4265">student who's receiving hateful email with the "n" word. And the colleges have to find</p><p end="4322" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4265">out who did that and take some measures. It's not a crime. But they do have a</p><p end="4322" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4265">responsibility to preserve an equal educational opportunity for all their women and</p><p end="4322" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4265">minorities on campus. So, that's the objective. And the system is remedial. It's not</p><p end="4322" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4265">punitive. The colleges' responsibility is to decide, by a preponderance of the evidence --</p><p end="4322" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4265">which is the standard that we use throughout the legal system for anything other than</p><p end="4322" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4265">incarceration. Decide whether the person did what's alleged and then take remedial</p><p end="4322" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4265">action to protect the victim. Usually involves some sort of separation. That is not</p><p end="4322" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4265">criminal punishment.</p><p end="4380" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4322">It's not incarceration. It's not a lifetime public record. It's not sex offender registration</p><p end="4380" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4322">and so on. So, those things need to be taken to protect the woman's opportunity to get</p><p end="4380" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4322">her -- to major in chemistry, to complete her class, and to get her degree. It's -- that's</p><p end="4380" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4322">how we reconcile the fact. And it's the same reason why someone who sues for</p><p end="4380" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4322">damages is heard in a different environment from somebody who's claiming to be the</p><p end="4380" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4322">victim of a crime.</p><p end="4443" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4380">Well, thanks for that great question. As you can guess, my answer is going to be the</p><p end="4443" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4380">courts.</p><p end="4443" is_meta="true" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4380">laughter</p><p end="4443" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4380">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="4443" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4380">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="4443" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4380">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 35 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="4443" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4380">Because it is very hard to deter people from serious crimes if you slap them on the wrist</p><p end="4443" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4380">for doing it. And being told to write a paper or even a suspension, that's a slap on the</p><p end="4443" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4380">wrist. Now, expulsion is a serious penalty. But if you keep that a secret, and it's nontransparent,</p><p end="4443" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4380">that is not the way you deter sexual assault. I got to add one little point</p><p end="4443" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4380">about a previous statement. The burden of proof that the government has forced us to</p><p end="4443" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4380">use -- us colleges to use -- preponderance of the evidence -- look, at Yale, what's our</p><p end="4443" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4380">standard of proof for a plagiarism case? It's clear and convincing evidence. That, legally -</p><p end="4443" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4380">- for those of you who know, that's a standard up from preponderance of the evidence.</p><p end="4443" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4380">That's what we do with all our cases. Now, with rape, we're forced to use a lower one. I</p><p end="4443" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4380">got to say one more thing -- mediation. You have to understand -- this goes to the workrelated</p><p end="4443" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4380">question before. Title IX has forced us to not do -- we're barred from doing</p><p end="4443" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4380">mediation.</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4443">What would grown-ups do with a groping allegation, grown-ups at a school? They bring</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4443">the parties in, get them to agree. "You're not going to do this anymore. You agree.</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4443">Right? If you break this agreement, you will be subject to penalties." They agree. That's</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4443">called mediation. No. We can't do that anymore because Title IX --</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4443">[inaudible] --</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4443">Well --</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4443">Actually, that's a different question than the one raised --</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4443">But that's an important --</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4443">-- one too.</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4443">Rachel asked, "Which system leads to more deterrence?" And deterrence --</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4443">Deterrence is one of the goals of the criminal justice system -- deterrence,</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4443">incapacitation, retribution. We're all criminal law professors up here, so you could -- we</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4443">could all talk about that. So the criminal justice system is designed to deter, generally. I</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4443">think the goals of the campus adjudicatory system are very different.</p><p end="4563" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4502">And I don't think they have the goal of large, general deterrents. I think they have the</p><p end="4563" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4502">goal of individual assessment of the facts and trying to match a remedy that fits</p><p end="4563" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4502">whatever happened. And I also think that the criminal justice system wildly overplays its</p><p end="4563" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4502">hand in its -- and it's far too incarcerative and punitive in general, which is what Stephen</p><p end="4563" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4502">talked about in his remarks. I think your question about which leads to more justice --</p><p end="4563" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4502">You can.</p><p end="4619" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4563">I think that they can get safety through -- if we didn't have these tribunals, they would</p><p end="4619" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4563">have safety through the school's reasonable measures that they could take, that they</p><p end="4619" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4563">take all the time.</p><p end="4683" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4619">They take them even without going through the tribunals. They just impose them,</p><p end="4683" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4619">depending on their individualized assessment of what the safety of the campus</p><p end="4683" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4619">requires. That does not mean what we need is a system, a shadow justice system that is</p><p end="4683" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4619">operating in schools. And so there are many options for schools to undertake to provide</p><p end="4683" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4619">for victim support. And they could be even doing a better job if they weren't so focused</p><p end="4683" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4619">on this quasi punitive system.</p><p end="4683" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4619">Yes, I think that question really goes to the heart of one major difficulty with the</p><p end="4683" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4619">proponent's position. Many, many victims do not want to force the case into the</p><p end="4683" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4619">criminal process. It's not that they -- they think a slap on the wrist is better. But, you</p><p end="4683" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4619">know, they have a classmate who's immature, who's just kind of boorish. They don't</p><p end="4683" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4619">want to ruin that person's life, but they want protection.</p><p end="4741" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4683">And the criminal justice system is a sledgehammer. Let's not kid ourselves. This is no</p><p end="4741" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4683">joke. We're not talking about going from a slap on the wrist to, I don't know, a pinch on</p><p end="4741" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4683">the cheek or something like that. We're talking about going from a slap on the wrist to a</p><p end="4741" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4683">sledgehammer. We're talking about ruining -- literally, not just expulsion, but sex</p><p end="4741" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4683">offender registration the rest of the person's life. And many victims, not only do they</p><p end="4741" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4683">not want to put themselves through that process, which is one reason why they</p><p end="4741" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4683">wouldn't report, but they also don't want to put their classmate through that process,</p><p end="4741" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4683">so they won't report. And it comes back to the question that the other person asked a</p><p end="4741" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4683">few minutes ago. How will you get the best prevention. If you have a system with</p><p end="4741" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4683">tremendous disincentives for a victim to report, then nothing will be done. And that</p><p end="4741" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4683">doesn't serve anybody's interests.</p><p end="4805" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4741">Sure, we do. I mean, 50 schools are under investigation. They've been charged by the</p><p end="4805" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4741">federal government with not enforcing and finding sexual assaults to be happening</p><p end="4805" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4741">sufficiently. And the threat is hundreds of millions of dollars in defunding. So you have</p><p end="4805" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4741">the threat which applies to all of them. You have 50 schools under investigation. And I</p><p end="4805" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4741">can tell you from personal experience that the administrators, the deans, the Title IX</p><p end="4805" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4741">coordinators are very, very afraid of being found liable by the Department of Education,</p><p end="4805" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4741">by the Office of Civil Rights. And if you talk to them, you will hear this fear expressed all</p><p end="4805" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4741">the time.</p><p end="4919" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4860">I'll start. I think there's absolutely no question that you get more justice and better</p><p end="4919" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4860">results if victims have options and if society itself has a mix of remedies and a mix of</p><p end="4919" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4860">ways to responding more moderately or more severely, depending on all the</p><p end="4919" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4860">circumstances. And it doesn't serve anybody's interest to have an either/or situation</p><p end="4919" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4860">where either nothing happens or a ton of bricks comes down on somebody's head.</p><p end="4919" is_meta="true" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="4860">bell rings</p><p end="4919" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4860">The courts have the competence, the impartiality, the neutrality to do this</p><p end="4919" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4860">properly. That's where you get justice. Nobody's talking about barring the schools from</p><p end="4919" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4860">doing anything. The question is -- I'd like you to send this message -- that courts should</p><p end="4919" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4860">be the ones deciding these cases because that's where -- that's the institution we've</p><p end="4919" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4860">built up for 200 years to do justice. And it's not happening in a conflict of interest</p><p end="4919" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4860">ridden and error ridden process.</p><p end="4985" is_meta="true" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4919">bell rings</p><p end="4985" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4919">We've had 200 years of history where the courts and the police have not taken sexual</p><p end="4985" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4919">assault seriously.</p><p end="4985" is_meta="true" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4919">applause</p><p end="4985" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4919">And the notion -- and the notion that closing off an option for victims and forcing them</p><p end="4985" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4919">to go to a system that is beholden to different interests and disinterested in equality,</p><p end="4985" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4919">disinterested in their civil rights and disinterested in their ability to maintain their</p><p end="4985" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4919">schooling, it's not a recipe for justice. Today, if you have an acquaintance rape situation,</p><p end="4985" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4919">and you don't have some physical evidence of harm you get nowhere --</p><p end="4985" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4919">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="4985" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4919">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="4985" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4919">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 41 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="4985" is_meta="true" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4919">bell rings</p><p end="4985" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="4919">-- you get nowhere.</p><p end="4985" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4919">I think that it is clear that the idea that schools are more interested in justice for victims,</p><p end="4985" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4919">that they're more interested in their well-being, that they're more interested in the</p><p end="4985" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4919">correct outcomes, that is absurd. Schools are entrenched in conflicts of interest, in all</p><p end="4985" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4919">kinds of problems, in different loyalties to different entities, to alumni, to their current</p><p end="4985" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4919">students, different political forces.</p><p end="5044" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4985">And our court system, hey, it's really flawed. We know that. But that is what it's</p><p end="5044" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4985">designed to do, to try to sort --</p><p end="5044" is_meta="true" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4985">bell rings</p><p end="5044" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="4985">-- these out.</p><p end="5044" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4985">Thank you. Many of you probably remember the case I'm about to mention to you, the</p><p end="5044" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4985">Duke Lacrosse case. That was when a woman accused three lacrosse players falsely, it</p><p end="5044" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4985">turned out, of raping her at a house party. What was the university reaction to those</p><p end="5044" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4985">false rape accusations? It was panic. The coach was immediately</p><p end="5044" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4985">fired. Suspensions. Everyone called for the expulsion of the accused students.</p><p end="5044" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4985">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="5044" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4985">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="5044" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="4985">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 42 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="5103" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="5044">88 Duke professors placed an ad calling that rape a disaster. All around the country</p><p end="5103" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="5044">there was a rush to judgment, a presumption of guilt. Television legal commentator,</p><p end="5103" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="5044">Nancy Grace, vilified those who even considered the possibility that a woman might lie</p><p end="5103" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="5044">about being a victim of gang rape. The local prosecutor, too, was taken in. It took the</p><p end="5103" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="5044">police and the courts and due process to prove that the rape accusation was a</p><p end="5103" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="5044">fabrication. How did we find out it was false? We found out because the toxicology and</p><p end="5103" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="5044">forensic evidence disproved the accuser's claims. We found out because there was</p><p end="5103" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="5044">transparency and professional evidence gathering and procedural fairness. Had the</p><p end="5103" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="5044">accuser reported only to school authorities, and had that case been tried on campus</p><p end="5103" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="5044">behind closed doors, it's a good bet that those lacrosse players would have been</p><p end="5103" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="5044">promptly expelled and had their lives ruined with no way to vindicate themselves.</p><p end="5164" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="5103">But that case happened in 2007 before all this stuff got going, so that's not what</p><p end="5164" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="5103">happened. Students were lucky. Their case went to court. Now, I'm not saying that</p><p end="5164" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="5103">such cases happen every day. And I'm not saying our courts are perfect or our police</p><p end="5164" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="5103">are perfect. We've got to do better. We have to encourage these cases to go to court</p><p end="5164" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="5103">through the police to get justice. I would just ask you to bear that kind of case in mind</p><p end="5164" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="5103">tonight when you vote on the resolution that courts should be the place where rape</p><p end="5164" is_meta="false" speaker="Jed Rubenfeld" start="5103">cases are tried.</p><p end="5164" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5103">The trouble with that Duke example is the claim that if they had been expelled, they</p><p end="5164" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5103">would have had no way to vindicate themselves. We've just heard from Professor</p><p end="5164" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5103">Rubenfeld's partner that there are cases all over the country that are overturning</p><p end="5164" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5103">expulsions that are based on botched procedures.</p><p end="5224" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5164">So there are remedies, and there will be remedies, but one of the worst tendencies in</p><p end="5224" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5164">American society today is to turn to the criminal justice system as the all purpose</p><p end="5224" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5164">solution for every social problem. Almost everybody who works in that system, no</p><p end="5224" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5164">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="5224" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5164">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="5224" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5164">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 43 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="5224" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5164">matter which side they're on, agrees that we have to reduce the reach of the criminal</p><p end="5224" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5164">law. We have to be diverting cases away from the criminal law. And that's especially</p><p end="5224" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5164">true of sex offenses because even a misdemeanor contact offense means sanctions that</p><p end="5224" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5164">are much, much too harsh and much too inflexible. So I remember vividly my children</p><p end="5224" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5164">aren't in college anymore but I remember the feelings that I had as a parent when they</p><p end="5224" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5164">were. Nobody wants to get a call from a daughter saying she's been sexually</p><p end="5224" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5164">assaulted. Nobody wants to get a call from a son saying he's been accused of sexual</p><p end="5224" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5164">assault. But, God forbid, if you did get a call like that from your daughter, wouldn't you</p><p end="5224" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5164">want her to have options for redress on campus?</p><p end="5283" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5224">Would you really prefer her to say that her only option was either to go to the police or</p><p end="5283" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5224">drop out of school? That's not even a close question. Limiting her to the criminal courts</p><p end="5283" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5224">makes a terrible situation many times worse. And what if your son called to say he'd</p><p end="5283" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5224">been unfairly accused? Any parent would dread getting that call, but if it happens,</p><p end="5283" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5224">which call would be more horrible? Your son might say, "Mom, I've been accused of</p><p end="5283" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5224">sexual assault, and I might even get expelled or suspended from school." That's a</p><p end="5283" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5224">nightmare. But would you prefer to hear your son say, "Mom, the DA down here is</p><p end="5283" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5224">prosecuting me for rape"? If that's what you would prefer, you should vote for this</p><p end="5283" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5224">resolution, but any parent who knows the criminal justice system knows that they --</p><p end="5283" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5224">taking a campus tribunal and the risk of possible campus sanctions, they would take that</p><p end="5283" is_meta="false" speaker="Stephen Schulhofer" start="5224">in a heartbeat. So we desperately need to reign in the criminal justice system --</p><p end="5345" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5283">Let me close by sharing with you a worry that we haven't really talked about yet</p><p end="5345" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5283">tonight. The trampling of fair process, which we see all over on campuses, should give</p><p end="5345" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5283">us concern about the disproportionate impact on students of color. I have personally</p><p end="5345" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5283">seen time and again allegations arising from the kinds of cases I was talking about, the</p><p end="5345" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5283">ambivalence, the ambiguity, or misunderstanding about consent. They fall on minorities</p><p end="5345" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5283">and poor students. And many others working on these cases have told me that this is a</p><p end="5345" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5283">campus secret nobody wants to talk about. Think about a nontransparent campus</p><p end="5345" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5283">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="5345" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5283">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="5345" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5283">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 44 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="5345" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5283">process as opposed to a transparent public hearing, without procedural safeguard,</p><p end="5345" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5283">behind closed doors where unconscious bias can flourish.</p><p end="5399" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5345">These are perfect conditions for biases and fears to reach inaccurate outcomes. One</p><p end="5399" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5345">college administrator told me that what keeps him up at night is panic that his school</p><p end="5399" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5345">could be one Department of Education investigation away from institutional</p><p end="5399" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5345">death. That makes it impossible for him to consider what's fair and what's</p><p end="5399" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5345">right. Campuses must respond to sexual assault. The vote tonight though asks you to</p><p end="5399" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5345">say whether shadow campus rape tribunals to decide responsibility and guilt are a</p><p end="5399" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5345">solution. Colleges have lost their way because of the impossible position -- and we</p><p end="5399" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5345">covered that tonight -- the impossible position that the federal government has put</p><p end="5399" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5345">schools in. I am sure officials from the Department of Education know about tonight's</p><p end="5399" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5345">debate.</p><p end="5463" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5399">And school administrators are watching too. You have the chance to send a message</p><p end="5463" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5399">about how you feel about these tribunals that have been generated under this kind of</p><p end="5463" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5399">fear. Vote for the motion, not just because you care about fairness and process, but</p><p end="5463" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5399">because you care about victims and about safety, and about effective responses to</p><p end="5463" is_meta="false" speaker="Jeannie Suk" start="5399">sexual assault.</p><p end="5463" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5399">Two quick responses. One, if you're concerned about racial justice and racial disparity, it</p><p end="5463" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5399">flourishes in the criminal justice system. Do you really want to send these cases there?</p><p end="5463" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5399">Two, if you're concerned about transparency, the plea bargaining system -- which, 60 to</p><p end="5463" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5399">90 percent, depending on which percentages you look at in the studies -- an</p><p end="5463" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5399">overwhelming majority of cases end up plea bargained. And they are entirely nontransparent.</p><p end="5463" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5399">Those processes are non-transparent.</p><p end="5522" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5463">Prepared by National Capitol Contracting 200 N. Glebe Rd., #1016</p><p end="5522" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5463">Arlington, VA 22203</p><p end="5522" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5463">Intelligence Squared U.S. - 45 - 9/17/2015</p><p end="5522" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5463">I am the dean of a law school, so I spend a lot of time thinking about how to lead a</p><p end="5522" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5463">complex institution and how to provide students with a save environment. Put yourself</p><p end="5522" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5463">in the shoes of a campus administrator. A shaken student comes to you and explains</p><p end="5522" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5463">that she's failing chemistry because a student gropes her breasts after weekly labs. She's</p><p end="5522" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5463">deeply distraught and she tells us she doesn't want to go to the police. Now, under this</p><p end="5522" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5463">resolution, you have to tell her, "I'm sorry. If he stole your lab homework or if he</p><p end="5522" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5463">punched you in your -- in the face, I could investigate. I could switch him to a different</p><p end="5522" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5463">lab section, or I could have him suspended, or send him to a different dorm, or have him</p><p end="5522" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5463">expelled. But since he sexually assaulted you, our hands are tied. You have to report to</p><p end="5522" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5463">the police. Good luck." No. You want to tell that student, "I'm sorry this happened to</p><p end="5522" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5463">you. If you change your mind and decide you want to report to the police, we will</p><p end="5522" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5463">support you every step of the way. But in any case, we will investigate. And if we have</p><p end="5522" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5463">enough evidence, we will take remedial steps to protect you.</p><p end="5582" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5522">And we'll try everything in our power to get this resolved this semester." This debate is</p><p end="5582" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5522">about equality. It's about what it means to have equal access to education when one</p><p end="5582" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5522">student harms another. The only way to protect students' civil rights to an equal</p><p end="5582" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5522">education is to allow the campus to act, to stop sexual assault, and protect students'</p><p end="5582" is_meta="false" speaker="Michelle Anderson" start="5522">safety. Vote no on this resolution. Thank you.</p></transcript></debate>