<debate duration="6203" url="https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/death-not-final"><speakers><speaker name="Dr. Eben Alexander" position="for"><description>Neurosurgeon &amp; Author, Proof of Heaven</description><bio>Eben Alexander, M.D., is a renowned academic neurosurgeon. A transcendental near-death experience (NDE) during a week-long coma from an inexplicable... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Dr. Raymond Moody" position="for"><description>Medical Doctor &amp; Author, Life After Life</description><bio>Raymond A. Moody, Jr., M.D., Ph.D., is a medical doctor and the best-selling and award-winning author of twelve books, including Life After Life (1975)... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Sean Carroll" position="against"><description>Physicist &amp; Writer</description><bio>Sean Carroll is a physicist and author. He received his Ph.D. from Harvard in 1993, and is now on the faculty at the California Institute of Technology... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Dr. Steven Novella" position="against"><description>Academic Neurologist, Yale School of Medicine</description><bio>Steven Novella, M.D., is an academic clinical neurologist at Yale University School of Medicine. He is the founder and current executive editor of... Read More</bio></speaker></speakers><results><result against="30" for="36" submitters="live" undecided="33" when="before" /><result against="46" for="42" submitters="live" undecided="11" when="after" /><result against="57" for="34" submitters="online" undecided="5" when="before" /><result against="60" for="34" submitters="online" undecided="2" when="after" /></results><transcript><p end="544" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="487">A naturalist is one who believes there is one world, the natural world. And it is our job to deal with it.</p><p end="544" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="487">The talented and charming Steven Novella.</p><p end="1143" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1077">Thanks, John. It's a pleasure to be here defending such a cheerful and uplifting proposition, as death is, in fact, final. Driving around the streets of Los Angeles, where I live, you can't help but notice these gigantic billboards telling us "All Men Must Die."</p><p end="1143" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1077">Turns out they were advertisements for "Game of Thrones," but I thought that they were advertisements for --</p><p end="1143" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1077">laughter</p><p end="1143" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1077">-- our event here tonight. It's a similarly -- you know, not quit as happy message as we might like to accept. Fortunately, we can open Dr. Alexander's book. It begins with a quote from Albert Einstein. Einstein says, "A man should look for what is, not for what he thinks should be," to which I would like to reply, "Exactly."</p><p end="1200" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1143">laughter</p><p end="1200" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1143">applause</p><p end="1200" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1143">We human beings are not always perfectly rational. Let me tell this shocking news toyou. We are bundles of cognitive biases. And one of the strongest biases we have is that we go easy on propositions that we would like to be true. What we should, in fact, do, is go especially skeptical on propositions that we would like to be true. And even I want it to be true, that death is not final. But we should hold something like that to an extraordinarily high standard of evidence. So, what are we actually being asked to accept? What should we expect the world to be like if death were not, actually final? For one thing, I would expect that the existence of souls persisting in the afterlife should be perfectly obvious. It should be just as clear that heaven exists as it is clear that Canada exists. But in fact, it seems that the souls persisting in the afterlife are kind of shy.</p><p end="1263" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1200">They don't talk to us, except sometimes they do talk to us. I would expect, also, that when people did have near death experiences, and really talked to other souls in the afterlife, that they would come back with consistent, interesting, non-trivial stories to tell. But in fact, when Christians have near-death experiences, they often say they've met Jesus. When Hindus have near-death experiences, they meet Hindu deities. There was a little girl who had a near-death experience, and she met a portly man wearing a red cap. She met Santa Claus. And we are told by some defenders of this that, well,</p><p end="1263" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1200">Jesus dressed up as Santa Claus so as not to scare the little girl. Possibly, that is true.</p><p end="1263" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1200">But we should be asking, are there other plausible explanations? I especially think that if we went and had a life after death and then came back to visit us, bringing some message back, that message would -- should be as useful as possible. We are told that,</p><p end="1263" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1200">you know, people have after death experiences, and they come back saying, you know what?</p><p end="1309" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1263">Love is really important. I agree with that. But actually, I knew it already. What I would like to know is the cure for Alzheimer's disease. What I would like to know is something that I didn't already know brought back to us. But it seems that the souls in the afterlife tend to speak in platitudes. The story that we're told of life after death doesn't really hang together. What we have are personal testimonies like that from Dr. Alexander. So people say, with very sincere voices, that what they experienced was totally real. And I have no doubt in the sincerity of this testimony. What I'm asking is, is it possible that our brain is telling us that something was real, but that thing does not actually correspond to something that really happened. And when you ask it that way, the answer is obviously yes.</p><p end="1365" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1309">Our brains are fooling us all the time. Steve Novella, my partner, will tell us about the neuroscience behind this. But basically, our brains are not like video recorders or photo albums. They're more like little theaters. When we try to remember something, it'smuch like imagining something that hasn't happened. It's more like running a script than reviewing a tape. And that's why, when we dream, when we hallucinate, when we have a near-death experience, it is just as vivid as something that actually happened. In the legal community, they will tell you that eyewitnesses who tell you that -- have a certain sincerity and conviction that their eyewitness testimony is true, that conviction is essentially uncorrelated with now true it actually is. The vividness or reality of a memory does not tell us that it was really real. So what is going on? We had this informal idea that there is a soul that sort of is a blob of spirit energy that takes up residence near the brain and drives us around like a soccer mom driving an SUV.</p><p end="1424" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1365">But we've known for a long time that this picture doesn't make sense. Back in the 1600s, princess Elizabeth of Bohemia carried on a correspondence with Ren&#233;</p><p end="1424" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1365">Descarteswho was trying to defend mind-body dualism. And Elizabeth demands, no,</p><p end="1424" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1365">how could something immaterial like the soul affect something material like the brain or the body? Descartes was never able to answer that question. And these days, science has gone way beyond that. We know a lot more about what is happening. We can literally see memories being formed. We can see the chemical changes in neurons. So the soul is supposed to also have memories. How do the memories get from the neurons to the soul? We know that brains often have false memories in them. Does the soul in the afterlife carry those false memories, or are they somehow corrected after death? We even know the laws of physics by which the atoms, the electrons, the elementary particles in our brains behave.</p><p end="1487" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1424">We know the equations that the electrons that are responsible for chemistry obey. And there's no ambiguity in these equations. They could always be wrong. It is always possible to say, well, we just don't know what is going on. That's fine. But what we have is the evidence of every experiment ever done telling us that these equations are correct. To overcome that, we would need very, very strong evidence, just one experiment, telling us how the soul is pushing around the chemicals in our brain. But we don't have that. What science says is that life or consciousness is not a substance like water or air. It is a process like fire. When you put out the flame on a candle, the flame doesn't go anywhere, it simply stops. And that is what happens when we die. So we're faced at the end with two scenarios. One scenario says that everything we think we understand about the behavior of matter and energy is wrong in a way that has somehow escaped notice by every experiment ever done in the history of science.</p><p end="1554" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1487">And instead, there are unknown mechanisms that allow information in the brain to the transferred to blobs of spirit energy that persist after we die and can talk to the otherblobs of spirit energy, but don't talk to us, expect sometimes they do. The other scenario says that physics is right and that people under stress sometimes have experiences that are not actually real. On the basis of rationality, it not a difficult decision to choose between these two options. On the basis of emotion, it might be difficult. But we need to have the courage to live life here in the actual world. Thank you.</p><p end="1554" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1487">applause</p><p end="2764" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="2701">Well, I think that Steven can talk about the specifics that might have been going on in the brain. But my emphasis is on weighing two different comprehensive pictures here.</p><p end="2764" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="2701">We have personal testimony from someone who says he experienced something, and it's very real and says that, well, we can't imagine that, even as a neurosurgeon, he just doesn't know what could possibly have been going on in his brain that would make that happen, therefore let's throw out all of the laws of physics. And I think that that is not nearly enough.</p><p end="2764" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="2701">They do. I could teach it right now --</p><p end="2865" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="2814">The thing about Einstein, Bor, de Broglie, et cetera, the founders of quantum mechanics,</p><p end="2865" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="2814">is that they're all dead, and they have been dead for many decades. And we know what's going on much better now than we did back then. They were inventing quantum mechanics, and occasionally they toyed with the idea that somehow consciousness had something to do with the fundamental laws of quantum mechanics. Now we know better.</p><p end="2936" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="2865">We know how laws of quantum mechanics help explain how electrons move in the brain, and there's nothing in there --</p><p end="3346" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3287">Yeah, I hope it's not insulting. It's certainly not ad hominem because the message is that nobody can be trusted. I think that that is part of what science has taught us, that if someone makes an extraordinary claim, the very first questions we should be asking ourselves are, number one, is there a different, simpler alternative explanation? And number two, how would we know if our purported explanation were false?</p><p end="3410" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3346">How would we disprove it? How could we possibly test this idea? And I think that, you know, when you look at the bigger picture of how the universe works, how the laws of physics work, the enormous success of understanding matter, energy, the brain, life --</p><p end="3410" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3346">everything that we've had -- there's just an enormous presumption against the idea that somehow, through ways that there are no equations, no experiments, or no direct evidence to tell us, the information in our brains persists after we die and is there forever and talking to other people who died. So, it's just a matter of presumption.</p><p end="3410" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3346">There's plenty of things that I would like to be true -- and I have been tricked into believing they're true. So, I know that I should be especially skeptical about them.</p><p end="3463" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3410">But this --</p><p end="3463" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3410">-- I mean, that's -- I think that's a perfect thing to have said in this debate, because it illustrates the difference here.</p><p end="3534" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3463">No evidence was given for this claim. No reason to believe it was given. All we are given is, "Well, maybe it's true and you can't absolutely disprove it." Maybe it is conceivable.</p><p end="3534" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3463">We have laws of physics that tell us how the moon moves around the earth. And they work very well. It is conceivable that there are also angels living inside the moon, gliding it around in exactly the way that Newton's Laws tell us. But we don't take that seriously as an idea, because there's no need for it or evidence for it. So, the question is not is it conceivable that there are other realms. The question is, is the evidence in favor of that other realm so overwhelming that it causes us to dismiss the enormous successes of physics, chemistry, biology and neuroscience?</p><p end="3534" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3463">Come over here to this side. We'll welcome you. We'll put your chair over here --</p><p end="3534" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3463">laughter</p><p end="3534" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3463">applause</p><p end="3534" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3463">Raymond Moody:And yet, you know, I think it's entirely conceivable that there's some other domain of existence over this that some people gain access to it sometimes.</p><p end="3598" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3534">And I know hundreds and hundreds of them.</p><p end="3598" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3534">And how would we know if there weren't?</p><p end="4428" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">Yeah, I think that -- you know, the idea that we could be convinced of another realm in addition to the natural world is obviously, "Yes." There's a million pieces of evidence that would help convince me. None of -- I mean, if this -- if there's a ghost in the room that could lift up that glass right now, then I would be convinced.</p><p end="4428" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">laughter</p><p end="4428" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">For those listening on the radio, the glass is not moving, and it --</p><p end="4428" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">laughter</p><p end="4428" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">-- it never moves when you do this.</p><p end="4428" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">applause</p><p end="4428" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">And we live in a world that looks exactly like there's only the natural world.</p><p end="4428" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">I don't want to die.</p><p end="4428" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">laughter</p><p end="4428" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">I want to live after I die, maybe not for infinity years but for a few hundred thousand years I could amuse myself.</p><p end="4428" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">laughter</p><p end="4428" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">Sadly, as a very wise philosopher once said, "You can't always get what you want."</p><p end="4428" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">laughter</p><p end="4428" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">applause</p><p end="4796" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4750">I think -- you know, it's a great question because there's this image -- like, when we're teaching high school and science, that it's a bunch of facts that are absolutely established, whereas professional scientists like to brag about the fact that -- like Steven just said -- that, you know, we're always skeptical and we're always ready to throw out everything. And both are true, but because there's some intermediate ground. There are many, many things that science does not understand, and we're hoping to get better at it. Many, many things. And there are also some things that science does understand and are not going to go away. This table is made of atoms. We will improve our understanding of what an atom is, what the elemental particles and fields are that make it up, how they interact. That is not finished yet.</p><p end="4863" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4796">We can do better. But a million years from now, our best scientific understanding will still say that the table is made of atoms. In my judgment, the current status of our scientific understanding, the parts that we're not going to give up, are enough to conclude that death is, in fact, final.</p><p end="4863" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4796">applause</p><p end="4924" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4863">Yeah, I mean, I think that, again, there is evidence in favor of those kinds of things.</p><p end="4924" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4863">There is other evidence against those kinds of things. And the kind of remote seeing or telepathy or telekinesis or clairvoyance that is being talked about here is in utter and complete violation with everything we understand about the current laws of physics.</p><p end="5156" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="5099">It doesn't go away. It's up in your head. They're just not continuing to live. It's exactly the same place the flame goes when you put out the candle.</p><p end="5760" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="5703">When I was about six years old, I had an emotional formative experience that apparently many other people share similar things. I was in bed, you know, going to sleep, sort of thinking about the day and so forth, and I started crying. I was just bawling uncontrollably, so much so that my mom heard me from her bedroom and came running in, saying, "What is wrong?" And I said, "Some day, our grandmom is going to die. And someday, you're going to die. And someday, I'm going to die. We're all going to die."</p><p end="5820" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="5760">And you know, she had to explain, "Well, yes." And so forth. And she had her own version of the story. And the reason I'm telling this story because even as convinced as I am that death is final, I have absolutely no desire to belittle the people in the room who disagree, who feel the other way. This is an incredibly important, central issue to our lives. I personally am convinced by the overwhelming scientific evidence from physics,from neuroscience, et cetera, that there is one world, the natural world. Biology is a process that can end. And death is final. And to me, that fact -- the finitude of our lives --</p><p end="5820" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="5760">gives enormous poignancy and importance to the finite number of years that we have here on earth. Our lives here are not dress rehearsals. This is the act. This is the one performance that we get. That does not remove meaning or value from the lives we're leading now.</p><p end="5881" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="5820">It gives -- it forces us to give meaning to everything we do, because we only have a finite number of things to do. If evidence came in on the other side, I would change my mind quickly, if the evidence was good enough. But I think that we're past the point where it's a scientifically interesting question. I think that we know enough to conclude that death is final. And personally, I think that that is okay. Thank you.</p><p end="5881" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="5820">applause</p></transcript></debate>