<debate duration="6203" url="https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/death-not-final"><speakers><speaker name="Dr. Eben Alexander" position="for"><description>Neurosurgeon &amp; Author, Proof of Heaven</description><bio>Eben Alexander, M.D., is a renowned academic neurosurgeon. A transcendental near-death experience (NDE) during a week-long coma from an inexplicable... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Dr. Raymond Moody" position="for"><description>Medical Doctor &amp; Author, Life After Life</description><bio>Raymond A. Moody, Jr., M.D., Ph.D., is a medical doctor and the best-selling and award-winning author of twelve books, including Life After Life (1975)... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Sean Carroll" position="against"><description>Physicist &amp; Writer</description><bio>Sean Carroll is a physicist and author. He received his Ph.D. from Harvard in 1993, and is now on the faculty at the California Institute of Technology... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Dr. Steven Novella" position="against"><description>Academic Neurologist, Yale School of Medicine</description><bio>Steven Novella, M.D., is an academic clinical neurologist at Yale University School of Medicine. He is the founder and current executive editor of... Read More</bio></speaker></speakers><results><result against="30" for="36" submitters="live" undecided="33" when="before" /><result against="46" for="42" submitters="live" undecided="11" when="after" /><result against="57" for="37" submitters="online" undecided="5" when="before" /><result against="65" for="32" submitters="online" undecided="2" when="after" /></results><transcript><p end="425" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="360">Astonishing.</p><p end="425" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="360">"no way," at least not until I knew all the facts.</p><p end="425" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="360">My very good friend, Dr. Raymond Moody.</p><p end="487" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="425">Yes. I was not religious. I got interested in the afterlife question at age 18 when Plato convinced me, through his argument, that the afterlife question is the most important question of existence.</p><p end="487" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="425">Yes.</p><p end="544" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="487">A naturalist is one who believes there is one world, the natural world. And it is our job to deal with it.</p><p end="544" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="487">The talented and charming Steven Novella.</p><p end="597" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="544">Well, I had briefly considered a career in interpretive dance.</p><p end="597" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="544">laughter</p><p end="597" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="544">but sadly, I had to conclude that my talents lay elsewhere. So I thought science skepticism was a good match.</p><p end="597" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="544">The dance of skepticism. I'll work on that.</p><p end="657" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="597">Thank you very much, John.</p><p end="719" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="657">I've been an academic neurosurgeon for over 20 years, and I fully believed in reductive materialism, our modern conventional science. In fact, six years ago I would've been sitting over on that side of the stage with Steven and Sean. Now, at that time I believed that the brain creates mind and consciousness, that we have no free will, that it's birth to death and nothing more. Then something happened. I now know that those ideas are false. In November 2008 I was driven rapidly into coma due to a severe bacterial meningoencephalitis which I much later came to realize is the perfect model for human death, destruction of the neocortex, the outer surface, the human part of the brain.</p><p end="719" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="657">Sadly almost no one returns, much less recovers, from a case of meningitis as severe as mine. The last evidence of any activity in my neocortex was in the first hour, so in the emergency room and afterwards I demonstrated only very pathological reflexes including severe brainstem damage.</p><p end="775" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="719">Given my gram negative bacterial meningoencephalitis, which I was found to have, and my descent into coma over three and a half hours, I had at best a 10 percent chance of survival at the very beginning. It only got worse. Mine was an absolutely lethal meningitis. My white cell count in my cerebral spinal fluid was 4,300 and a protein of 1,340. Both those numbers should be zero. In fact, the glucose in that fluid, normally 60 to 80, and maybe as low as 20 in a severe case of bacterial meningitis, went all the way down to one. None of the consultants in my case, from Harvard, UVA, Duke, or Wake Forest had ever seen that severe a case. My doctors never found a cause. The scan showed diffuse destruction of my neocortex with blurring of the gray-white junction over all eight lobes of my brain. No area was spared. Later in the week, off all sedation, my neurological activity was almost nil.</p><p end="845" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="775">With what's called a glass glaucoma scale, which in everybody in this room would be 15 and a corpse is three, my scale was ranging from three to five. This was a very severe meningitis. On day seven, with no residual neocortical function, brain stem badly damaged, reflecting the deadly nature of my illness, my doctors recommended, because I was down to a 2 percent chance of survival by that point, with a best case scenario that if I survived I'd spend a month or two in the hospital, be transferred to a nursing home,</p><p end="845" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="775">and die in a coma months later, hence, they recommended just stopping the antibiotics.</p><p end="845" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="775">My journey deep in the coma began in a very primitive unresponsive realm, which I later called the "earthworm's eye-view," the best consciousness my brain could muster,</p><p end="845" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="775">soaking in pus. My prior neuroscientific view would've dictated that the next step would be one of no awareness at all. Yet, it was just the opposite, like the blinders coming off. I ascended into far more crisp, vibrant, ultra real realms of pure joy, love,</p><p end="845" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="775">and understanding, realms I called the "gateway in the core," far too rich and complex to fully describe.</p><p end="910" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="845">Soon thereafter I started to return to this world, but with my brain so wrecked that I had no memory of words or language, nothing of Eben Alexander's life before coma, any religious concepts, et cetera, yet I knew the entire ultra-real odyssey that I had just been deep in coma, went [spelled phonetically] so extensive it seemed to last for months,</p><p end="910" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="845">even though it had to fit within seven days of earth time. Words came back to me over hours and days, childhood memories over weeks, and knowledge of brain-mind consciousness of more than 20 years' experience in neurosurgery came back over two months. My doctors have no explanation at all for my full recovery. Other cases of medically inexplicable healing do occur in transcendental near-death experiences, like those of Anita Moorjani and Dr. George Rodonaia. In the 36 hours after emerging fromcoma, I was in and out of a delusional, paranoid, psychotic nightmare that was completely different, not even in the same ballpark, when compared to the ultra-reality of the deep-coma experience in the gateway in the core.</p><p end="963" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="910">Those experiences deep in coma seem almost seem to weigh too real to be real. My doctor's believing that the brain creates consciousness, and knowing the destruction they had seen in my brain, had told me that I could not have had any such experience in the depth of coma, and therefore just to forget about it. I knew I'd experienced something and sensed that it had to do with the fundamental flaw in the models of consciousness and the -- and the role of the neocortex. Early on, I tried to explain all of this as a brain-based phenomenon based on my old paradigm, writing it up as a report for the neuroscience literature. It's important that when I was emerging from that coma, I saw six faces at the very end. And these were faces that were very important in helping me to realize that the entire coma experience happened between Days 1 and 5 of my coma, and not at the very end.</p><p end="1018" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="963">Over those weeks of recording my experience after coma, I also began to talk with my doctors and review my medical records, especially neurological examinations and the scans, and came to realize just how deathly ill I was and how there was no way that such an ultra-real crisp and vibrant experience could have happened in my physical brain.</p><p end="1018" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="963">Modern neuroscientific ideas of the neocortex and consciousness would dictate that I should have experienced nothing at all beyond that earthworm's eye view. I wrote the entire experience down, 20,000 words that I wrote over six weeks, before I read anything about near death experiences. I have never read that literature before.</p><p end="1018" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="963">Initially, I was very worried that the memories would fade. Those memories are as sharp today as when they happened. Memories of the delusional paranoid psychotic nightmare that occurred over those 36 hours after I came out of coma faded within weeks.</p><p end="1077" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="1018">Very different origin. I had never read NDE literature before, and was shocked to find that the experience seemed hyperreal in over half of NDE accounts, and the memories do not fade like those of hallucinations, dreams, confabulations, or drug effects. People recount their own NDE stories to me by the hundreds, usually starting -- I'd never told anyone this before, but even from over 50 years ago, as if they happened yesterday, I came to see that the similarities in the NDE and afterlife literature far outweighed the differences. And the commonalities across cultures, beliefs, continents, and millennia indicate an underlying constant reality of that realm. Many of the petty differences are due to our being so restricted by our earthly language. This is not like we're describing atrip to Disneyland. Personal biases and religious beliefs might taint the telling of those stories. But the core similarities remain striking.</p><p end="1143" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="1077">[inaudible] --</p><p end="1143" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1077">Thanks, John. It's a pleasure to be here defending such a cheerful and uplifting proposition, as death is, in fact, final. Driving around the streets of Los Angeles, where I live, you can't help but notice these gigantic billboards telling us "All Men Must Die."</p><p end="1143" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1077">Turns out they were advertisements for "Game of Thrones," but I thought that they were advertisements for --</p><p end="1143" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1077">laughter</p><p end="1143" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1077">-- our event here tonight. It's a similarly -- you know, not quit as happy message as we might like to accept. Fortunately, we can open Dr. Alexander's book. It begins with a quote from Albert Einstein. Einstein says, "A man should look for what is, not for what he thinks should be," to which I would like to reply, "Exactly."</p><p end="1200" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1143">laughter</p><p end="1200" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1143">applause</p><p end="1200" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1143">We human beings are not always perfectly rational. Let me tell this shocking news toyou. We are bundles of cognitive biases. And one of the strongest biases we have is that we go easy on propositions that we would like to be true. What we should, in fact, do, is go especially skeptical on propositions that we would like to be true. And even I want it to be true, that death is not final. But we should hold something like that to an extraordinarily high standard of evidence. So, what are we actually being asked to accept? What should we expect the world to be like if death were not, actually final? For one thing, I would expect that the existence of souls persisting in the afterlife should be perfectly obvious. It should be just as clear that heaven exists as it is clear that Canada exists. But in fact, it seems that the souls persisting in the afterlife are kind of shy.</p><p end="1263" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1200">They don't talk to us, except sometimes they do talk to us. I would expect, also, that when people did have near death experiences, and really talked to other souls in the afterlife, that they would come back with consistent, interesting, non-trivial stories to tell. But in fact, when Christians have near-death experiences, they often say they've met Jesus. When Hindus have near-death experiences, they meet Hindu deities. There was a little girl who had a near-death experience, and she met a portly man wearing a red cap. She met Santa Claus. And we are told by some defenders of this that, well,</p><p end="1263" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1200">Jesus dressed up as Santa Claus so as not to scare the little girl. Possibly, that is true.</p><p end="1263" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1200">But we should be asking, are there other plausible explanations? I especially think that if we went and had a life after death and then came back to visit us, bringing some message back, that message would -- should be as useful as possible. We are told that,</p><p end="1263" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1200">you know, people have after death experiences, and they come back saying, you know what?</p><p end="1309" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1263">Love is really important. I agree with that. But actually, I knew it already. What I would like to know is the cure for Alzheimer's disease. What I would like to know is something that I didn't already know brought back to us. But it seems that the souls in the afterlife tend to speak in platitudes. The story that we're told of life after death doesn't really hang together. What we have are personal testimonies like that from Dr. Alexander. So people say, with very sincere voices, that what they experienced was totally real. And I have no doubt in the sincerity of this testimony. What I'm asking is, is it possible that our brain is telling us that something was real, but that thing does not actually correspond to something that really happened. And when you ask it that way, the answer is obviously yes.</p><p end="1365" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1309">Our brains are fooling us all the time. Steve Novella, my partner, will tell us about the neuroscience behind this. But basically, our brains are not like video recorders or photo albums. They're more like little theaters. When we try to remember something, it'smuch like imagining something that hasn't happened. It's more like running a script than reviewing a tape. And that's why, when we dream, when we hallucinate, when we have a near-death experience, it is just as vivid as something that actually happened. In the legal community, they will tell you that eyewitnesses who tell you that -- have a certain sincerity and conviction that their eyewitness testimony is true, that conviction is essentially uncorrelated with now true it actually is. The vividness or reality of a memory does not tell us that it was really real. So what is going on? We had this informal idea that there is a soul that sort of is a blob of spirit energy that takes up residence near the brain and drives us around like a soccer mom driving an SUV.</p><p end="1424" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1365">But we've known for a long time that this picture doesn't make sense. Back in the 1600s, princess Elizabeth of Bohemia carried on a correspondence with Ren&#233;</p><p end="1424" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1365">Descarteswho was trying to defend mind-body dualism. And Elizabeth demands, no,</p><p end="1424" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1365">how could something immaterial like the soul affect something material like the brain or the body? Descartes was never able to answer that question. And these days, science has gone way beyond that. We know a lot more about what is happening. We can literally see memories being formed. We can see the chemical changes in neurons. So the soul is supposed to also have memories. How do the memories get from the neurons to the soul? We know that brains often have false memories in them. Does the soul in the afterlife carry those false memories, or are they somehow corrected after death? We even know the laws of physics by which the atoms, the electrons, the elementary particles in our brains behave.</p><p end="1487" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1424">We know the equations that the electrons that are responsible for chemistry obey. And there's no ambiguity in these equations. They could always be wrong. It is always possible to say, well, we just don't know what is going on. That's fine. But what we have is the evidence of every experiment ever done telling us that these equations are correct. To overcome that, we would need very, very strong evidence, just one experiment, telling us how the soul is pushing around the chemicals in our brain. But we don't have that. What science says is that life or consciousness is not a substance like water or air. It is a process like fire. When you put out the flame on a candle, the flame doesn't go anywhere, it simply stops. And that is what happens when we die. So we're faced at the end with two scenarios. One scenario says that everything we think we understand about the behavior of matter and energy is wrong in a way that has somehow escaped notice by every experiment ever done in the history of science.</p><p end="1554" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1487">And instead, there are unknown mechanisms that allow information in the brain to the transferred to blobs of spirit energy that persist after we die and can talk to the otherblobs of spirit energy, but don't talk to us, expect sometimes they do. The other scenario says that physics is right and that people under stress sometimes have experiences that are not actually real. On the basis of rationality, it not a difficult decision to choose between these two options. On the basis of emotion, it might be difficult. But we need to have the courage to live life here in the actual world. Thank you.</p><p end="1554" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="1487">applause</p><p end="1602" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="1554">Thank you. Since 1965, I've had the honor of interviewing thousands of people from all over the world who had near-death experiences. And unless you've been hiding in a cave somewhere for the last 40 years, you've all heard about this, that people on the brink of death tell us that they leave their bodies, and they go into a beautiful light which they find very difficult to describe. And in that light say that relatives or friends of theirs who have already died seem to be there to meet them and to help them through this transition. And they have panoramic memory in which they see all of the events of their lives displayed around them in a sort of holographic panorama of which they witness instantaneously.</p><p end="1670" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="1602">My assessment from 40-something years of working on this, and I will underline that word "assessment" is that in the words of the proposition, death is not final. But I want to translate a little bit to say that what I'm trying to say with that is that in my opinion,</p><p end="1670" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="1602">at death, personal consciousness is taken up into a more inclusive state of reality or frame of existence in a way that people who go through this find it very difficult to put into words. One of the most common things they say is, however articulate they may be, they say that this experience is ineffable, or indescribable. I want to emphasize here something at the very beginning. And please hear me out on this one. I have decided,</p><p end="1670" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="1602">or sort of assessed the situation, that there is a life after death.</p><p end="1723" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="1670">However, I want to say anybody who tells you in the year 2014 that that is a scientific matter is not thinking clearly. In 2014, the question of life after death is not yet a scientific question. I am not a parapsychologist. And I think parapsychology is a pseudo science. So there's a different frame of reference to think about this, though. And that is that reason is a much bigger category than science. Scientific method is about, say,</p><p end="1723" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="1670">400 years old. Reason itself is about 2300 years old, a much bigger institution that includes history and philosophy and literary theory and the law in addition to scientific thinking.</p><p end="1795" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="1723">So what I am suggesting to you is that the solution to the afterlife question is not going to come initially from science, but rather from, I think, the whole area of critical thinking and logic. As I look back on the debate that -- on near-death experiences that's gone on for almost 2500 years now, what strikes me is that a big part of the problem is that the format of the debate is basically twisted. Since Democritus and Plato fought this out 2300 years ago, the way we've debated this is we say that some people look at these near-death experiences, and they take it at face value, as Plato did, and they say, well,</p><p end="1795" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="1723">this is an indicator of an afterlife. Other people Democritus being an example, said, as Democritus famously did, "There is no such thing as a moment of death," implying that therefore what he's getting is that these near-death experiences are just the patient's perception of the winding down process of the body.</p><p end="1866" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="1795">The trouble with this whole debate is that that format of debate itself is incoherent. We can't keep debating it that way. Let me give you an indication of why. All of the elements that we think of as a near-death experience, getting out of the body, going into this light, seeing a panoramic review of one's life, seeing apparitions of the deceased occur very commonly, not just to people who almost die and are brought back, but rather to the healthy and uninjured bystanders at the bedside of someone else, shared death experiences, as I call these. As the person in the bed, it's fairly common that bystanders will say that they themselves leave their bodies and accompany their dying loved ones partway toward this light, or they see the apparitions of relatives and friends of the dying person come into the room.</p><p end="1910" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="1866">So my question is, if the causation of these near-death experiences is the physiological distress and the events going on in the brain, why should the bystanders who are not ill or injured have identically the same experience? So I think that we're into a situation with this now where really the problem has sort of outgrown the format that we use to debate about it. In my opinion, we really are on the verge of breakthroughs in thegenuine, and I will underline "genuine," rational investigation of the question of life after death.</p><p end="1974" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="1910">And in that context, I think there are two people in history who have more than anyone else I think stated this afterlife question very clearly and the major problems that come with it, Plato being one, who said that, "Whenever we talk about the afterlife, there's always going to be the narrative aspect, a story, because we've got to have some sort of story just to get thought about this kind of thing started, but also we've got to have some sort of set of concepts to link the -- these narratives with the statement of what --</p><p end="1974" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="1910">that there is life after death." I think that's coming. I think that we are on the brink of a breakthrough in rational study of an afterlife, but it's not going to come initially from science, but initially from the realms of logic and critical thinking. So thank you very much.</p><p end="1974" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="1910">applause</p><p end="2029" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="1974">Thank you. Thanks, John. I want to say thank you to the Intelligence Squared Debate for inviting me here. It's an honor to be here. So I'm going to convince you that you need to vote against this proposition because if you vote for the notion that death is not final then you -- that by necessity means that you are voting against the conclusion, the scientific position, that the mind is what the brain does. The mind is a process of the brain itself. You would have to reject that in order to accept that the mind exists without the brain. Well, how sure are we? How confident are we in -- as a scientific conclusion, which is what we're here to talk about, that the mind is essentially the brain?</p><p end="2095" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="2029">Well, we're very certain about that, and we're as confident of that as we are of anything in science. We have a mountain of neuroscience, countless experiments, that look for the neuroanatomical correlates of consciousness, of the brain functioning, of the mind.</p><p end="2095" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="2029">Everything that you think, feel, believe, is something that's happening inside the brain,</p><p end="2095" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="2029">demonstrably. But let's take that as a scientific hypothesis. If the mind is entirely thebrain, then what must also be true? Well, then if the arrow of causation's going from brain to mind, then if we change the brain, that should change the mind. And if we damage the brain, that should damage the mind. And if we turn off the brain, that should turn off the mind. Well, if all of those propositions are correct, that strongly supports the notion that the mind is essentially the brain, and that is, in fact, exactly what scientists have discovered over and over again over the last one to two centuries of neuroscience.</p><p end="2154" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="2095">I can give you -- I'm a neurologist, so I can give you tons of examples from my own personal clinical experience. But let me just tell you about one very interesting neurological phenomenon called Capgras Syndrome. This is a syndrome in which -- well,</p><p end="2154" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="2095">I'll give you -- I'll back up a little bit. So when you're looking at, let's say, the face of your wife or your spouse, what's forming on your retina is just shapes and shadows and colors and lines, but your brain has to construct that into an actual image. But then it also have to give meaning to the image. It has to tell you that these shapes are, in fact, a face. And then another part of the brain tells you, "That's not just any face. That's the face I know well. That's the face of my spouse, the face of my wife." Now, assuming,</p><p end="2154" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="2095">however, you have feelings about your wife -- let's assume that -- then --</p><p end="2154" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="2095">laughter</p><p end="2154" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="2095">-- there's also a connection between that part of your brain that tells you that that face is your wife to the limbic system. That's the emotional part of your brain. And that connects your emotions, your feelings about your wife to that image.</p><p end="2212" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="2154">So, when you see your wife, those feelings are connected to it. Those are all circuits that are happening demonstrably in your brain. Now, in Capgras Syndrome, that last connection is broken by a stroke, by damage, by something. So, when someone sees their spouse, they recognize them as their spouse. But the feelings aren't there. So,</p><p end="2212" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="2154">what do people conclude when this happens? Well, it's interesting. When people have brain damage, it affects how their brain constructs their image of reality, because as my -- as Sean was saying, are -- we don't have a tape recorder in our minds, in our brains.</p><p end="2212" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="2154">We are constructing reality and image of reality all the time. It's a very active process.</p><p end="2212" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="2154">And when you -- when that process breaks down, then your construction of reality breaks down. So -- and you usually don't have insight into that, especially initially,</p><p end="2212" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="2154">because we tend to assume that our experience is a real, continuous experience. That's also something your brain constructs.</p><p end="2271" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="2212">So, what do people conclude when they have this syndrome, that circuit is broken in their brain? They conclude that their wife, their spouse must be an impostor . That's the only explanation that they can come up with. There's, in fact, a documented case of a husband who murdered his wife because he was convinced that an impostor had replaced his wife, you know, with an exact -- you know, it makes no sense, but that's the only way his brain could make sense of its broken construction of reality. And there's endless examples of this. There's no limit -- there is no practical or functional limit that neuroscientists have encountered so far to the degree which we can mess with your mind by messing with your brain. Your -- your sense that you're in your body, that you control your body, that you separate from the universe -- basic fundamental things about your concept of yourself and your experience of reality are all things demonstrably happening in the brain, and we could turn it off like a switch. Now we actually have the technology to do that.</p><p end="2337" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="2271">So, given the mountain of evidence that the mind is the brain, we wouldn't reject this easily. Do near death experiences provide such compelling evidence that there is mental activity outside of brain activity, that we need to reject the mountain of neuroscientific evidence that's growing every day, that tells us that the mind, in fact, is the brain? Well,</p><p end="2337" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="2271">I think the answer there is definitely no as well. There are -- as Sean said, there are stories -- anecdotes, compelling narratives. We're all about compelling narratives. That's what our brain does -- that people have had very unusual experiences. We don't doubt that they have had, you know, life-altering, unusual experiences. Whenever your brain is constructing reality in a different way that you're not used to, that's going to be a very weird, profound experience. It's going to be memorable. It's going to be amazing.</p><p end="2337" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="2271">Astonishing, even. We have no doubt about that. But it's demonstrably something happening in the brain. What we don't have are any documented cases of mental activity occurring when there could not be brain activity.</p><p end="2404" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="2337">Now, proponents will often say that, "Well, but the person remembers being, you know,</p><p end="2404" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="2337">in the emergency room, or they remember -- they have these memories that were forming while their brain wasn't functioning." But we don't know that. There is no case in which that's been documented. They easily could be forming their memories when they're coming out of their -- whatever state, whatever coma that they were in. Dr.</p><p end="2404" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="2337">Alexander even says he had a prolonged recovery. We have no idea what was happening in his brain during that period of time. When people are in a coma, there's still some break activity. There are animal experiments showing that sometimes even during an acute stress, there could be even a burst of neural activity. Who knows what kinds of astonishing memories are occurring there? We have a reality testing module in our brain, a circuit in our brain that says, "This feels real to me." And that testing module could break down. And then things -- you don't test reality. It just seems hyperreal. Every element of a near death experiment -- experience can be duplicated,can be replicated with drugs, with anoxia, with lack of blood flow, by turning off circuits in the brain.</p><p end="2455" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="2404">Every single component is a brain experience that we could now reproduce. And we're zeroing in on the exact circuits in the brain which reproduce them. That's why you must vote against this proposition. Thank you.</p><p end="2455" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="2404">applause</p><p end="2640" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="2572">No.</p><p end="2640" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="2572">Well, I think the important thing to point out is I get asked to give a lot of talks at medical groups, neurosurgery and other surgical groups, physician groups, because they realize the power of the medical situation. And I think this is what certainly grabbed me and challenged me within weeks after my coma is my knowing mybrain mind consciousness came back, and I started to review the records to reveal just how sick I was. I think the problem is that any other reason for being in deep coma, I probably would have been stuck because usually if there's some part of the neocortex that's still working, you could make an argument that that part was part of the process of putting it all together.</p><p end="2701" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="2640">But I think the important thing to point out is, with my neocortex so badly damaged, it became very difficult to try and come up with a way to explain how this very rich,</p><p end="2701" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="2640">elaborate set of memories occurred.</p><p end="2701" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="2640">Well, it was a very real experience that had no way of occurring in my physical brain.</p><p end="2701" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="2640">Now, initially, I looked at all kinds of possibilities; could it have happened early going in,</p><p end="2701" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="2640">could it have happened coming out, was there some way that other structures in thebrain or some part of brain was participating and generating this very long, elaborate journey? And yet that's where I kept running into trouble with it.</p><p end="2764" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="2701">Well, I think that Steven can talk about the specifics that might have been going on in the brain. But my emphasis is on weighing two different comprehensive pictures here.</p><p end="2764" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="2701">We have personal testimony from someone who says he experienced something, and it's very real and says that, well, we can't imagine that, even as a neurosurgeon, he just doesn't know what could possibly have been going on in his brain that would make that happen, therefore let's throw out all of the laws of physics. And I think that that is not nearly enough.</p><p end="2764" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="2701">No, that's not at all true. In fact, they still teach quantum mechanics, right?</p><p end="2764" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="2701">They do. I could teach it right now --</p><p end="2764" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="2701">Because I think it's important to point out, from my point of view, what drove the Founding Fathers at that field into mysticism was the fact that getting at the very depths of trying to understand subatomic reality they were led to believe the consciousness,</p><p end="2764" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="2701">the observing mind actually played a role in the unfolding of what was being observed.</p><p end="2814" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="2764">And I think that that mystery, to my satisfaction, has not really been solved in a way that says that the concerns of people like de Broglie and Dirac, Einstein, Bohr, and others,</p><p end="2814" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="2764">that they were trying to understand how consciousness influenced them.</p><p end="2865" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="2814">Well, I believe at some point science can be very useful at determining a lot of this.</p><p end="2865" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="2814">I think that -- in my view, this is all about how understanding the true nature of consciousness, soul and spirit, has a lot to do with helping to take physics to the next level in terms of understanding --</p><p end="2865" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="2814">The thing about Einstein, Bor, de Broglie, et cetera, the founders of quantum mechanics,</p><p end="2865" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="2814">is that they're all dead, and they have been dead for many decades. And we know what's going on much better now than we did back then. They were inventing quantum mechanics, and occasionally they toyed with the idea that somehow consciousness had something to do with the fundamental laws of quantum mechanics. Now we know better.</p><p end="2936" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="2865">We know how laws of quantum mechanics help explain how electrons move in the brain, and there's nothing in there --</p><p end="2936" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="2865">Well, it's -- I can only quote MIT physicist Scott Aaronson who says, as far as he can tell,</p><p end="2936" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="2865">quantum mechanics is confusing, and consciousness is confusing, so maybe they're the same.</p><p end="2936" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="2865">laughter</p><p end="2936" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="2865">applause</p><p end="2936" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="2865">You know, really, I think the end reality, what we're dealing with here is not a scientifically decidable issue, but a philosophical question. And what it's called is the mind-body problem, probably first articulated in the West by Pythagoras, but there have been many, many different theories of it. The one that's current in the neurosciences is called epiphenomenalism, which says, in effect, that there is no independent reality to what we experience as consciousness. But it's a secondary byproduct of the primary reality which is the brain and the electrochemical events going on in the brain.</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="2936">In my opinion, that's a philosophical statement, really. And my answer is, I don't know.</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="2936">I think the mind-body problem is still unresolved.</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="2936">I think, you know, Dr. Alexander said that the experience that he remembers -- again, I don't doubt he has a memory of a profound experience -- that it could not have occurred as he was coming out of his coma. But you have no basis for that statement, I don't think, that you have no sense of time. Your brain also constructs your sense of time. And when your brain is only partially working, you can have experiences that are hyper-real, that are both bizarre, that it's hard for you to reconstruct. And then your memory struggles to sort of construct a narrative that makes sense. It takes these bits and pieces of things that were firing in your head when you were in this semi-conscious state, and it constructs a narrative out of it based usually culturally on your pre-existing beliefs.</p><p end="3068" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="3001">You know, near-death experiences, whether, --</p><p end="3068" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="3001">-- as Moody said [unintelligible] in a cave, in a cave [unintelligible] --</p><p end="3068" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="3001">Perfectly consistent with what we know about the brain.</p><p end="3068" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="3001">Well, I would say the --</p><p end="3068" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="3001">Well, the interesting thing to me in looking back on it is the fact that, you know, I started for a very long time in what I call this "earthworm eye-view," a very primitive, coarse,</p><p end="3068" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="3001">unresponsive realm that had absolutely no kind of interactivity to it, and yet I remember that prolonged period. And that's what I said earlier is that the next step beyond that should have been one of no awareness at all, and yet what really happened was the blinders coming off and emerging into this far grander reality that was --</p><p end="3068" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="3001">-- which was much crisper than my [inaudible] --</p><p end="3118" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="3068">Well, to have that be an explanation, one would want at least some part of the neocortex still in a state that could participate because all of our modern thinking in neuroscience --</p><p end="3118" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="3068">-- is that there really was no part of my brain -- I mean, the factors that showed me when it happened, which was between days one and five and not at the end on coming out of it, basically those are part of the experience itself that to me were very difficult to explain, because they showed that it happened when my doctors told me my brain was way too sick to manufacture anything.</p><p end="3177" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="3118">Well, we don't know and he didn't give an answer to the question of when did those memories form? We don't know. They were not necessarily happening when you were at your worst. And when you were at your worst, there wasn't the kind of functional monitoring that we would've needed to know that your brain was not functioning at all.</p><p end="3177" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="3118">We don't know that. We saw anatomically, we had edema, swelling, and that certainly would have kept you unconscious, but you weren't getting an fMRI, a PET scan, or an EEG as far as I could see anything that you've written or said about it that would have documented zero brain activity. You can't say that. Nobody can say that. And even still, the memories that you have now were not necessarily formed when you were at your deepest part of the coma.</p><p end="3244" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="3177">They could've been forming in the hours and days when you were coming out of the coma. Then you had a later delusional period, but at different points in time, different parts of your brain were working or not working, and you were constructing reality in a very bizarre way, in ways that we can reproduce with drugs and hypotension and, you know, with electromagnetic stimulation of different parts of your brain.</p><p end="3244" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="3177">No, I would say that's not true at all. There are tremendous examples of people encountering souls of departed loved ones, learning information that they couldn't possibly learn in any other way. You had said earlier that there were no cases of any of these memories being generated when the brain was out, and yet there are examples of that, where the brain -- people under deep anesthesia, with complete circulatory arrest,</p><p end="3244" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="3177">things like that, where they do have some astonishing stories of getting information that it doesn't seem to be any other way that they could have gotten it. So those cases are out there.</p><p end="3244" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="3177">But those cases are not controlled or documented, so, in other words we don't know that they couldn't have gotten that information any other way</p><p end="3287" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="3244">A lot of those cases I've read, that they're like cold readings, you're getting information that is either plausible or later was retrofitted to the scenario. It's all a lot of special pleading, the same kind of information you get from a psychic. It's not controlled scientific information. There are, in fact, attempts at putting controls in place like putting playing cards on top of a shelf that could only be viewed if you were actually floating above the ceiling. And to the extent that those have been done, no one has been able to demonstrate any information that could only have been obtained while they were extracorporeal, floating above their body. And, by the way, we could make you float above your body.</p><p end="3346" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="3287">Yeah, you can go to Eben.</p><p end="3346" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3287">Yeah, I hope it's not insulting. It's certainly not ad hominem because the message is that nobody can be trusted. I think that that is part of what science has taught us, that if someone makes an extraordinary claim, the very first questions we should be asking ourselves are, number one, is there a different, simpler alternative explanation? And number two, how would we know if our purported explanation were false?</p><p end="3410" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3346">How would we disprove it? How could we possibly test this idea? And I think that, you know, when you look at the bigger picture of how the universe works, how the laws of physics work, the enormous success of understanding matter, energy, the brain, life --</p><p end="3410" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3346">everything that we've had -- there's just an enormous presumption against the idea that somehow, through ways that there are no equations, no experiments, or no direct evidence to tell us, the information in our brains persists after we die and is there forever and talking to other people who died. So, it's just a matter of presumption.</p><p end="3410" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3346">There's plenty of things that I would like to be true -- and I have been tricked into believing they're true. So, I know that I should be especially skeptical about them.</p><p end="3410" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="3346">What I would say about what Sean says is I agree with it up to a point, in the sense that,</p><p end="3410" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="3346">yes, I love physics, too.</p><p end="3463" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="3410">I was an astronomer from the age of seven and so on. And I accept there's a physical realm and so on. But that doesn't rule out that there could be a state of being that doesn't operate by physical principles. I noticed, Sean, when you were trying to think of some other realm, you were thinking in terms of energy or soul substance or whatever.</p><p end="3463" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="3410">But I'm talking about something entirely different. There's no inconceivability in thinking that everything that we know is true. And yet, there is a higher dimension or a higher domain of existence that sort of -- in which this one is included.</p><p end="3463" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3410">But this --</p><p end="3463" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3410">-- I mean, that's -- I think that's a perfect thing to have said in this debate, because it illustrates the difference here.</p><p end="3534" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3463">No evidence was given for this claim. No reason to believe it was given. All we are given is, "Well, maybe it's true and you can't absolutely disprove it." Maybe it is conceivable.</p><p end="3534" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3463">We have laws of physics that tell us how the moon moves around the earth. And they work very well. It is conceivable that there are also angels living inside the moon, gliding it around in exactly the way that Newton's Laws tell us. But we don't take that seriously as an idea, because there's no need for it or evidence for it. So, the question is not is it conceivable that there are other realms. The question is, is the evidence in favor of that other realm so overwhelming that it causes us to dismiss the enormous successes of physics, chemistry, biology and neuroscience?</p><p end="3534" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="3463">No. I would say absolutely not. It doesn't require you to dismiss the findings of science to &#8211;</p><p end="3534" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3463">Come over here to this side. We'll welcome you. We'll put your chair over here --</p><p end="3534" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3463">laughter</p><p end="3534" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3463">applause</p><p end="3534" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3463">Raymond Moody:And yet, you know, I think it's entirely conceivable that there's some other domain of existence over this that some people gain access to it sometimes.</p><p end="3598" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3534">And I know hundreds and hundreds of them.</p><p end="3598" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="3534">And how would we know if there weren't?</p><p end="3598" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="3534">You know something? You're right about the false of viability problem, Sean. That's very big in the afterlife question. But I think the way that this is going to work out is that what we need to do is prepare people in advance, before they ever have a near death experience, in new ways of thinking about these things. You know, the standard -- the standard objection to mystical experience has always been -- as A.J. Ayer put it -- that if the mystic tells us that he can't possibly describe what he experienced, then he's got to admit that he's talking unintelligibly when he talks about it. And that's the problem that we can change, because I think it's --</p><p end="3671" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="3598">What my argument --</p><p end="3671" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="3598">Yes. Yes. My argument is that when thousands and thousands of people whose judgment I trust and other -- in all other circumstances, a lot of medical friends --</p><p end="3671" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="3598">John Donvan:Okay. Give us one example, because I know you've written about this, examples where people who were not the person lying in the bed, but other people --</p><p end="3671" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="3598">Okay.</p><p end="3671" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="3598">Okay.</p><p end="3671" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="3598">And artist I met a couple of years ago, Jeff Olson, by name, a very well-known graphic artist, had a horrific car crash in which he lost his leg, he -- his wife was killed instantly,</p><p end="3671" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="3598">and he had a profound near-death experience.</p><p end="3719" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="3671">As he was thinking about this, what am I going to do about this?" his doctor had not been informed about this. So he decided to write this story up, and then he wanted to use the name of his doctor. So he called the doctor and invited him to lunch. The doctor came and Jeff told him the store I have his near-death experience, whereupon the surgeon said, "Well, I've never told anybody this, but that night you were in the hospital I knew that you weren't going to die. Your wife was talking with me in the surgery room. And the --"</p><p end="3719" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="3671">Yes.</p><p end="3786" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="3719">And so did the scrub nurse also had an experience of vivid sense of presence and seeing the -- so my point here is that it's not proof, but at a certain point, you know, where do you draw the line and --</p><p end="3786" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="3719">-- give people respect?</p><p end="3786" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="3719">Well, we want to know what's really, really true, not just what seems to be true, what we want to be true. And, you know, again, our brains are narrative generating machines. It tries to construct a story that makes sense to us, appeals to us, stream --</p><p end="3786" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="3719">puts everything together seamlessly. And you know, we can have what we believe -- we have memories of experiences that mean something to us, but don't really relate to reality. We know this is true.</p><p end="3839" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="3786">If you accept that level of evidence -- and this is not about respect. I believe that people have these memories of these experiences. It's just about the interpretation of them.</p><p end="3839" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="3786">Anyone. I mean, think about it.</p><p end="3839" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="3786">But all we have is a story constructed after the fact. We have similar stories about people being abducted by UFOs, seeing big foot, any weird kind of experience you can imagine. If you accept this level of evidence, then you have to believe every paranormal claim out there because we have that level of evidence for thousands of stories that are conflicting in mutually exclusive, often culturally dependent. It's simply not acceptable.</p><p end="3839" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="3786">And we know -- we know for a fact that the brain can absolutely manufacture those memories, come to absolutely believe a story like that, that's absolutely not true.</p><p end="3888" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="3839">I would say the brain does not create consciousness. That is something a lot of scientists, those interested in neuroscience are far along that pathway. Now it's called the hard problem of consciousness. In fact, no neuroscientist on earth can give the first sentence to explain the mechanism by which the physical brain creates consciousness.</p><p end="3888" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="3839">applause</p><p end="3888" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="3839">We don't have to know how the brain creates consciousness.</p><p end="3888" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="3839">In order to know that it creates consciousness. That it creates consciousness, we absolutely know, just like we don't have to know how the earth generates gravity to know that it generates gravity. There's no question we have gravity even though we haven't untangled the deepest understanding of every possible thing.</p><p end="3949" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="3888">So yes, we don't know exactly how the brain creates consciousness, but the evidence can only lead to one interpretation, that it is consciousness. The consciousness is what the brain does, no question.</p><p end="3949" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="3888">As I said, no neuroscientist on earth can give the first sentence to explain a mechanism by which the physical brain gives rise to consciousness.</p><p end="3949" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="3888">I don't -- I disagree with that because there are -- there's consciousness research. There are researchers who are doing a very good job of making progress of understanding consciousness as a neurological phenomenon. We certainly are not all the way there of understanding exactly what it is. It's a very difficult nut to crack. But that we are not at the -- but not knowing the mechanism is not the same thing as saying it's not possible,</p><p end="3949" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="3888">or it's impossible, or we need a nonphysical mechanism. We certainly don't.</p><p end="4014" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="3949">Well, it's not a black or white thing. We have some knowledge. We don't have complete knowledge about it. It's like saying, do we understand -- do we understand everything about genetics? No. But we know that DNA is the molecule of inheritance.</p><p end="4014" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="3949">That's not questionable.</p><p end="4014" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="3949">But not one sentence. Give the first sentence of how you would trace from the physical brain that it gives rise to consciousness.</p><p end="4073" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="4014">Yeah, I think William James was kind of right about that, that whatever experience one has one can say that by definition almost there's some correlated state of the central nervous system. The question of reality is an entirely different question. Can I imagine that maybe by taking some substance someone could gain access to some other kind of reality? Yes, I can imagine that. However, I think it boils down to the particular, doesn't it? I think you have to look at a much broader set of information to make a -- but generally speaking, yeah.</p><p end="4199" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="4140">Well, I think that, to me, is a very interesting question. The number out there is roughly 15 percent, 20 percent of people who have a medical situation that might lead to a near-death experience, about 15 to 20 percent seem to report them. That's a historical figure that I think is probably low because it comes from an era when we weren't asking people to volunteer that kind of information.</p><p end="4257" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="4199">I think the actual number is probably higher. If I had just come back from my earthworm eye view, you know, that very prolonged initial phase, that very dumbed-</p><p end="4257" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="4199">down consciousness that I think was the best my brain could do, I would have had a hellish NDE. Turns out that hellish NDEs are probably, what --</p><p end="4257" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="4199">-- 3 or 4 percent.</p><p end="4257" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="4199">A near-death experience. And the hellish ones are quite rare by comparison, 3 or 4 percent. My own feeling is that that is because they're incomplete, that souls don't go in with quite the oomph and that exactly in my case, I went in with plenty of oomph and went through that phase and up into the much higher levels of ultra-reality.</p><p end="4257" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="4199">Yeah, I mean, it&#8217;s perfectly compatible with the neuroscientific hypothesis of these experiences depends on what parts of your brain are working and not working at any given moment. What's the mechanism of your being in a coma or unconscious? Was it traumatic? Was it lack of oxygen?</p><p end="4313" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="4257">You know, we could put pilots in a centrifuge, spin them up until they pass out -- a lot of them have near-death experiences, too, they're not near death, but we're depriving their brain of blood flow -- you know, with similar numbers, very, you know, profound,</p><p end="4313" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="4257">memorable, vivid experiences. So it just depends on the particulars of what parts of the brain are working or not working.</p><p end="4313" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="4257">There is -- as I said, 3 or 4 percent of people have hellish NDEs. I believe -- I believe there's actually a reality to that realm, to those lower spiritual realms, that you can see referred to back in the Tibetan Book of the Dead, Egyptian Book of the Dead. I mean,</p><p end="4313" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="4257">it's something that's been referred to for a long time.</p><p end="4368" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="4313">For me, you know, I'm open to evidence for anything. What I would need to see is some information that the people having the experience gained through no other mechanism.So -- and there are experiments ongoing -- preliminary ones have been negative, there are bigger ones ongoing -- to see if people could, for example, look up on the top shelf and see a card that's placed there, that you could only see if you were actually floating above, near the ceiling, so that would be compelling evidence. I mean, it would need to be enough to -- that would be enough to me to at least take it seriously, but then to be -</p><p end="4368" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="4313">- to say that it's probably true, you need as much evidence as we have for the neuroscientific model which says it's not possible.</p><p end="4428" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="4368">I could be convinced of anything if the evidence were sufficient.</p><p end="4428" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">Yeah, I think that -- you know, the idea that we could be convinced of another realm in addition to the natural world is obviously, "Yes." There's a million pieces of evidence that would help convince me. None of -- I mean, if this -- if there's a ghost in the room that could lift up that glass right now, then I would be convinced.</p><p end="4428" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">laughter</p><p end="4428" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">For those listening on the radio, the glass is not moving, and it --</p><p end="4428" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">laughter</p><p end="4428" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">-- it never moves when you do this.</p><p end="4428" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">applause</p><p end="4428" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">And we live in a world that looks exactly like there's only the natural world.</p><p end="4428" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">I don't want to die.</p><p end="4428" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">laughter</p><p end="4428" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">I want to live after I die, maybe not for infinity years but for a few hundred thousand years I could amuse myself.</p><p end="4428" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">laughter</p><p end="4428" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">Sadly, as a very wise philosopher once said, "You can't always get what you want."</p><p end="4428" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">laughter</p><p end="4428" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4368">applause</p><p end="4750" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="4685">So, as I said -- as I was saying, I'm a skeptic, so I'm in a perpetual state of doubt about everything. I need lots of evidence and logic to convince me. And all we could say within the scientific realm is what does the best evidence tell us today? Right now, we have lots of evidence that we could be highly confident in the conclusion that the mind is what the brain does. And we have no compelling evidence -- only narratives and really dubious evidence to -- against that proposition, against that notion, or for the notion that there is some consciousness separate from the brain. So, the scientific conclusion today is that the mind is the brain.</p><p end="4796" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="4750">If new, dramatic evidence comes to light that changes that, I will happily move along with the evidence.</p><p end="4796" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4750">I think -- you know, it's a great question because there's this image -- like, when we're teaching high school and science, that it's a bunch of facts that are absolutely established, whereas professional scientists like to brag about the fact that -- like Steven just said -- that, you know, we're always skeptical and we're always ready to throw out everything. And both are true, but because there's some intermediate ground. There are many, many things that science does not understand, and we're hoping to get better at it. Many, many things. And there are also some things that science does understand and are not going to go away. This table is made of atoms. We will improve our understanding of what an atom is, what the elemental particles and fields are that make it up, how they interact. That is not finished yet.</p><p end="4863" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4796">We can do better. But a million years from now, our best scientific understanding will still say that the table is made of atoms. In my judgment, the current status of our scientific understanding, the parts that we're not going to give up, are enough to conclude that death is, in fact, final.</p><p end="4863" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4796">applause</p><p end="4924" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4863">Yeah, I mean, I think that, again, there is evidence in favor of those kinds of things.</p><p end="4924" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="4863">There is other evidence against those kinds of things. And the kind of remote seeing or telepathy or telekinesis or clairvoyance that is being talked about here is in utter and complete violation with everything we understand about the current laws of physics.</p><p end="4924" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="4863">Even if we put plausibility aside, a hundred years of parapsychological research has not been able to produce one bit of compelling replicable evidence that shows that it's a real phenomenon.</p><p end="4989" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="4924">My response is that the evidence for things like telepathy, precognition, remote viewing, out of body experiences, past life memories in children, the afterdeath communications is overwhelmingly positive evidence that it exists and is real. For those out there in the scientific --</p><p end="4989" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="4924">applause</p><p end="4989" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="4924">-- community who want to know more, I would urge them to check the book,</p><p end="4989" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="4924">"Irreducible Mind: Toward a Psychology for the 21st Century," 800 pages of very dense science data and analysis that shows the absolute reality of nonlocal consciousness in all of those forms. It shows that we have a long way to go in beginning to understand anything about consciousness and that the model that brain creates consciousness and that we can only know things locally with our connected senses is completely false and disproven by a lot of scientists, not just in that book, and those who participated in that,</p><p end="4989" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="4924">but in multiple other books.</p><p end="5042" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="4989">And, I mean, for example, the afterlife experiments Dr. Gary Schwartz, that's a pretty powerful documentation of the power of mediums. There are --</p><p end="5042" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="4989">Basically, did a scientific assessment of mediums and their ability to work especially with --</p><p end="5042" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="4989">Well, established that they could communicate and know things that only could be known by the departed relative.</p><p end="5042" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="4989">Demonstrably not true. I mean, everything you said is the exact opposite of the truth.</p><p end="5042" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="4989">applause</p><p end="5099" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="5042">Gary Schwartz's methodology was massively flawed. It's been absolutely picked apart by other scientists. He essentially allowed himself to be bamboozled by charlatans and by cold readers. He did not produce anything reliable, anything that I would consider to be credible scientific evidence.</p><p end="5099" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="5042">So that's the bottom line.</p><p end="5156" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="5099">It doesn't go away. It's up in your head. They're just not continuing to live. It's exactly the same place the flame goes when you put out the candle.</p><p end="5156" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="5099">I would say it's more a question of the information, you know, than the energy. It's not a conservation issue around energy.</p><p end="5209" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="5156">People often use that one to argue against a soul being able to influence the material world. I would say it's much more a question of the information, and especially when you -- as I said, when you -- for example, a very renowned skeptic and scientist, Carl Sagan admitted that past life memories in children, the evidence for that is overwhelming.</p><p end="5209" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="5156">That's not true. Come on, Carl Sagan, please.</p><p end="5209" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="5156">He said that in his book, in his book, "The Demon Haunted World," on page 302, he says exactly that.</p><p end="5209" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="5156">laughter</p><p end="5209" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="5156">I've read that book a hundred times. Carl Sagan did not believe in past lives. He did not believe in anything paranormal or supernatural. That is just not true.</p><p end="5281" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="5209">Yeah, I mean, I haven't read that particular study, so I don't have any detailed information about the specifics, or I'd certainly be interested in taking a look at it. But just the notion that somebody can explain something beyond their experience is not unusual. We are actually pretty creative, inventive people. You know, our human brains have no problem inventing things that we haven't directly experienced. So again,</p><p end="5281" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="5209">I would need to see details that could not be explained as a brain experience in order to find it compelling.</p><p end="5336" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="5281">Well, I would like to go back to what Sean had said about how consciousness is very confusing to us as is quantum mechanics. And I would put out there, I think they're related. There's a reason why they're both so confusing.</p><p end="5398" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="5336">And that's -- you can chuckle, but in fact, that's what drove brilliant people like Einstein and others into mysticism. And in fact, I would say that that mystery has only gotten much deeper over time. We have not answered that at all. In support of my claimearlier about brain damage allowing enhanced function, which really goes against the materialist model that Steven talked about earlier, I point out two very common examples in clinical practice; acquired savant syndromes, in which strobe brain trauma,</p><p end="5398" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="5336">autism, can allow super human mental function, something that's often seen, that certainly has no explanation from the brain makes mind model; and also terminal lucidity, in which demented elderly patients often have periods of great clarity,</p><p end="5398" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="5336">especially around the time that they are encountering souls of departed loved ones that are there to escort them over. And I would say that these very commonly observed phenomena really demand a much deeper model of consciousness than we get out of the materialist models.</p><p end="5457" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="5398">I'll point out that Dr. Wilder Penfield wrote a book in 1975, "The Conscious Mind." He probably still holds the record for having stimulated the brain in awake patients more than any other neurosurgeon. And never once did he duplicate any kind of situation of free will. He concluded very strongly that the mind consciousness is not created in the physical brain. And I think it's important to point out that the pure materialism fails. It's a hard problem of consciousness and at the enigma of quantum mechanics, that the brain actually confines and limits consciousness, that science acknowledging consciousness, soul and the spirit becomes much stronger than the overly simplistic science of reductive materialism. Death of the physical brain and body is not final.</p><p end="5457" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Eben Alexander" start="5398">Thank you.</p><p end="5512" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="5457">So up until a couple hundred years ago, every culture in the world believed that there was a life energy. They knew intuitively, they sensed that there was something fundamentally different about living things from nonliving things, and they hypothesized that there must be some energy, some [unintelligible] vital, spiritus, chi, whatever you call it, that fundamentally makes living things different than nonliving things. But over the next 100, 150 years, basically the 19th into the 20th century, we discovered biochemistry and genetics and developmental biology, and all different principles of biology, until essentially there was nothing left for the life force to do. We hadexplained everything that living organisms do, and we explored the blurry line between living and nonliving, and we realized that there is no fundamental difference there. It's just, as you get increased complexity at some point you cross this fuzzy line, and you're doing a process that we call "life." Well, we're kind of going through the same process though maybe a little bit delayed with consciousness.</p><p end="5571" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="5512">You -- we understand that the brain causes consciousness. We certainly don't understand a lot about how it is produced exactly. But we're making progress. Our research paradigms are working quite well, thank you, and we're making lots of progress. It's just as irrational, if you will, to hypothesize that there is some magical energy or some non-corporeal thing, stuff, that is consciousness, as it was 200 years ago to say that, "Well, because we can't explain life, then we need a life force." We don't need a brain force, a mind force any more than we needed a life force 200 years ago.</p><p end="5571" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="5512">The fact is that the neuroscientific community is progressing relentlessly with the paradigm that is materialist, reductionist. We're looking for neuroanatomical correlates of everything that the mind does, and that research program is very, very successful.</p><p end="5571" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="5512">And it -- how well an idea advances in science is more telling about how valuable it is,</p><p end="5571" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="5512">how true it is, than what our current state of knowledge is.</p><p end="5639" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Steven Novella" start="5571">Our current state of knowledge is always going to be incomplete. It doesn't mean that our ideas are wrong or are weak. That's why you have to vote against this proposition.</p><p end="5639" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="5571">First of all, I want to say that to me to this day the notion of life after death is very counterintuitive. I think as a nonreligious person I had no background in that. It never occurred to me, as a young astronomy buff, that there might be something beyond this.</p><p end="5639" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="5571">I've been through a process now of 40+ years that finally drove me into this situation where I'm sort of forced to say, almost against my will, that "Death is not final," there is a life after death.</p><p end="5703" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="5639">Basically what happened to me was that hearing thousands of people with near-death experiences, hundreds of people with shared death experiences who had the identical experience we call a near-death experience, except they weren't ill or injured, they were simply there at the bedside of someone else who died, and I have seen joint transcendent experiences where, for example, a physician and a critically ill patient would have some sort of joint transcendent experience at the same time. That leads me to be forced almost into a position to say that I trust these people's judgment. It seems to me that they've been somewhere where I haven't been, and I can begin to put a little picture together of what they're talking about. So for that reason I would say I'm onboard. I think there is life after death.</p><p end="5760" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="5703">So vote, vote, vote for the afterlife.</p><p end="5760" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="5703">laughter</p><p end="5760" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="5703">applause</p><p end="5760" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Raymond Moody" start="5703">And --</p><p end="5760" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="5703">When I was about six years old, I had an emotional formative experience that apparently many other people share similar things. I was in bed, you know, going to sleep, sort of thinking about the day and so forth, and I started crying. I was just bawling uncontrollably, so much so that my mom heard me from her bedroom and came running in, saying, "What is wrong?" And I said, "Some day, our grandmom is going to die. And someday, you're going to die. And someday, I'm going to die. We're all going to die."</p><p end="5820" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="5760">And you know, she had to explain, "Well, yes." And so forth. And she had her own version of the story. And the reason I'm telling this story because even as convinced as I am that death is final, I have absolutely no desire to belittle the people in the room who disagree, who feel the other way. This is an incredibly important, central issue to our lives. I personally am convinced by the overwhelming scientific evidence from physics,from neuroscience, et cetera, that there is one world, the natural world. Biology is a process that can end. And death is final. And to me, that fact -- the finitude of our lives --</p><p end="5820" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="5760">gives enormous poignancy and importance to the finite number of years that we have here on earth. Our lives here are not dress rehearsals. This is the act. This is the one performance that we get. That does not remove meaning or value from the lives we're leading now.</p><p end="5881" is_meta="false" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="5820">It gives -- it forces us to give meaning to everything we do, because we only have a finite number of things to do. If evidence came in on the other side, I would change my mind quickly, if the evidence was good enough. But I think that we're past the point where it's a scientifically interesting question. I think that we know enough to conclude that death is final. And personally, I think that that is okay. Thank you.</p><p end="5881" is_meta="true" speaker="Sean Carroll" start="5820">applause</p></transcript></debate>