<debate duration="6181" url="https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/embrace-common-core"><speakers><speaker name="Carmel Martin" position="for"><description>Exec. VP, Center for American Progress and Fmr. Assistant Secretary of Education</description><bio>Carmel Martin is the executive vice president for policy at American Progress. She manages policy across issue areas and is a key member of CAP&#146;s... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Michael Petrilli" position="for"><description>President, Fordham Institute &amp; Co-Editor, &lt;em&gt;Knowledge at the Core&lt;/em&gt;</description><bio>Mike Petrilli is an award-winning writer and president of the Thomas B. Fordham Institute, one of the country&#146;s most influential education-policy... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Carol Burris" position="against"><description>Principal, South Side High School &amp; Blogger, Washington Post</description><bio>Carol Burris, Ed.D. has been the principal of South Side High School in Rockville Centre, New York since 2000. She was named the 2013 NASSP New York... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Frederick Hess" position="against"><description>Resident Scholar and Director of Educational Policy Studies, AEI</description><bio>An educator, political scientist and author, Frederick M. Hess studies K-12 and higher education issues. His books include Cage-Busting Leadership... Read More</bio></speaker></speakers><results><result against="13" for="49" submitters="live" undecided="38" when="before" /><result against="27" for="67" submitters="live" undecided="6" when="after" /><result against="50" for="16" submitters="online" undecided="32" when="before" /><result against="50" for="32" submitters="online" undecided="16" when="after" /></results><transcript><p end="179" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="113">Well honestly John, we weren&#8217;t thinking about political backlash. We were thinking about what was best for kids, but I do agree that the issue has become a little bit of a political football, which I think is unfortunate and I hope people will focus on what&#8217;s best for children.</p><p end="179" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="113">My partner is my sometimes opponent actually, always my friend and distinguished colleague, the brilliant Michael Petrilli.</p><p end="234" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="179">I was hoping for "good -looking," but I'll take brilliant. That's good -- that's okay.</p><p end="234" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="179">Yeah.</p><p end="234" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="179">A ffirmative .</p><p end="234" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="179">Right.</p><p end="234" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="179">Absolutely. On the left and the right.</p><p end="298" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="234">Well, over half of my ninth graders last year refused to take the Common Core test when they were in eighth grade, wi th their parents' permission. So, I think it's safe to say they're not fans.</p><p end="361" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="298">My partner is the good looking and charming Rick Hess.</p><p end="361" is_meta="true" speaker="Carol Burris" start="298">laughter</p><p end="361" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="298">John Donvan:Ladies and gentlemen, Rick Hess.</p><p end="361" is_meta="true" speaker="Carol Burris" start="298">applause</p><p end="361" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="298">Rick, you're at the American Enterprise Institute. You are an education policy studies resident scholar and director of that section. You hav e a blog called "Rick Hess Straight Up &#8221; at Education Week. Like your opponent, Mike, you are an executive editor for Education Next. And it's also interesting to note, you and your opponent Mike co -wrote a book in 2006. So, are there no more collaboration s down -- down the road for the two of you?</p><p end="361" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="298">You know, John, we wrote that book on No Child Left Behind after Mike -- who had been an enthusiast -- came to share my more measured take. I'm hopeful that history will eventually repeat itself.</p><p end="478" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="421">Thank you very much. It's a real honor to be here. I was just surprised -- I just saw Rick press the undecided button. So, that was interesting. We'll see how that goes. It is such an honor to be here today. Let me tell you a little bit about what our game plan is, that -</p><p end="478" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="421">- Carmel and I. We've been together all afternoon, we've been scheming about this. I will start by talking about what it means to embrace the Common Core . Then I will talk about some of the problems in our educ ation system and frankly in previous waves of reform that the Common Core is trying to address.</p><p end="540" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="478">Carmel then is going to talk about the process of developing the Common Core , the role that educators play, the role that evidence played, as well a s talk about some of the equity issues that are at stake here, how the Common Core can help to narrow the achievement gap. Now, what you won't hear us argue is, first of all, that Common Core is going to solve all of our nation's educational problems because, of course, it won't. You're not going to hear us say that the Common Core are perfect. They were not handed down from Mount Sinai, they are not set in stone, right, or we're going to hear plenty of concerns about this individual standard or that individual standard, so you won't hear us say that they're perfect. And you're not going to hear us say that it's all going perfectly out there around the country, because, of course, it's not all going perfectly out there around the country. This is a big country, 50 million kids in public schools, 100,000 of those schools, and like any ambitious reform, it's a work in progress,</p><p end="540" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="478">okay ? But what you are going to hear us argue is that despite all of that you should still embrace the Common Core .</p><p end="597" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="540">Now, why is that? Why should you embrace the Common Core ? And what does that mean? In our view, to embrace the Common Core is, f irst of all, to embrace the idea that our schools should have standards, all right, that doesn't sound so radical, and that the standards that we have should be set at a high enough level to indicate that our students are ready for what comes next. And that means kids graduating from high school, that they're either ready to go and succeed in college or to go and get a goodpaying job. Now, what you might have to understand is that this is a radical departure from how we used to do this. States did have standards before the Common Core, but,</p><p end="597" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="540">by and large, they were set at a very, very low level. And so what that meant is that students could meet those standards, they could pass the standardized tests connected to those standards, but it didn't mean that they were ready for success later on. In fact,</p><p end="597" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="540">in many states it didn't even mean that they were at grade level. And so we had a system that was giving a lot of false information out there to students, to teachers, to parents alike.</p><p end="658" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="597">So, to emb race the Common Core is to say, "Let's embrace standards that are set at this college and career ready level." It's also to say that we should embrace the idea of moving to next generation assessments, right, tests that measure these standards, that are w orlds better than the tests that we've been living with for the past two decades. Many of us in this room as parents or as teachers, we know that there has been this huge focus on standardized testing in this country. And unfortunately, by and large, tho se tests have been terrible, fill in the blank, multiple choice tests, tests that don't do a good job measuring what students know and that encourage very low level kind of teaching and learning in the classroom. But now, after four years, we're finally g etting to the point where there are new assessments coming connected to the Common Core that are going to be much more like advanced placement exams or international baccalaureate exams like the ones that Carol uses in her school, and this is our chance to move to those assessments. So, if you embrace the Common Core, its high standards, it s next generation assessments, that's what we are moving towards.</p><p end="715" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="658">Now, what's the problem we're trying to address? Every study that's ever been done on American education comes to pretty much the same conclusion. It's not that our schools are failing, though some are failing, but on the large, it's not that schools are failing, it's that our schools, by and large, are mediocre when compared to schools ov erseas. They're in the middle of the pack. They're not the best schools in the world,</p><p end="715" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="658">they're not the worst schools in the world. They're in the middle of the pack. And it's not just our demographics. It's not just because we have a lot of childhood p overty,</p><p end="715" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="658">though we do. Our rich kids are in the middle of the pack compared to other rich kids around the world, poor kids, middle class kids, high achievers, low achievers. Throughout the education system, it's this concern around mediocrity. And we've k nown this for 30 years. And we have been working hard at trying to address that. And we've made some progress, right? Poor and minority and low achieving kids today are reading and doing math two to three grade levels ahead of where they were</p><p end="715" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="658">back in the 1990s. That's incredible progress.</p><p end="771" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="715">And our public education system deserves credit for making that progress. And almost certainly it was because back in the '90s and 2000s , states decided to set standards, to have tests that measured those standards, and to have accountability systems to make those standards stick. And it -- again, we've made real progress. But because the standards were set so low and because the tests ha ve been so easy, all of the focus has been getting the lowest performing kids over that very low standard, right? And that's led to great progress for the kids at the bottom but it hasn't done much for the kids at the middle or the kids at the top because they were so far ahead of those standards that it didn't get much traction with them. At the same time, it's come along with a lot of unintended consequences, and we know about those, too, teaching to the test,</p><p end="771" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="715">narrowing of the curriculum, driving out a lot of the joy that we want to have in our school s, okay? And again, Carol, Rick, many others have been very eloquent on this point.</p><p end="839" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="771">This is our chance to embrace the Common Core , is to fix all of that, to move to a system with much higher standards but also better tests that give better information but that also encourage better teaching and learning in the classroom. Carmel and I had a chance today to meet with a group of teachers, many of them are here in the room tonight, to tell us how i t's going with Common Core . And it's not perfect. There's issues,</p><p end="839" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="771">and there is bumps in the road, but they talked about these higher expectations for their students that some of these kids, they couldn't -- you know, four years ago they couldn't believe t hat the kids could perform at the level that they're performing now,</p><p end="839" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="771">but these higher standards have pushed them in that direction. Now, Rick and Carol are going to say that we should not embrace the Common Core, and I don't know if they're willing to hug the Common Core or kiss the Common Core or fist bump the Common Core , so I'm not -- we'll see what their position it, but what do they want? Do they want us to go back to the old standards, the ones that were set way too low, that gave everybody this fal se impression that everything was fine? Do they want us to stick with the -- still the standardized tests, these rinky -dink standardized tests that we've lived with for 20 years?</p><p end="893" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="839">Do they want to follow the example of Oklahoma, the one state in the country that has repealed the Common Core and replaced it with something else right away, and in Oklahoma today, today in Oklahoma schools, teachers did not know what standards they were supposed to teach to. They don't know six months from now which tests they're going to be held accountable to, but I guarantee you it's not going to be one of these next generation assessments because there's no time and there's no money for that. It's going to be one of these rinky -dink assessments instead. Lots more to talkabout throughout this debate, but for all of those reasons, this is why you should vote to "Embrace the Common Core ." Thank you.</p><p end="954" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="893">Good evening, and thank you for inviting us to this very important debate about the quality of the Common Core standards. I say "quality " because this isn't a debate about whether or not we need standards. Of course we do. And this isn't a debate about whether or not schools should improve. That's a given. Rather, this is a debate that asks whether or not the Common Core standards are so remarkable and so sound that we should embrace them as the standards by which every American child is both educated and judged. In a little while, Rick is going to explain the flaws in the design of the standards. As a lifelong educator, I'm going to explain the flaws in the standards themselves. Let's begin with kindergarten. Listen while I read this Common Core</p><p end="954" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="893">kindergarten standard.</p><p end="1019" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="954">"Compose and decompose numbers from 11 to 19 into 10 ones and some further ones. Example, by using obj ects or drawings and record each composition or decomposition by a drawing or equation. Example, 18 equal 10 plus eight. Understand that these numbers are composed of 10 ones and one, two, three, four, five, six, seven,</p><p end="1019" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="954">eight, or nine ones." Now, I ask you, should that be a standard for a five -year -old?</p><p end="1019" is_meta="true" speaker="Carol Burris" start="954">laughter</p><p end="1019" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="954">Or to put it another way, do the standards know and match what we know now about childhood development? Well, in 2010, when the standards were first rolled out,</p><p end="1019" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="954">experts said, "No." Five hu ndred early childhood experts, pediatricians, psychologists,researchers, and teachers found the Common Core standards to be so developmentally inappropriate that they called for their suspension in grades K through 3 .</p><p end="1075" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="1019">Back to Louisa Moats , one of the few early childhood experts that were on the team that created the literacy standard, is now one of their most outspoken critics. Why? Because the Common Core standards disregard decades of research on early reading development and instead y ank up difficulty levels at every grade. So, how could the developers of the Common Core get it so wrong? The Common Core</p><p end="1075" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="1019">standards were built backwards from grade 12 down to pre -K. But kids don't grow backwards, they grow forward, and their development is unique and uneven. The Common Core requiring that kindergarteners count from one to 100 by ones and 10s,</p><p end="1075" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="1019">even though we know that most five years old can count to 20, is as silly as expectin g all two -year -olds to be potty trained.</p><p end="1134" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="1075">Research did not guide the development of the Common Core standards. And then there is the math. Most of the time, when we think of standards, we think about what topics should be taught at different grade levels. But the Common Core goes beyond and seeks to influence how math should be taught, often in confusing ways. Here&#8217;s a first grade example. &#8220;Use strategies such as counting on, making ten. E xample, eight plus six equals eight plus two plus four equal ten plus four equal 14, decomposing the number leading to a 10. Example, 13 minus four equal 13 minus three minus one equal ten minus one equal nine, and creating equivalent but easier or known sums . Example,</p><p end="1134" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="1075">adding six plus seven, by creating the known equivalent, six plus six plus one equal twelve plus one equal thirteen. &#8221;</p><p end="1194" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="1134">Now, when you listen to that, are we surprised that we have created complicated homework problems that comedians joke about and that make children cry? This is why parents and teachers are rebelling. In one year, in the bluest of states, California and New York, the Common Core has moved from majority approval to majority disapproval. In one year, teacher support for the Common Core has dropped 30 poin ts. This is not a Tea Party rebellion. This is a parent rebellion and it&#8217;s happening because the Common Core has moved from paper to practice, from the ideal to the real. And then yes, there are the tests. Even as the consortia developed national tests,</p><p end="1194" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="1134">New York State is giving Common Core tests twice. And guess what, they&#8217;re multiple choice tests and they don&#8217;t look anything like the IB.</p><p end="1375" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="1314">Thank you John and thanks to Intelligence Squared for bringing this debate here tonight and including me in it. I want to start by telling you the story of Janelle, a young woman from Philadelphia who I spoke to recently. And whose story embodies why I feel so strongly that the Common Core is a crucial step forward for American education. Janelle is an African American woman from the north side ofPhiladelphia. Her parents believed in the power of education to transform liv es. They had one overriding message for their daughter : Do well in school and you will be the first person in the family to go to college.</p><p end="1431" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="1375">Janelle got the message. She worked hard. She took honors courses. She got all As. She was her vice president of her senior class. And she graduated in the top of her class. She was number three in her class. She diligently applied to college, and she and her parents ecstatically celebrated when she not only got into college, a public four -year institution in Pennsylvania, but got a full scholarship. But it wasn't very long after going to college before she realized that she had been duped. The As she'd earned in her honors courses in high school seemed to bear little relationship with what it took to succeed in her college -level courses. In subject after subject, she struggled, becoming more and more dejected. She explained to me how one of the problems that she encountered was that in high school, her teachers helped her translate her textbooks.</p><p end="1496" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="1431">But when she got to college, her professors expected her to be able to do that for herself and then analyze the information, as opposed to just understanding it. And her --</p><p end="1496" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="1431">she didn't have those skills. They hadn't taught them to her in her high school. As a result -- as a result, Janelle 's GPA dropped and she lost eligibility for her scholarships.</p><p end="1496" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="1431">Now, the good news is, she did -- she has managed to return to college as a sophomore.</p><p end="1496" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="1431">She was able to fill the gap left by her scholarships with student loans. Many children in her -- in her situation would have give n up and dropped out. The Common Core is for Janelle and for the thousands of students who are giving it their all but not getting their money's worth. Now, I agree with something Rick has said before, which is that standards are meaningless unless they're translated into effective instruction. As Mike noted, the Common Core is not a silver bullet for all that ails our education system. But it is an essential building block.</p><p end="1556" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="1496">And for students like Janelle who, for generations, have been shortchanged by the old,</p><p end="1556" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="1496">failed system, new standards will help ensure they are never left behind again. We know what we were doing before wasn't working. We see remediation rates as high as one in four college students who are not ready for college -level material. And that translates,</p><p end="1556" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="1496">just he re in New York, to $80 million in wasted resources that could be spent on other supports for our students to be successful. And that doesn't even address the students like Janelle who are not in remediation, but are struggling with college level content.</p><p end="1556" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="1496">S ome schools, like the one that Carol runs, have adopted International Baccalaureate programs or advanced placement courses to supplement the old state standards, butwe can't rely on visionary principles like Carol -- or a patchwork of programs to c lose our nation's gaping achievement gaps or prepare future generations to compete with China.</p><p end="1617" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="1556">Now, I'd like to cut -- clear up a couple misconceptions about the Common Core that had been promoted by the Glenn Becks of the world. First the Common Core was not developed in secret and was not developed by the federal government. This was an initiative led by Democratic Governor M arkell of Delaware and Republican G overnor Sonny Perdue of Georgia. Back in 2008, virtually all of the governors, w ith the exception of Rick Perry and Sarah Palin, were strongly supportive of it. Unlike the previous patchwork of standards, the Common Core was developed with significant input from educators and content experts, like the National Council of Teachers of M athematics.</p><p end="1617" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="1556">The authors consulted teacher unions, the civil rights community, college leaders, and business leaders. The standards were revised based on over 10,000 comments from the general public. And contrary to the assertion of the opposition, most tea chers are not opposed to the standards, and indeed strongly support them.</p><p end="1672" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="1617">Now, I appreciate that there has been a great deal of controversy about the way the standards have been implemented and concerns with how test scores are being used in o ur education system. I think those concerns are real. And we should -- we should address them. But -- and teachers, when asked about the standards in the context of accountability -- particularly accountability for themselves -- their own performance --</p><p end="1672" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="1617">they're hesitant about the standards. But despite these concerns, a Winston poll in early August revealed that two out of three teachers approved of the adoption and believed they are what their students need to be successful. And when implementation is done</p><p end="1795" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="1735">It's a pleasure to be here with you this evening to talk about this issue.</p><p end="1859" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="1795">Notice that we -- I am not here to argue that the Common Core is malicious or atrocious. I am here to argue that we should not embrace it. Now, you might wonder why. I heard Mike try to recharacterize the Common Core as meaning that one is f or standards, for high standards, and for great tests. Well, if that's the Common Core , then I'm for it, too. But that's actually not the Common Core. That is Mike trying to turn the Common Core into a vague principle that we like good stuff. Carmel talked about Janelle. I got to tell you, if you think there was any state in the Union, circa 2009, that said, "It's state standards," or, "It's okay to graduate high school as an illiterate," that's actually not the facts on the ground. The standards bear only a passing resemblance to what is asked of kids and what actually gets taught. But that's all kind of a distraction. There's a couple reasons that we should absolutely not embrace the Common Core . First, the Common Core does not solve the problem that it was designed to solve.</p><p end="1918" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="1859">The motivation behind the launch of the Common Core was what we called the "race to the bottom," after No Child Left Behind, the concern that states were playing games with their test scores in order to make their schools look better than they were. Common Core was supposed to help address this. It doesn't. It doesn't because in order to get a lot of states to sign on, partly with the inducement of federal money,</p><p end="1918" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="1859">the advocates for the Common Core brutally compromised the design of the thing. Common Core allows every state to set its own cut score, so every state can decide what is or is not passing. The Smarter Balanced Consortium, one of the two federally funded testing consortia, gives s tates a 12-week testing window. They can decide where in a 12 -week period during the spring they would like to test their kids. That means some states can have their kids get 50 percent more learning time than other states.</p><p end="1977" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="1918">This is a time -test ed way to inflate your test scores. And only about 35 to 40 percent of students are actually going to be tested in the spring with the federally funded Common Core assessments. Other states have been bailing in droves, and we've now got a slew of states whipping up half- baked assessments for next spring that certainly aren't comparable and very likely may be lousier tests than the one they abandoned for the Common Core . So the bottom line is that Common Core actually not only doesn't solve the race to th e bottom problem, it may actually aggravate it. Second issue going on here is a number of strident claims were made for the Common Core . We are told that the Common Core is evidence based. We are told that it's internationally benchmarked,</p><p end="1977" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="1918">that it's rig orous. Well, that evidence is about as disciplined as Mike's reference to the -</p><p end="1977" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="1918">- his assertion that every study over 30 years -- just no, you can't make statements like this.</p><p end="2039" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="1977">There are tens of thousands of studies conducted of United States education, and they don't all show anything. The idea that the Common Core is evidence based? Look, what they mean is the folks sitting on the committees that wrote the Common Core looked at some statistics on the kinds of high school courses that college kids take, and they looked at some surveys of employers and college professors. That's fine. That's good. I'm glad they did that. That's not evidence of what needs to be or not be in the Common Core . In fact, I'm not sure what kind of evidenc e one would point to, to prove that children need to learn to multiply fractions at this grade rather than that grade. Frankly, these are judgment calls which reasonable people can disagree on. Lynn Fuchs, professor at Vanderbilt, who's got no dog in the Common Core fight, has pointedout that there's no empirical basis for the Common Core, that we don't know yet whether it makes sense to have this particular set of standards or not.</p><p end="2095" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="2039">Internationally benchmarked? What they mean is that people o n the committees writing the Common Core looked at some international standards, and they copied some, and they didn't copy others. The idea that the Common Core's more rigorous? Well, frankly, the Common Core ends high school math after algebra 2. Most state standards went beyond that. They included trigonometry and pre -calculus before the Common Core . Now, Mike and Carmel might say that they don't think that stuff's necessary or useful, but it's hard for somebody to convince me that these are undenia bly more rigorous standards when we're jettisoning the last two years of mathematics. Now, this would all be interesting enough and a reason to maybe go slow,</p><p end="2095" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="2039">but there's another piece to the puzzle, which is that Common Core is actually not just about wo rds on paper. It's also about theories of hypotheses about how kids will learn better.</p><p end="2150" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="2095">These hypotheses are baked into the Common Core , into the tests that have been designed to support the Common Core, and they have received shockingly little debate,</p><p end="2150" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="2095">given how radical they are. One is a fascination with what Common Core advocates called close reading. This is the idea that students ought to learn to read by deciphering the text -- preferably nonfiction, by deciphering the text without regard to other knowledge and without any personal reaction to the text. Now, I don't have a problem with close reading. It turns out when I taught high school two decades ago, I actually did a fair bit of this. But the idea that this is how every child at eve ry grade level in every subject across an ocean ought to experience reading? I find that a radical proposition. Common Core embraces something called conceptual math. You may have seen some of the worksheets or the YouTube videos.</p><p end="2217" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="2150">This is the stuff that Carol was talking about, the idea that elementary children in particular ought to master math by learning the concepts, not just the arithmetic, and the best way to master these concepts is by composing and decomposing lots of these numb ers in various drawing exercises. I don't have a problem with this as a way to teach kids math. I find it shocking that this should be the way all children of all performance levels across the nation ough t to learn it. Third, the Common Core</p><p end="2217" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="2150">embraces so mething called informational text, informational reading. At the high school level it wants kids to read 70 percent informational text. It doesn't want to do this in English class, which is why we are now looking at children in chemistry classes, for instance, reading EPA reports. The idea that you are going to learn science moreeffectively by reading EPA reports than by doing lab is a radical proposi tion. In some,</p><p end="2217" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="2150">given that the Common Core doesn't solve the problem, it has been sold based on exag gerated claim and calls for major changes of a certain value, it seems to me reasonable not to embrace the darn thing. Thank you.</p><p end="2277" is_meta="true" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="2217">applause</p><p end="2398" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="2337">I would say yes and no. You know, certainly they weren&#8217;t conceived in secret, but they were conceived by a very, v ery small group of people who were predominantly non-</p><p end="2398" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="2337">educators.</p><p end="2462" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="2398">And the input happened after the fact. Certainly as an educator, I had really no awareness of any of this going on and I stay very current. Until 2010, and then everything w as presented in one fell swoop. Certainly the president has made it very c lear that he is supportive of the Common Core standards but mostly what happened was Race to the Top. And that was a federal program. And if you look at some of the writings and went back to 2008, as the G overnors Association were talking about this,</p><p end="2462" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="2398">they were actually saying these are the kinds of incentives that we need.</p><p end="2462" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="2398">Right, Race to the Top was a sti mulus program that came into effect shortly after President Obama was elected president. The whole idea behind Race to the Top was that there were going to have to be radical changes in school s, adoption of Common Core standards or something similar., test ing programs, evaluation of teachers by test scores, and other things.</p><p end="2518" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="2462">And in order to get the money and we all desperately needed the money, states very,</p><p end="2518" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="2462">very quickly put together applications.</p><p end="2518" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="2462">Well , I would say again, this was an effort that was underway before President Obama was President Obama. It was led by a democratic and republican governor from very diverse states. They had the support of virtually again, Sarah Palin and Rick Perry don&#8217;t support much, but the other 48 governors were strongly supportive of it.</p><p end="2571" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="2518">And the Obama administration supported an initiative that was state led, that was driven from, I would argue , bottom up, not top down. And I think what we need to k eep in mind though, is even if--we&#8217;l l never know how many states would have adopted the standards but for the incentives provided by the federal government. But then the question before us right now is, given that it was something that was developed,</p><p end="2571" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="2518">through I would argue, contrary to Carol , through a very rigorous process. It brought teachers into the process. It brought the public into the process. And then onc e each state adopted it, there was process at the state level around the standards. So, then the question before us is, are the standards good for our students? And Mike and I think it is.</p><p end="2631" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="2571">Yes, I think first off, Carmel is playing, her characterization of the timeline is I think loose</p><p end="2631" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="2571">-- what the governor s supported in 2008 was the exploration of the idea of making some standards more common. I think most folks, in 2009, 2010, imagine there were maybe a dozen or 15 states that were, themselves, ready, unprovoked, to move forward and explore the Common Core. In fact, Mike, I'd like to hear your take, because you, for instance, have said that the federal government has been heavy -handed with Common Core and deserves to be chastened. In fact, you have encouraged Oklahoma gov ernor Ma ry Fallin to sue --</p><p end="2631" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="2571">I'm sorry.</p><p end="2631" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="2571">My apologies.</p><p end="2631" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="2571">Sure. No. Absolutely. My apologies for that. Mike, I'm curious on your response to Carmel, given that you have previously testified to the Indiana State Senate that the federal government has been heavy -handed with this refo rm and deserves to be chastened.</p><p end="2694" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="2631">A nd that you have, in fact, said that you hope th e Oklahoma Governor, Mary Fallin, sues the U.S. Secretary of Education because not th rough race to the top, but through waivers from No Child Left Behind -- you said, "Nothing gives a secretary of education the authority to push states around whe n it comes to those standards."</p><p end="2694" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="2631">I did. Yes.</p><p end="2694" is_meta="true" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="2631">laughter</p><p end="2694" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="2631">And it had a question mark at the end. That was good. Yes. Absolutely. And if we were here to debate the federal role in education, I would move over there. Maybe Carol would be over here. I'm not sure. But we are here to debate --</p><p end="2694" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="2631">-- to debate the Common Core , right? It is true. Look, the -- I think everybody is in agreement. I wrote an article recently with a strong opponent of the Common Core . We wrote together. Here are the facts. It started out as a state -led initiative. And then the Obama Administration came in and endorsed it. There's no doubt that it had a big impact in the number of states that got involved. And in my opinion, we would all be much better off if the federal government would now butt out. So, Carmel, maybe you can share that view with the Secretary of Education.</p><p end="2755" is_meta="true" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="2694">laughter</p><p end="2755" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="2694">Well, I would say --</p><p end="2755" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="2694">-- it's early to judge the implementation of the standards.</p><p end="2755" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="2694">I understand that.</p><p end="2755" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="2694">I would -- but I would say, although it's early, we do see some signs of success. And I would point to Kentucky, which was one of the first states to adopt the Common Core .</p><p end="2755" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="2694">Well --</p><p end="2755" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="2694">Okay.</p><p end="2755" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="2694">Well, I mean, I think that's just factually inaccurate.</p><p end="2818" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="2755">I think that the folks who got together to draft the new standards relied very heavily on the existing research that they had about what children needed to be able to do and what set of knowledge they needed to have to be successful in college and in good jobs.</p><p end="2818" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="2755">They brought in the people from the post -secondary sector, something that hadn't been done in K -12 education historically, which really is pretty illogical that that hadn't been done before. They brought in people from the business community to talk about what skills they needed their employees to have. They brought in content experts. They showed the standards to the associations that represent teachers in mathematics and E nglish language arts. And they took in their input. I think neither Mike nor I would say that each and every standard is perfect. But I think if you look at the process that was used in the development of these standards and compare --</p><p end="2818" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="2755">-- it to the process that was used under the old standards by most states, that it was very rigorous, and they did look at evidence. And you can --</p><p end="2818" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="2755">-- disagree, but they did look at evidence.</p><p end="2882" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="2818">No. I -- the truth of the matter is, one of the things that's very different about the Common Core that I spoke about, is unlike the old Massachusetts standards, the standards in New York -- which really just identify what kids should know at grade levels -- the Common Core standards create -- or contain what's called instructional shifts in practice. Six in ELA and six in [unintelligible].</p><p end="2882" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="2818">English language arts. Thank you. For example, the whole idea that it makes sense for yo ung children to engage in close reading -- there is absolutely no evidence that that's the case. At the high school level, yes. But not at the elementary level. There was no real research that was based on yanking up lexile levels. We know from years of developmental reading research that kids do best when they read independently with leveled readers. But the Common Core says no. The Common Core says predominant readin g should be on what is considered to be grade level, which has just been increased.</p><p end="2929" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="2882">And if the kids don't get it, well, the teachers should read it aloud. Well, let me tell you something. You learned how to ride your bicycle by riding your bicycle. You didn't learn how to ride your bicycle by having your dad never taking his hands off the bar.</p><p end="2929" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="2882">Yeah, and I'm so glad that you raised this, a couple times, this idea of clos e reading. And I spent the big part of the weekend talking to some reading experts getting ready for this question, and I think I have a better understanding. It's going to get a little weedy,</p><p end="2929" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="2882">but I'll get through it very fast. And it's this. We've had a system for years where we've said, "Okay, if a child can only read at the first -grade level and they're in fifth grade,</p><p end="2929" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="2882">we're going to give them first -grade level books, right, with the hope that over time they would get better. The problem is there's five or six rigorous studies showing by and large those kids were never getting better at reading.</p><p end="2996" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="2929">And that they're -- what the studies showed is what you really need to do is find ways to get the kids to read more challenging texts at their grade level, which means at first --</p><p end="2996" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="2929">and the teachers today helped explain this so, so much better than I could -- that the teachers start by reading it aloud, having the kids follow along. They do what they call,</p><p end="2996" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="2929">"scaffolding," over time. And over time, th ey start to teach the kids how to do this reading so that they can let go of the handlebar and they can ride the bike on their own. And kids who a re way behind grade level, including kids who are special education students, are never going to make progre ss if we don't challenge them with those grade level texts. This is what the evidence says, and the Common Core looks at the evidence.</p><p end="2996" is_meta="true" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="2929">applause</p><p end="2996" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="2929">Yeah.</p><p end="2996" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="2929">Mike, I hate to step on the applause line, but actually I think you conflated two things. You conflated close reading and Lexile. These are not the same thing.</p><p end="2996" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="2929">A lexile is gauging how complicated a piece of reading is -- a piece of literature. Look,</p><p end="2996" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="2929">close reading is a particular theory of how kids should read.</p><p end="3057" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="2996">David Coleman, president of the college board, the lead writer on the English Language Art s Standard, liked to talk about close reading as teaching kids to read like a detective and write like a journalist. Frankly, I think that sounds perfectly fine as one piece of how we teach children to read. I don't think that I'm a particular fan of the idea tha t every child in America from grades K to 12 ought to learn to write like a journalist.</p><p end="3057" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="2996">Right, but Rick, is that actually in the standards? Do the standards say that? No. What the standards say is that children need to read at grade l evel proficiently.</p><p end="3057" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="2996">Well, Mike, wait [laughs] a minute. This is, I think, the degree of ambiguity in the Common Core that drives a lot of people crazy, that at one level the Common Core is just a bunch of innocuous words on paper, you know, one of the eighth grade reading standards, "Compare and contrast the structure of two or more texts and analyze how the deferring structure of each text contributes to its meaning and style." This isn't very different from what most states previously had.</p><p end="3120" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="3057">These are a bunch of pleasant words on paper. I have no particular objection to them.</p><p end="3120" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="3057">The significance of the Common Core is that the advocates for the Common Core and the people who are designing the test talk very explicitly about, as Carol said, these instructional shifts, which have not been publicly debated, which got little public airing as 40 -odd states rushed to adopt the Common Core in 2009, 2010, and which portend a dramatic shift in how we teach 50 million children reading and math.</p><p end="3120" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="3057">I'm not sure these are bad things, but I sure as heck think we ought to find out more before we embrace them.</p><p end="3120" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="3057">But when there is evidence --</p><p end="3120" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="3057">-- as we have now in early reading -- there was evidence 20 years ago on phonics -- on phonemic awareness, that was finally incorporated into our schools -- now we have good evidence that these level texts, just having kids who are fifth graders reading fi rstgrade texts over and over again, has not been working. Now we have that evidence. It's time to follow the evidence. And that's what Common Core does. Not every point has that, but where there is evidence -- we know that calculator use in the first grade, not a good idea.</p><p end="3177" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="3120">The Common Core s says we should not be using calculators till the kids get older. These are dramatically more evidence based than the standards that came before.</p><p end="3236" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="3177">-- seen the evidence that level checks do not work.</p><p end="3236" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="3177">I -- no, I'm absolutely confident. Look, this has been the dominant way we have taught reading now for decades. And you look at our achievement in reading, and it is mostly flat. And you look at our achievement in reading for special education kids, for kids who are behind, and what you find is that they are not making progress fast enough. We've done better in math where we've made greater progress, particularly for poor kids, but in reading it's been slow. We've made some progress in teaching early reading because of phonics and phonemic awareness because there we finally followed the evidence.</p><p end="3236" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="3177">And what I'm saying is that we n eed to follow the evidence. The Common Core is saying that's what we need to do, follow the evidence. Kids deserve to be challenged.</p><p end="3294" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="3236">The teachers I talk to today, you know --</p><p end="3294" is_meta="true" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="3236">applause</p><p end="3294" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="3236">-- I mean, Carol's argument earlier -- the four words, "These are too hard," right?</p><p end="3294" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="3236">Yeah.</p><p end="3294" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="3236">Well, first, I just want to f inish Mike's thought there. I mean, when we talk ed to teachers today, they acknowledge that when the standards were first brought to their schools, they were concerned that they would be too hard for their children, but we heard things like reports that tea chers said, "Wow, I didn't think they'd be able to do it and they are," and talk about the joy that they've had in seeing their children meet that challenge. And I have to say, as a former civil rights attorney, it just makes me very nervous when people talk about how, you know, you need to --</p><p end="3294" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="3236">-- some kids can't reach the same expectations as other kids.</p><p end="3353" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="3294">Can I jump in?</p><p end="3353" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="3294">I am the last person on the planet that would ever say, "Some kids can't." I run an integrated high school, 16 percent of our kids are on free or reduced price lunch, and every one of them tomorrow who are 12th g raders will walk into an international baccalaureate English class. So, that's -- this is not about it being hard, it's about it being wrong. That's what it's about. It's about it being appropriate.</p><p end="3353" is_meta="true" speaker="Carol Burris" start="3294">applause</p><p end="3353" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="3294">Yeah.</p><p end="3353" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="3294">Yeah, like I said earlier the point -- the example that Carol made about being able to count to one -- to 100 in ones and tens, I know lots of five -year olds who can do that. And I think that if we ask children coming from all different backgrounds to be able to do that, they'll be able to do that.</p><p end="3414" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="3353">And, you know, I think that we have lots of evidence that we're -- what we're asking them to do under the old standards wasn't working, that --</p><p end="3414" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="3353">I'd be happy to take it. It's not a matter of too high or too low, it's a matter of silly and not right. For example, in the early grades, there are a lot of stan dards that are not developmentally appropriate, but then when you go up to the high school level, which Rick was talking about -- I mean, I was talking with my math teachers today.</p><p end="3476" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="3414">We have to implement Common Core geometry. Well, what does it do? It's a whole different course i n geometry based on constructions. Well, it worked out really well for the early Greeks, but it is not an effective strategy today. We actually tried it in our school a couple years ago in anticipation of the Common Core, and the kids were lost. Trigonometry has been stripped out of the algebra 2 class. Since I went to school back in, I hate to admit it, the 1960s, trigonometry was part of the course of studies in high school. Common Core has changed it. It's not algebra 2. So the problems that you hear is not, "It's too hard," or, "It's too soft," it's just not right at a variety of levels.</p><p end="3476" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="3414">Yes.</p><p end="3535" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="3476">Right.</p><p end="3535" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="3476">Right, is that their concerns are very well founded, as are the concerns of many ed ucators who have been complaining for years, decades now, that the tests we&#8217;ve been using to judge schools are not well designed. And they&#8217;re right. Those tests by and large have been very inexpensive tests. They&#8217;ve been set at a low level. They&#8217;ve been fill in the blank. And now we finally have this opportunity to move to much better tests with the Common Core , that are under development, that are coming this spring for the very first time in about half of the country. And this is our opportunity to now address many of those concerns. And for example, these tests will have a lot more writing on them than most of the other tests had. It&#8217;s very hard to test kids&#8217; critical thinking skills if it&#8217;s just multiple choice. Right, certainly hard to test their writing skills.</p><p end="3595" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="3535">Yet a state like Georgia has been trying to get by with a test that costs eight dollars per kid and therefore doesn&#8217;t have any writing on it. And what we&#8217;re trying to do here is to turn that page. And say look, there were maj or problems with the test under the No Child Left Behind era. We&#8217;ve heard those concerns and now we&#8217;re trying to get something better, something that I think that Carol and Rick have supported in the past.</p><p end="3595" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="3535">John Donvan:I&#8217;d appreciate it if Rick, if you w ant to step in, because we haven&#8217;t heard from you in a bit. And you look like you&#8217;re steaming over there.</p><p end="3595" is_meta="true" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="3535">laughter</p><p end="3595" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="3535">If you want to defer to your partner, please do.</p><p end="3595" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="3535">No , I always look that way. Two thoughts, one on testing and one just on the prior question. One, you know John, one way to think about this is it&#8217;s really we&#8217;re debating embrace the Common Core . Again I&#8217;m not declaring the Common Core to be atrocious or malicious. I am suggesting that the standard of proof for the Common Core is much higher than for old state standards. Massachusetts had had state standards in place for 18 years, give or take.</p><p end="3652" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="3595">Those standards had produced substantial and sustained improvements in student learning. If what Mike and Carmel had been advocating for, was taking these standards whose tires we&#8217;ve kicked for 15 or more years, and taking those national, I would have been very open to that. The idea that we have a bunch of design hypotheses about what kids should know, we think, maybe , and how they should learn it, maybe. The idea that we want to roll this out for 50 million children with little opportunity to see how this plays out or what it means, leaves me remarkably nervous. So for me --</p><p end="3652" is_meta="true" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="3595">applause</p><p end="3652" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="3595">So, for me it&#8217;s less about too high or too low. I think frankly we just don&#8217;t know. On the testing point, I mean, like I said at the beginning, I&#8217;m with Mike. I&#8217;m for good tests. I&#8217;m anti -bad tests. Mike and I are on the same page here.</p><p end="3652" is_meta="true" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="3595">laughter</p><p end="3652" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="3595">But I think the notion that the Common Core tests are good is an open question.</p><p end="3775" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="3712">I would say the Common Core standards very much drive towards teaching and assessment that is focused on creating problem solvers and good communicators, those kind s of skills. And we heard just today from a group of teachers that we talked to, that under the new assessments, they can&#8217;t teach to the tests anymore, because the tests are no longer about rote memorization.</p><p end="3832" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="3775">It&#8217;s about children being able to make inferences and digest the texts, so I think it goes exactly to the point that you me ntioned. The crafters of the Common Core did look at</p><p end="3832" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="3775">at PISA. They also looked at Massachusetts and they did borrow from places where they thought it was working, as well as looking into the evidence, so I think it really tackles the issue that you're talking abou t very effectively. And I think assessments aligned to those kinds of standards should really help us move away from a mode of rote memorization towards teaching in an enriched way.</p><p end="3832" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="3775">I think it's always helpful to have an example. Here's what's called the Research Simulation Task. The Research Simulation Task -- this is from P ARCC -- is an assessment component worthy of student preparation because it asks students to exercise the career and college readiness skills of observation, deduction, and proper use and evaluation of evidence across text types .</p><p end="3890" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="3832">In this test, students will analyze an informational topic presented through several articles, multimedia stimuli, the first text being an anchor text. Students will engage with the text by answering a series of questions and synthesizing information from multiple sources in order to write two analytic essays. I think that sounds great. Grade 3.</p><p end="3890" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="3832">That was Grade 3. You know what? If kids ca n do that at the end of Grade 3, I can retire.</p><p end="3890" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="3832">Just give them calculus in fourth grade and send all those Doogie Howsers off to college.</p><p end="3890" is_meta="true" speaker="Carol Burris" start="3832">laughter</p><p end="3890" is_meta="true" speaker="Carol Burris" start="3832">applause</p><p end="4012" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="3958">Sure. I mean, one, Carmel -- I mean, I think this point about Massachusetts, if I recall right, Mike, for instance, has argued that the Massachusetts standards were better -- or at least as good as the Common Core . So, yet -- I think let's be careful about imputing claims to the Common Core . Even folks who support them, I think, tend to be more measured about how good they think they are.</p><p end="4073" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="4012">Second, the Kentucky point -- the fact that you've got more kids scoring profi cient doesn't mean anything whatsoever. You can adjust a cut score in any direction you want. This has always been the concern with post -No Child Left Behind testing. So, the fact that Kentucky scores went up doesn't tell us a thing unless we know how Kent ucky is setting the score and [inaudible] --</p><p end="4073" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="4012">That's correct.</p><p end="4073" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="4012">That's correct.</p><p end="4132" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="4073">So, you know, my response would be, "Look" I think not embracing the Common Core</p><p end="4132" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="4073">says that if there are states where parents and educators and policymakers are sufficiently enthused about the work -- I think there's eight or 12 or 15 of these -- I thinkthey should proceed. And they can go down that road, and we can see how well it works and see what the results are. I think in other states we should absolutely, as Mike suggested, get the federal government the heck out of this question through No Child Left Behind waivers or anything else. We should feel comfortable with states either choosing to revert to the standards they had in place, highly regarded previous standards like Massachusetts', D.C.'s, Indiana's, or California's, because, remember,</p><p end="4132" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="4073">nobody hit the delete button on those old standards, on the curricula that ma tched, or on those assessments.</p><p end="4195" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="4132">I think it makes sense, before one does a dramatic and bold remaking of 50 -- of the schools serving 50 million kids, that we actually move deliberately and carefully for once and see how this works and what unanticipated changes lurk.</p><p end="4195" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4132">Well, you know, I know Rick spends a lot of his time writing books in a cave somewhere. I think he's been in a cave perhaps --</p><p end="4195" is_meta="true" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4132">laughter</p><p end="4195" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4132">-- because Ri ck is 2014. Teachers have been implementing these standards for four y ears in these states, okay?</p><p end="4195" is_meta="true" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4132">applause</p><p end="4195" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4132">So, you know, there are enormous --</p><p end="4195" is_meta="true" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="4132">inaudible</p><p end="4195" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4132">You know, there are enormous, enormous costs, financial, morale issues. You know,</p><p end="4195" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4132">teachers have put their heart and soul into teaching these standards -- I mean, we heard from some of these teachers today -- for four years. So let's be clear that this i s not now a hypothetical argument, "Should we move forward? Should we adopt the Common Core ?" Schools have adopted it. They're moving forward. And so now the question is,</p><p end="4195" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4132">"Should we go back and undo all the work of the last four years?"</p><p end="4261" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4195">And you've held this very high bar, both you and Carol today, that basically the Common Core have to be remarkable in order to go ahead. So if you're going to go back to those old standards, those lower standards, in the vast majority of states, what is y our evidence that we should move to those lower standards? Why aren't you having a high bar for that?</p><p end="4261" is_meta="true" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4195">applause</p><p end="4261" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="4195">[unintelligible] and that, I find to be a very frightening --</p><p end="4261" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="4195">-- I find to be a very frightening argument. I -- you know, I don't live in the world of talking points where I have to worry about changing my mind. I live in the world of kids,</p><p end="4261" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="4195">and I see what the Common Core standards a re doing to kids. I hear my teachers come in. I don't know what group of teachers you're talking to, but they're very different than the ones that I work with every day who come in, showing me bizar re worksheets, who tell me their children don't want to go to school anymore, that they hate school, that they want to be able to read interesting books instead of technical manuals.</p><p end="4317" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="4261">You know, we're really resilient smart people, teachers. Please don't think that we could not adjust. I've lived through four sets of standards since I've been in education. We can do it. We can do the work. We need the federal government to back off, and we need to have dialogues within our states where we ta ke -- maybe we start with the Common Core . We clean up what's a mess, and we make them actually better. You know, there is something about competition that is not a bad thing. If we are all doing the same thing in every state and doing it the same way, where will the new ideas come from? I really see the changes in my high school.</p><p end="4317" is_meta="true" speaker="Carol Burris" start="4261">applause</p><p end="4317" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="4261">And they're not positive.</p><p end="4439" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="4375">Well, I don't have the exact numbers in terms of how much time will be spent testing,</p><p end="4439" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="4375">but it is my hope that under these new better fairer fewer assessments under the Common Core that we can eliminate a lot of the testing that happens around the country un der the old set of standards and assessments, what we see across the country is districts layering on additional assessments on top. And I think as we move towards these better assessments under the Common Core that we can eliminate unnecessary testing. I think testing is a tough issue. It's something -- my kids hate it, and I have to explain to them why they have to do it and how it provides really valuable information to their teachers about how they're doing so they can help them to do better, just li ke when I bring my child to the doctor and they say, "I really don't want to get that shot,"sometimes you have to do things that aren't very pleasant. I think what's important is to make sure that in creating a culture around testing, we're not making children stressed out, we're not making them cry over the tests. And I think that part of that is professional development, the environment in the school around the tests.</p><p end="4500" is_meta="true" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="4439">applause</p><p end="4500" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="4439">We heard that -- we heard that from some teachers w e talked to today about how that's -- and that takes a lot of leadership in the school to make sure that it is being used as a tool to get better. I think Carol has made a lot of good points about the way assessments are being used, that we really should take a cl oser look at that --they do help create a negative culture around testing. But again, that's about how the tests are used, not what the standards should be and whether you should have the assessments so you can learn from them and improve practice.</p><p end="4500" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="4439">Yeah, in New York State, testing was increasing anyway, but under the Common Core it's gotten worse. You're talking about increases of 200 percent, for example, at some of the grade levels. You're talking about three da ys of ELA testing, three days of math testing, and a lot of it is really because of not only the Common Core itself, but also the policies that were also part of the Department of Education that Carmel worked for.</p><p end="4558" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="4500">So, that teachers now are evaluated by test scores which then added a lot of other additional tests. All of these things have come together at once, and kids are crying. I've had colleagues who -- they've had kids who've wet their pants. You know,</p><p end="4558" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="4500">kids want to do well on tests. They want to please their teachers. They want to please their parents. And when they find themselves reading and rereading paragraphs in order to do close readings and flipping back and forth, some of them really just start to give up. You know, in New Yo rk, we had 60,000 kids opt out of testing last year.</p><p end="4558" is_meta="true" speaker="Carol Burris" start="4500">applause</p><p end="4558" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="4500">We never had that. We never had that before.</p><p end="4676" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4613">Thank you. That's a great question. You know, this is key. And we've had these debates for a long ti me. Just to say that, you know, standards does not have to equal standardization, right? We want to make sure that our education system is linked to success for what comes next, and that means that if we're measuring student progress,</p><p end="4676" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4613">this should be against the real world and what they're going to have. But that does notmean that we have a standard way of getting there. Different schools have different approaches, different teachers have different approaches, and different kids are going to learn different ways, and that's all absolutely appropriate. What we don't want to have is a system that has standards that are set so low that we're giv ing the false impression that kids are doing fine when they're not. And, you know, Carol, I know you keep saying, "Well, it's not too high, it's not too low, it's just wrong." Go back to those old systems, okay? Colorado, before they adopted the Common Core, for example, you could score at the 10th percentile in reading in Colorado and be considered proficient,</p><p end="4676" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4613">okay? So you would get a report as a parent that your child is proficient. That's great.</p><p end="4742" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4676">Okay, what you didn't know was that, that m eant that 90 percent of the kids at that same grade level nationwide were reading better than you were. That meant that you weren't ever even close to being on grade level. That is the system that we had, and that is the system that state states that are thinking about pulling out the Common Core , which is mostly in these red states, with big Te a Party influence. That is what they are going back, that&#8217;s what this is about, that&#8217;s why we need to keep moving forward.</p><p end="4742" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="4676">So Mike, first that&#8217;s not an accurate characteriz ation of what it means to be a Common Core sta te. As you well know, lots of Common Core states are making up their own tests. They are choosing their own cut score. Nothing of significance has changed from under NCLB. So imputing this great virtue. Secondly these statistical gains can be played both ways. James Milgram, P rofessor Emeritus at Stanford, one of the five members of the Common Core validation committee who refused to sign off on the quality of the Common Core , has pointed out that if you look at federal data for instance.</p><p end="4797" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="4742">That students who only go through Algebra II, only 40 percent of them ever comple te a four year college degree. Where as 75 percent of students who take pre -calc ulus , which those old Colorado standards had, go on to complete a college degree. So , I guess if we&#8217;re going to argue about these implications, one question is, why truncate it if this data seems to suggest that the Co mmon Core is going to have fewer children ready to complete their educations?</p><p end="4797" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="4742">John Donvan:Mike Petr illi.</p><p end="4797" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4742">Right so, let&#8217;s go back to the question about testing. Rick is right, that there are a number of states out there, that because o f political pressure, mostly from the political right, have decided to pull back from the Common Core testing. Right, it&#8217;s because that&#8217;s the position you are arguing. Your position is being heard in red states and they are saying, therefore we&#8217;re not go ing to do these better tests. We&#8217;re going to do our own tests. Because we don&#8217;t want anything involved with the federal government.</p><p end="4856" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4797">We&#8217;re afraid of all kinds of other issues. My argument is that those states have not embraced the Common Core . They have not fully embraced the Common Core . Because you cannot embrace higher standards if you don&#8217;t also embrace better assessments.</p><p end="4856" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="4797">But Mike , embracing the Common Core.</p><p end="4856" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4797">They go together.</p><p end="4856" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="4797">Embracing the Common Core, does embracing the Common Core mean embracing a national cut score?</p><p end="4856" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4797">It means embracing a rigorous standard .</p><p end="4856" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="4797">No, no, no. Does it mean embracing a national, because otherwise, states can use a Common Core tests, which are still very much of unproven quality, as I think you&#8217;ve publicly conceded. We don&#8217;t know if they&#8217;re good tests or not. But you can use those tests and still make up your own cut score, and still [unintelligible] three extra mo nths of instruction. So the idea that you are now getting honest clear apple s to apples comparisons because you have used, it is just simply.</p><p end="4856" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4797">Then I am excited.</p><p end="4856" is_meta="true" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4797">applause</p><p end="4856" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4797">Michael Petrilli:What I think I&#8217;m hearing Rick, is that you agree with our position, that we should embrace the Common Core , embrace good assessment and make sure that the states are [unintelligible] .</p><p end="4920" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4856">Right. I woul d prefer that kind of policy. And it looks like the states that are doing the P ARCC test , as far as we can tell, are going to agree to a common cut score. We&#8217;re not sure yet about S marter Balance. I think even those other states, even those that don&#8217;t ha ve great tests, all signs are, even those are going to have much more challenging cut scores than they had before. So we will have made some progress on these issues. But look, Rick, I would love -</p><p end="4920" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4856">That is a yes.</p><p end="4920" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="4856">I mean I think, frankly, I think this is part of it. I think not embracing the Common Core is to say look, a number of states should do the Common Core and they should do it uncompromisingly and aggressively. And we should see if their children actually benefit.</p><p end="4980" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="4920">I&#8217;d like, I&#8217;d like, I&#8217;d like --</p><p end="4980" is_meta="true" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="4920">applause</p><p end="4980" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4920">Follow through on what we started?</p><p end="4980" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="4920">Excuse me?</p><p end="4980" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="4920">You&#8217;d like us to follow through on what we started?</p><p end="5104" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="5043">The Common Core standards most certainly are copyrighted.</p><p end="5104" is_meta="true" speaker="Carol Burris" start="5043">applause</p><p end="5104" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="5043">They are. And I really -- all of you. Go online tonight and look. You're going to see that they're copyrighted. They're not allowed to be changed. When they're adopted by states, states may add 15 percent, but they cannot change any of the standards. That's one of the problems. Second, i n terms of scripts, if you look, in New York State, Engage New York, we spent over $28 million for curriculum.</p><p end="5159" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="5104">And that curriculum is full of script. And those scripts -- at Engage New York, at least you publicly praised when you've talked to -- I think it was the Governor's Commission, you said how wonderful Eng age New York is. They truly are scripts. And we find so many teachers who are so afraid to go off -script, to not teach exactly what --</p><p end="5159" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="5104">-- [inaudible] --</p><p end="5159" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="5104">Sure. Let's talk about --</p><p end="5159" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="5104">New York is an interesting case, because it is the only state in the country that has developed a fully fleshed out curriculum. And I think you can certainly make the case that it's too fleshed out. And out -- and goo d administrators will tell their teach ers, "Hey,</p><p end="5159" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="5104">use it as a resource . And it's there for you. But by no means should you be following it word -by -word," okay?</p><p end="5218" is_meta="true" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="5159">applause</p><p end="5218" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="5159">You know, it -- most states have the opposite problem, which is that there's nothing.</p><p end="5218" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="5159">There's nothing been developed, and teachers are saying, "I'm desperate for something to help me teach to these standards." And what those teachers usually use is Engage New York.</p><p end="5218" is_meta="true" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="5159">laughter</p><p end="5273" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="5218">Great. Thank you, John. And thank you so much to Rick, and Carol, and Carmel for this great discussion. It's -- it is so nice for a change to have a discussion about the Common Core that is so substantive, because unfortunately, that's not been what's happening for much of the last couple of years. I just want to say to some of the points that Rick and Carol made. They're very smart to go and to look at some of the specific standards that they've got questions about.</p><p end="5337" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="5273">And as we said at the beginning, there's no doubt, the Common Core are not perfect,</p><p end="5337" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="5273">nor are they set in stone. You look at states around the country, they have found ways to add to the standards. Florida, for example, adding calculus to their math standards because of some of the concerns that Rick made. Totally legitimate. Other states adding cursive, because parents have been concerned we're not teaching cursive. There are no Common Core cops. States are free to do that, and they should do that. And they should make them their own. But I want to talk again about what happens on the other side of this if you go backwards. Rick is right. Rick's book, "Spinning Wheels," you should read it. It's a classic, right? You want to see spinning w heels? Go check out Oklahoma right now, because that's where you have spinning wheels, because the legislature decided out of political pressure to pull back on these standards. You listen to Jeannetta Jante [spelled phonetically], she's a English language arts teacher at Oklahoma City's Southeast High School, she called that decision a "travesty." She says,</p><p end="5337" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="5273">quote, "Now it's like we've wasted teacher training, teacher time, lesson planning,resources, all of those things we've just done. The senators have basically said, 'Oops,</p><p end="5337" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="5273">sorry, we didn't mean for you to do all of that.'</p><p end="5395" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="5337">The chaos in the classrooms will be great. The chaos in the classrooms will be great." Okay, we are four years into this. And many, many teachers, millions of teache rs across the country are working hard at making Common Core work. We should follow through now on what we have started. We should make it better as we go. We should address problems and challenges. But we should embrace the Common Core . Thank you.</p><p end="5395" is_meta="true" speaker="Michael Petrilli" start="5337">applause</p><p end="5523" is_meta="false" speaker="Carol Burris" start="5454">Okay, don't embrace the Common Core .</p><p end="5580" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="5523">Thanks, John.</p><p end="5580" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="5523">Okay.</p><p end="5580" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="5523">Thank you, John. As a mom and a former civil rights attorney, I've seen firsthand the consequences of low expectations and their long term effects. Our children do deserve more. They deserve to be taught to the level that they need to be successful in college and career, and that's the overarching goal of these standards, and there's lots of evidence to support that it will get them to where they need to be. The Common Core</p><p end="5580" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="5523">gives teachers the spac e to create an exciting classroom experience for all rooted high expectations, project- based learning, problem solving, and exploring concepts deeply instead of focusing on worksheets and rote memorization.</p><p end="5637" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="5580">If this were 2012, all four of us -- all four of the panelists here would be in agreement that we should not repeal the Common Core . Carol said as recently as 2012 that higher level thinking is more prominent in the Common Core than in all present state standards. And Rick said jus t last week that he was not necessarily saying to pull out of the Common Core . I think what he's saying tonight is the jury is out. What Mike and I are saying is to -- let's keep moving forward because our children can't afford to wait any longer for hig her standards, and they can't rely on extraordinary principles or teachers to help them get there. The achievement gaps in our country are staggering,</p><p end="5637" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="5580">and it's time to tackle them aggressively. Your vote tonight will be closely watched and folks outside of this theater may not understand all of the nuance of Rick and Carol's position. A vote to not embrace the Common Core will be interpreted as a vote to repeal the Common Core altogether.</p><p end="5703" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="5637">And as Mike said, we do not believe that there are good alternatives to that. There are real consequences to this decision, higher versus lower standards, new expenses in changing course, frustration for countless educators. Those consequences should be at the forefront of your decision. Students who come to high school, falling behind, only one in 10 of them get to catch up, according to a recent ACT study. We need to get to them earlier.</p><p end="5703" is_meta="false" speaker="Carmel Martin" start="5637">I urge you to "Embrace the Common Core ."</p><p end="5703" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="5637">Thanks, John, it's a pleasure to be with all of you this evening. Mike, Carmel, thanks for a terrific conversation. Mike and Carmel tonight have repeatedly suggested that the Common Core is right on the big things, that all of th e concerns, the tests, the curricula,</p><p end="5703" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="5637">the instruction are glitches, they're bumps in the road, they're things to be worked out.</p><p end="5759" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="5703">For me, having done this for a while, this all brings to mind the advice offered by a thoughtful pundit a few years ago on another major reform effort, No Child Left Behind.</p><p end="5759" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="5703">On reflecting on NCLB, this pundit, who had enthusiastically championed it until he soured on it penned a terrific chapter for a book of mine, titled, "The Problem with Implementa tion," is the problem. The author was our own Mike Petrilli. In this chapter,</p><p end="5759" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="5703">Mike observed the central task of No Child Left Behind implementation is translating its aspirational statements in bold principles into action in the real world. To work well at the local level in real schools affecting real children, its contradictions must be resolved,</p><p end="5759" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="5703">its fuzzy notions must be made crystal clear. He wrote that when this fuzziness led to confusion, the fault must be placed on the law itself, not just on those charged wit h carrying it out.</p><p end="5815" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="5759">Mike offered some terrific advice there on this whole question of whether to embrace these kinds of changes. He observed, "Where the implementation of the law has gone most smoothly is where at least a handful of states and districts have already paved the way." I think that was great advice. I think Common Core , like No Child Left Behind,</p><p end="5815" is_meta="false" speaker="Frederick Hess" start="5759">certainly deserves its day in the sun. I'm not opposed to giving it a chance to show what it can do. Happily, state s have only begun implementation in earnest in most cases. Until 2013, two thirds of American adults had never even heard of the Common Core . This is actually a propitious moment to hit pause, slow down, figure out what we're doing before we get too far downstream. For that reason, I'd like to ask you tonight to please vote against embracing the Common Core .</p></transcript></debate>