<debate url="https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/fdas-caution-hazardous-our-health"><speakers><speaker name="Dr. Scott Gottlieb" position="for"><description>Practicing Physician &amp; Former Deputy Commissioner, FDA</description><bio>Scott Gottlieb, M.D., is a practicing physician and a resident fellow at the American Enterprise Institute. From 2005 to 2007, he served as the FDA... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Peter Huber" position="for"><description>Senior Fellow, Manhattan Institute and Author</description><bio>Peter Huber is a senior fellow at the Manhattan Institute writing on the issues of drug development, energy, technology, and the law. Before joining... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Dr. Jerry Avorn" position="against"><description>Professor of Medicine, Harvard Medical School</description><bio>Jerry Avorn, M.D., is a professor of Medicine at Harvard Medical School and chief of the Division of Pharmacoepidemiology and Pharmacoeconomics in... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Dr. David Challoner" position="against"><description>VP for Health Affairs Emeritus, University of Florida</description><bio>David R. Challoner, M.D. is vice president emeritus for Health Affairs of the University of Florida.  Dr. Challoner has held leadership and health... Read More</bio></speaker></speakers><results><result against="32" for="23" submitters="live" undecided="45" when="before" /><result against="37" for="53" submitters="live" undecided="10" when="after" /><result for="100" submitters="online" when="before" /><result for="100" submitters="online" when="after" /></results><transcript><p end="425" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="363">Well, mostly, I'm just hoping to overcome my intellectual attention deficit disorder.</p><p end="2761" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="2700">I -- forgive me, but --</p><p end="2761" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="2700">On the accelerated -- look, but this is absolutely unequivocal. Under the accelerated approval rule, you cut off a big chunk of what the FDA's normal rules do. You actually cut off in the middle of Phase III or Phase II. Or -- and some people are pushing to cut off after Phase I, because the results are so dramatic there, okay? You are actually not doing what is normally required</p><p end="2761" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="2700">As -- wait just as second. And who does it, then? Because you still have to finish. And the answer is, you do it -- by and large, you do it in Phase IV. And a lot of doctors out there are now also using the drug. And they are working completely independently and they are the ones who are using the modern tools to work out how to fit these rather simple drugs to our extremely complex bodies. They're finding the biomarkers on efficacy and safety. These are all emerging later. They are getting the precision medicine. And nowhere else in the FDA protocols you get that.</p><p end="2820" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="2761">It never emerges during the standardized conventional protocols. You are blinded all the way through. There is no Bayesian adaption during the trials. There's --</p><p end="2820" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="2761">-- you just don't get the information, okay?</p><p end="2820" is_meta="true" speaker="Peter Huber" start="2761">laughter</p><p end="2820" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="2761">I put in one word, Bayesian. That means that you're actually --</p><p end="2820" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="2761">It means you're actually looking at the data as you go and learning from it as you go and adapting to it. And the FDA --</p><p end="2820" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="2761">-- is so concerned about something called selection bias, they don't allow it all.</p><p end="2820" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="2761">I would just add to that the FDA has actually been backing away from the accelerated approval rule in recent years, so much that the Congress had to re-codify it and reach a legislation to say, &#8220;We really meant it. We want you to use this try to&#8221; --</p><p end="2820" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="2761">It --</p><p end="2820" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="2761">It is. The only place we are actually developing modern drugs --</p><p end="2820" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="2761">Nowhere else [inaudible] FDA.</p><p end="2944" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="2882">Look -- and I couldn't agree more, but let me tell you something. The whole notion that you convene a group of patients of a certain size, and you test them for a certain time,</p><p end="2944" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="2882">and then you make a declaration of a drug is a pure artifice of the kinds of the statistics that the FDA uses in its conventional protocols. It's the frequentest trial. If you --</p><p end="2944" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="2882">forgive the jargon -- the alternative I've been discussing is typically called Bayesian trials.</p><p end="2944" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="2882">And those are completely open-ended. No serious Bayesian says we will stop after certain time and a certain number of patients. You keep feeding the data into the system forever and you keep refining forever. And you put it in massive computer -- the databases, which people are already doing. And that's the process. And you can have separate calls on when people convene and charging -- they're using the drugs, but that's how you do the side.</p><p end="3122" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="3061">I --</p><p end="3122" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="3061">All right.</p><p end="3659" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="3598">No, I want people to have access to a drug we've developed the science so well that we know it will work in that patient, not in the crowd that exists somewhere in the FDA's computers. And that requires the use of the very best tools of modern molecular medicine. And I ask you to think very carefully, where are they being used systematically, okay? They're being used after a drug gets licensed, okay? Under the FDA's standard protocols, we are not developing that science. We should be. It's the --</p><p end="3659" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="3598">the -- I think it's almost required by law. The FDA doesn't license a drug. It licenses a drug plus a label.</p><p end="3718" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="3659">The label is saying, is it safe and effective in these circumstances of use? And the FDA is not developing any of that science. During the trial, it scripts every step of the way. The one exception is under the accelerated approval rule where --</p><p end="3718" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="3659">-- it cuts it out and lets the process -- [unintelligible].</p><p end="3838" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="3777">But wait, I have to -- I simply have to -- your description that the targeted drugs are a rarity is just disconnected from reality. All of the HIV drugs were structure-based design. Most all of the [unintelligible] are targeted drugs, all monoclonal antibodies are precisely targeted drugs. You know, most of our cancer therapies are on this. They can now go from a genetic identification to a mab or a structure-based drug in four years,</p><p end="3838" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="3777">licensed, okay? They're doing it here in New York. They just got Xalkori out in four years, gene to active drug, targeted. This is not a rarity. And this is where all of medicine is headed.</p><p end="3838" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="3777">If only that were true.</p><p end="4146" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="4090">The first thing I would say to them is my heart goes out to you. Thalidomide was a terrible tragedy and it involved kids. And any parent, and I am one, that -- it just breaks your heart to read this, okay?</p><p end="4204" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="4146">I will add that it was a drug from the 1950s. And so, then, I would -- and then now, I'd like to tell you the follow-up on thalidomide. This does not excuse anything that was done back then. It wasn't, of course, licensed in the United States, but it was licensed abroad. You know that thalidomide is licensed as a drug in the United States today, you know? And you know it was -- in fact, it was given accelerated approval through theFDA, was rushed through, and they used the -- an incredibly clever dodge -- whoever --</p><p end="4204" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="4146">whichever lawyer thought of --</p><p end="4204" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="4146">Well, well, just --</p><p end="4204" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="4146">Well --</p><p end="4204" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="4146">Just a second. The question is, when you don't understand a thing about what drugs are doing, you make horrendous mistakes. And we've made many in the past. And many of the examples, certainly in Dr. Avorn's book, are about misuse of estrogen, which dates way back, decades; and diet drugs, which have been used for all sorts of non-medical purposes and so on. You know, I -- nobody wants tragedies, but the way you don't -- I would rather prevent them than apologize for them and regret them.</p><p end="4258" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="4204">The pharmacoepidemiologists find them out late. The people who looked for the biomarkers that control how a drug performs find safety biomarkers too. Dr. Avorn has gotten -- has done important work on liver toxicity with a drug called Rezulin. There are biomarkers for liver toxicity. We should be looking whether they're explaining the liver toxicity when you try the next Rezulin. You get them on the label and you don't prescribe these things. Let's fix problems, not just lament them.</p><p end="4509" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="4435">I would be --</p><p end="4509" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="4435">I'd tell you what the very best systems are out there today, to my knowledge, okay?</p><p end="4509" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="4435">And they are the ones that have, unfortunately not mainly during the FDA trials, but post-market, okay, accumulated huge databases of massive amounts of molecular data and clinical data.</p><p end="4573" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="4509">IBM is pioneering some of this work. Their HIV computers outperform doctors. You give a patient profile, root of entry, the -- what country you're in, these things, and they are doing massive searches through very large amounts of molecular data, and they give you precision, custom-tailored -- the best possible prescriptions you can get. You get those prescriptions only when you've accumulated a lot of patient-specific data and a lot of clinical data. We should start doing that during the FDA clinical trials. We don't.</p><p end="4740" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="4680">Well, let me put it --</p><p end="4740" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="4680">-- this way. If you outlawed it, as some people suggest we should, or actually crack down -- and by the way, under the federal drug law, it's quite clear doctors have a right to practice off-label medicine. But oncology would essentially shut down if you actually prohibited this. Oncology is all toolkits. "All" is not true, but some of the cocktails go through FDA licensing scripts. The vast majority of oncology today is doctors looking at drugs that have a particular molecular medicine &#8211; a mechanism unknown. Theyunderstand, gee, if I do this to the breast cancer cell, I'll frac this receptor. And they're sequencing the tumor of multiple points in the body and are finding all sorts of different ways to attack it, and they&#8217;re -- that's how they do it. There's some areas you just have to do that. Okay?</p><p end="4740" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="4680">Look, look, many people my age and others, you know, are taking fistfuls of drugs all the time. I mean --</p><p end="4740" is_meta="true" speaker="Peter Huber" start="4680">laughter</p><p end="4740" is_meta="true" speaker="Peter Huber" start="4680">applause</p><p end="4805" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="4740">I think, to tell you the truth, and I don't necessarily want to go here, I do -- I think I am quite confident that in our lifetimes, with this massive convergence of digital and biochemical technology and our ability to acquire all this data, we will get increasingly personalized. We will get to the point where the information is there, where the people best qualified to decide how to prescribe one or more drugs to this patient, will be the doctor and patient, because you've got a unique body there.</p><p end="4865" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="4805">You have a massive record of how things connect to each other. And Bayesians know how to draw those networks. They're doing it --</p><p end="5400" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="5341">Could I add --</p><p end="5400" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="5341">In the White House report that I mentioned, they described the IT systems inside the FDA, that they are woefully inadequate. They are -- the systems don't connect among offices, okay? They have incompatible protocols. And they are still resorting to entering data manually. Now, I don't blame this on any individual at the FDA, but that's what happens to large, bureaucratic structures in Washington; they are an information industry and they can't -- you know, they're working with clay tablets and donkeys,</p><p end="5400" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="5341">really. It's ridiculous.</p><p end="5400" is_meta="true" speaker="Peter Huber" start="5341">laughter</p><p end="5887" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="5822">In the form of arguments for and against this motion, I actually believe only one thing,</p><p end="5887" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="5822">that we -- the best thing for our health is to get the very best drug science we can possibly develop, and the rest will take care of itself. And I -- and I have been lamenting,</p><p end="5887" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="5822">in case you haven't noticed, the FDA's dreadful failure to move molecular medicine systematically into its protocols. And it's had 20 years to do this, you know, and to tell us that they're working on it, you know, it's too late now. When they're done, vote for the other side. But for tonight, you know, vote for our side.</p><p end="5887" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="5822">But let me -- I would like to give you just a taste, which blew my mind when I read this,</p><p end="5887" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="5822">of the incredible new powers that medicine acquires once it begins doing molecular medicine, you know, from scratch, thinking mechanistically about what drugs actually do.</p><p end="5887" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="5822">True story: Six-year-old Emily Whitehead was on -- you may have read this in the Times.</p><p end="5887" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="5822">You know, was on the brink of death after a two-year battle with leukemia. Her doctors extracted from some of her cancerous cells some signature molecules and moved them into some of her healthy immune system cells.</p><p end="5939" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="5887">Exactly as planned, they went in a -- into a wild attack on their cancerous siblings, so wild that they overproduced a molecular -- an immune system signaling molecule, a cytokine. One of her doctors knew that an arthritis drug, of all things, controls cytokines. He prescribed a massive dose. Emily -- the ICU staff gathered to sing happy birthday when Emily awoke from her coma on the day she turned seven. The Times ran her story just before Christmas, and Emily is healthy to this day, and cancer free.</p><p end="5939" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="5887">We should be simply appalled, you know, that, you know, intense molecular tracking and learning on the fly and measuring everything you possibly can in sight during clinical trials isn't an -- I mean, isn't just the norm today rather than an exception you have to go through to -- a special rule to even find.</p><p end="6009" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Huber" start="5939">What are we thinking when we tell the doctors, you know, to put on blindfolds and do no adaptation, no significant learning during the trials? The diseases that are probably going to kill you, and you, and you, and me, and the people we love are going to require complex arrays of drugs, you know, prescribed in complex ways. We have to do molecular medicine. The FDA isn't doing it.</p></transcript></debate>