<debate duration="5669" url="https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/google-violates-its-dont-be-evil-motto"><speakers><speaker name="Harry Lewis" position="for"><description>Dean of Harvard College, Gordon McKay Professor of Computer Science at Harvard</description><bio>In 2003 Lewis was honored with the title of Harvard College Professor in honor of his teaching excellence. Over more than thirty years of teaching... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Randal C. Picker" position="for"><description>Paul H. and Theo Leffmann Professor of Commercial Law at the University of Chicago Law School</description><bio>Picker is also a senior fellow at The Computation Institute of the University of Chicago and Argonne National Laboratory and has for a number of years... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Siva Vaidhyanathan" position="for"><description>Chair, Department of Media Studies, University of Virginia &amp; Author of The Googlization of Everything</description><bio>A cultural historian and media scholar, Siva Vaidhyanathan is currently the Robertson Professor and the Chair of the Department of Media Studies at... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Esther Dyson" position="against"><description>Investor and Director of 23andMe and Yandex</description><bio>Ester is well qualified to opine on Google. In 1997, she wrote Release 2.0: A Design for Living in the Digital Age, about the impact of the Internet... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Jim Harper" position="against"><description>Director of Information Policy Studies at the Cato Institute</description><bio>A nationally recognized privacy, Internet, and technology policy expert, Jim has testified in Congress a half-dozen times and in state legislatures... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Jeff Jarvis" position="against"><description>Creator and Founding Editor of Entertainment Weekly and Sunday Editor and Associate Publisher of the New York Daily News</description><bio>Jeff is writing a book, WWGD? - What Would Google Do?, that reverse-engineers the company's success and applies those lessons and laws to other industries... Read More</bio></speaker></speakers><results><result against="50" for="50" submitters="live" when="before" /><result against="50" for="50" submitters="live" when="after" /><result against="50" for="50" submitters="online" when="before" /><result against="50" for="50" submitters="online" when="after" /></results><transcript /></debate>