<debate duration="6245" url="https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/guns-reduce-crime"><speakers><speaker name="Stephen Halbrook" position="for"><description>Represents the NRA in suits against the DC and Chicago handgun bans</description><bio>Halbrook's most recent book is The Founders' Second Amendment. He filed a brief on behalf of over 300 members of Congress in the Supreme Court case... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Gary Kleck" position="for"><description>Professor in the College of Criminology and Criminal Justice at Florida State University</description><bio>Kleck's research centers on violence and crime control, focusing on gun control and crime deterrence. Kleck is the author of Targeting Guns: Firearms... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="John R. Lott" position="for"><description>Senior Research Scholar at the University of Maryland</description><bio>Lott has held positions at the University of Chicago, Yale University, Stanford, UCLA, Wharton, and Rice and was the chief economist at the United... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="John J. Donohue" position="against"><description>Leighton Homer Surbeck Professor at Yale Law School</description><bio>Donohue&#146;s recent work has used large-scale statistical studies to estimate the causal impact of law and public policy in a wide range of areas from... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Paul Helmke" position="against"><description>President of the Brady Campaign/Center to Prevent Gun Violence</description><bio>The Brady Center to Prevent Gun Violence is the nation's largest national, non-partisan, grassroots organization leading the fight to prevent gun... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="R. Gil Kerlikowske" position="against"><description>36-year Veteran of Law Enforcement</description><bio>Kerlikowske was appointed as chief of police for Seattle in August 2000. Kerlikowske served as the police commissioner for Buffalo, New York. He has... Read More</bio></speaker></speakers><results><result against="60" for="13" submitters="live" undecided="16" when="before" /><result against="63" for="16" submitters="live" undecided="10" when="after" /><result against="66" submitters="online" undecided="33" when="before" /><result against="33" for="66" submitters="online" when="after" /></results><transcript /></debate>