<debate duration="6321" url="https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/hunters-conserve-wildlife"><speakers><speaker name="Anthony Licata" position="for"><description>Editor-in-Chief, Field &amp; Stream</description><bio>Anthony Licata is the editor-in-chief of Field &amp; Stream, America'&#128;&#153;s largest outdoor sports magazine brand, with an audience of over 9 million... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Catherine Semcer" position="for"><description>COO, Humanitarian Operations Protecting Elephants</description><bio>Catherine E. Semcer is a dedicated conservationist and experienced non-profit leader. As the COO of Humanitarian Operations Protecting Elephants (H... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Wayne Pacelle" position="against"><description>CEO &amp; President, The Humane Society of the United States</description><bio>Wayne Pacelle is president and CEO of the Humane Society of the United States (HSUS), named by Forbes as one of the largest charities in the U.S,... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Adam M. Roberts" position="against"><description>CEO, Born Free USA &amp; Born Free Foundation</description><bio>Adam M. Roberts, based in Washington, D.C., is the CEO of Born Free USA and Born Free Foundation. He helped launch Born Free USA in 2002 to bring... Read More</bio></speaker></speakers><results><result against="36" for="21" submitters="live" undecided="43" when="before" /><result against="65" for="25" submitters="live" undecided="10" when="after" /><result against="28" for="58" submitters="online" undecided="9" when="before" /><result against="33" for="57" submitters="online" undecided="5" when="after" /></results><transcript><p end="308" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="243">Thanks for having me.</p><p end="308" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="243">Hunting is about a lot more than just taking an animal. On that trip to Alaska, I absolutely fell in love with Southeast Alaska and that's what made it so memorable.</p><p end="308" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="243">My partner is Catherine Semcer.</p><p end="359" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="308">Sure. A hunter is someone who pays a fee to pursue game within the context of a conservation program that has government oversight. A poacher, in contrast, is an outlaw who illegally kills game to supply illicit markets around the world. The keydifference is that hunters support conservation programs and poachers actively undermine them.</p><p end="417" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="359">Thank you very much.</p><p end="417" is_meta="true" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="359">applause</p><p end="417" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="359">Well, it was. I had all of the encyclopedias, some old Britannica encyclopedias dog-</p><p end="417" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="359">eared to all of the animal entries, the polar bears and the pronghorns and all the other animals. So I couldn't get enough information when I was a kid about animals.</p><p end="417" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="359">My good friend, Adam Roberts. Glad to have him here.</p><p end="540" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="481">Thank you, everyone. I really feel that I should not be up here tonight. I really feel like the person who should be here talking about African wildlife is somebody from Africa,</p><p end="540" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="481">from South Africa, from Zimbabwe, from Namibia, from Mozambique, somebody who has to live with that wildlife and somebody who has to live with the consequences of the policies that the United States and the EU often implement in relation to that wildlife, but I'm here and I appreciate the invitation.</p><p end="600" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="540">I think this is going to be an interesting debate because Wayne, Adam, and I agree on a lot. First and foremost, we agree that wildlife is valuable and should be conserved. I think all of you feel the same, otherwise you wouldn't be here this evening. Wayne and I agree that factor farming is bad for people, animals, and the environment, and Adam's organization, Born Free, just recently joined the International Union for Conservation of Nature, which I also serve as a volunteer, the largest network of conservation professionals in the world. So, welcome, Adam. If you came here looking for the brawls that usually characterize this topic, I hope you're going to leave disappointed.</p><p end="600" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="540">Anthony and I are not zealots. We're not absolutists. We're realists. And that realism,</p><p end="600" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="540">along with our personal experience, is what leads us to the position that hunters conserve wildlife. And it's a position I hope you will vote in favor of this evening.</p><p end="660" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="600">We're going to share with you stories from Africa's poaching wars. We're going to talk about the success of the North American model of wildlife conservation. We're going to share figures and realities that we have gained through boots on the ground experience working with lions, elephants, cape buffalo, sable, in places where photo tourists will not go because they're what we call a non-permissive environment, places that are dangerous, remote. But hunters will go there and hunters are the ones who are conserving these places. A little fun fact. Do you know that hunting concessions have conserved an area in Africa 1.7 times the size of the U.S. National Park system? That is a huge chunk of conservation land. How much of our national park system are we willing to put into jeopardy on the African continent?</p><p end="722" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="660">I'm going to share some stories about why hunters conserve wildlife. One place we work is called Coutada 11 in Mozambique. It's an area of about 2.5 million acres. To put that into perspective, it's an area about the size of Yellowstone National Park. As many of you probably know, during the 1990s Mozambique saw an absolutely brutal civil war,</p><p end="722" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="660">horrific. If you're not familiar with it, you should become familiar with it, because it's something that should never happen again. One consequence of that civil war was that Coutada 11 was completely wiped out of wildlife. Cape Buffalo were down to 1,200 in number. Sable, we're down to 44. People were starving. In came a man named Mark Haldane, South African, a professional hunter, and outfitter, a concessionaire.</p><p end="779" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="722">He took charge of Coutada 11 in partnership with the government of Mozambique.</p><p end="779" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="722">1,200 buffalo became 21,000. Forty-four sable became 1,400. In the last 10 years, hehas invested one million dollars of his revenue to restore wildlife in this area. He invests $100,000 a year in anti-poaching alone. And now because of that anti-poaching work which my organization helped support with training, advisory assistance and procurement services, this is the only area in Mozambique that did not see a decline in elephant numbers during the last national elephant census. If that's not conservation,</p><p end="779" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="722">then I don't know what conservation looks like. But let's take a step back. Let's get a definition of conservation.</p><p end="846" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="779">The International Union for Conservation of Nature that I had mentioned previously that I served that Adam's organization is a part of, they define conservation as, and I'm going to read here because I want to make sure that we get this right, "Conservation is the protection, care, management, and maintenance of ecosystems, habitats, species, and populations within or outside of their natural environments in order to safeguard the natural conditions for their long term permanence." Because of this definition, a scientific consensus has emerged through the IUCN, the largest network of conservation scientists in the world. There is a consensus that hunters conserve wildlife. The IUCN just recently sent a briefing paper to the European Parliament that was influential in convincing that parliament not to adopt trade bans that would interfere with African hunting programs.</p><p end="905" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="846">Now, you will always find scientists on the fringe who are willing to say, "That's not true," who are willing to buck the consensus. Climate change deniers do this all the time. But for those of us who care about wildlife, we should listen to the consensus that hunters are an indispensable part of the conservation ecosystem. And this isn't to say that we're the only part. We need birdwatchers as much as we need duck hunters. This isn't an either/or question. This is about a holistic, sustainable approach to wildlife conservation that Anthony, myself, and the people who HOPE serves are grateful to be a part of because we want to pass down a rich, natural heritage that's filled with elephants, sable, cape buffalo, wolves, grizzly bears, white-tailed deer.</p><p end="962" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="905">And for all of those reasons I just said, you should vote in favor of the motion, &#8220;Hunters Conserve Wildlife." Thank you.</p><p end="962" is_meta="true" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="905">applause</p><p end="962" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="905">Walter Palmer used his wealth to travel halfway around the world to shoot a magnificent lion not for management, not for food, but to add another trophy to his home collection. In pursuit of more and more trophies as we see so many members of the Safari Club International, this globetrotting enterprise of killing the biggest and rarest animals in the world.</p><p end="1021" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="962">Now, we are outraged as a nation and so many people around the world were outraged about it. And part of that is explained by our growing sensitivity to animals. We're less tolerant of factory farming. We don't like dogfighting and cockfighting. We don't accept horse slaughter for human consumption. There are all sorts of abuses of animals that we once accepted, but now don't meet our moral tests in our society. So there is obviously a very big ethical debate about trophy killing or other forms of hunting, sport hunting, and commercial trapping. I think there are gradations in that world. I think Walter Palmer and the other trophy hunting advocates who travel around the world to kill rare species are one category, and a guy in West Virginia or Pennsylvania who kills a deer to eat meat and fill the freezer is a whole other beast, if you will.</p><p end="1091" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="1021">And we're not going to really get into all the elements of that debate, because tonight we're talking about this motion, that hunters conserve wildlife. And I want to prove to you tonight, with Adam, that that is a really gross overstatement. It's really a bromide.</p><p end="1091" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="1021">It's something that's been repeated decade after decade, and there's very little evidence to support it at this time. You know, most hunters are going out into the woods for, you know, their own reasons. Walter Palmer traveled to Zimbabwe to kill a lion because he wanted to kill a lion and get a trophy. Other people want to go out and be with their friends or family members. Some like to experience nature. Some may do it for meat purposes. But most people are not going out to kill these creatures because they support conservation. If you do that, you can give money to a land trust, or you can support conservation in all sorts of ways -- very tangible ways -- to help creatures who were really facing so many pressures from those of us -- our species -- that is crowding so many of these animals out.</p><p end="1147" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="1091">You know, when you think about the United States, two billion acres is the land mass of this country. 700 million acres is owned by the federal government. Just 2 or 3 percentof that land has been purchased as a consequence of hunting-oriented programs, like Duck Stamps or the federal Pittman-Robertson Act, which sets aside money -- it's a tax on guns and ammunition. Actually, all gun owners and ammunition buyers, not just hunters. There are many more people who have guns in the world than have an interest in hunting. So, it's a tiny percentage of the lands that has been preserved or saved from development. And when you think about the land trusts in this country, the nature conservancy, and hundreds and hundreds of other land trusts, almost none of them have a hunting orientation.</p><p end="1202" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="1147">They're out to save the land. They're out to protect wildlife because they just want it to be, not because they want to use these creatures and shoot them for recreation, for trophies, for other purposes. And you know, when we start to take a proper accounting,</p><p end="1202" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="1147">when we really think about conservation, we think about protecting land, saving threatened and endangered species, preserving ecosystems, let's think about some of the things that are the collateral effects of hunting. Hunters are one of the biggest sources of lead dispersed into the environment. Now we have copper shot, we have bismuth, we have steel. All of these forms of shot can be used by hunters, but we're putting millions of pounds of lead into the environment that's poisoning 15 to 20 million animals a year. Loons and other species -- also, the highly endangered California condor.</p><p end="1260" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="1202">Why are we using lead when we have alternatives? If you're conservation minded,</p><p end="1260" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="1202">you're not going to randomly poison millions of creatures. We have captive hunts that are tolerated by the NRA and the Safari Club International, and other organizations in this field, where exotic animals are stocked in fenced areas and shot for a fee, in an open-air slaughterhouse house sort of arrangement. It's disguised hunting. But all of the national hunting groups support it, they defend it. They oppose our legislative efforts to stop it. And many of these exotic species that they're shooting in the United States have escaped and they're colonizing our habitats. That's the reason we have wild boars in so many parts of the country that are degrading landscapes and are considered a nuisance by federal land managers and state wildlife managers. We have this Safari Club program globally -- you want to get the Africa Big 5 award?</p><p end="1322" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="1260">You shoot a lion, a leopard, a rhino, an elephant, and a cape buffalo. You want to shoot -- you want to get the Cats of the World award? You shoot five of the big cats. I mean,</p><p end="1322" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="1260">these folks are going after some of the rarest animals in the world. Hunting is not -- and the idea of hunting as conservation, you know, it sounds like a wonderful slogan, but what are the details? What are the specific terms? Because they pay hunting licensefees? Because they buy a Duck Stamp? Well, there's a tax on tobacco, and some of that money goes to the healthcare system. Does that make tobacco companies and smokers healthcare advocates? The oil companies are taxed under the Land and Water Conservation Fund, and some of that money goes to protect habitat. Do we think of the oil companies and the gas companies as leading wildlife and land protectors? No. It just happens to be that they're taxed because there are costs to the enterprise.</p><p end="1392" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="1322">And much of the money that is used, you know, for those purposes goes to just maintain the hunting program in a quasi-agricultural program to provide more deer and more game animals for hunters to shoot, when the reality is there are dozens and dozens of other species that desperately need our attention. So, hunting is an ethical issue and it's declining in terms of its popularity, but the idea that hunting is conservation, that's not why anybody goes out into the woods when they want to kill an animal. Thank you very much.</p><p end="1392" is_meta="true" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="1322">applause</p><p end="1440" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="1392">Thank you. Thank you. Tonight, we're going to show you how hunting has, in fact,</p><p end="1440" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="1392">protected wildlife and habitats throughout North America through this wonderful North American model. I was really happy to hear Wayne ask for details, because I could have -- I have some. And I would like everyone else's opinion about some of the numbers that he's pooh-poohed to see if they really are all that small. And the fact is, hunting provides a sustainable, repeatable model on which wildlife could be managed and protected. I want to give you some history first. At the turn of the 20th century, habitat loss and market hunting had had our species at the point of extinction. Bears, elk,</p><p end="1440" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="1392">moose, even white-tailed deer.</p><p end="1507" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="1440">Around this time, concerned hunters, including the editors of Field &amp; Stream and New Yorker Theodore Roosevelt, pushed to set game laws, base wildlife management on science, and make it managed by the public. The principles that formed this are called the North American Wildlife Model. It still drives much of what we do for a simple reason. It works. The system is not perfect, but there is no other form of wildlife management that has the results that this model has had. Hunting is at the center of this story. It's a tool for managing wildlife, but it also makes hunters a powerful tool and advocate for wildlife -- supporters of wildlife. But let's talk about numbers, some of those pieces of land and some of those programs that Wayne mentioned. Hunters provide 80 percent of the funding to fish and game wildlife agencies. There's about 37 million hunters in the United States, and every single one of them contributes. All told,</p><p end="1507" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="1440">sportsmen contribute a billion dollars a year to wildlife conservation.</p><p end="1565" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="1507">To me, that's not a small number. These funds come from a variety of ways. The first source of these funds is through hunting licenses. These monies go directly to the state that sold them, and these dollars can only be used for wildlife management and conservation. Big numbers, small numbers -- since 1965, they generated $22 billion.</p><p end="1565" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="1507">Just last year, in 2015, they generated $821 million. Wayne explained Pittman-</p><p end="1565" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="1507">Robertson. This is the excise tax on sales of ammunition. Something to know here is that this law was advocated for, lobbied, supported, by hunters -- voluntarily. It has generated more than 12 billion for state wildlife management and conservation. Of those funds, 62 percent are used to buy, develop, and maintain wildlife habitat.</p><p end="1621" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="1565">Since the Act became law, states have purchased about four million acres of wildlife habitat, an additional 40 million acres are managed under agreements with private landowners. The U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service credits Pittman-Robertson with rebuilding these populations of these animals and extending the ranges from wild turkey, white-tailed deer, mule deer, elk, black bear, bobcat, mountain lions. For example, in 1910, there were 20,000 elk in Montana. Now, there's 120,000 -- in large part, thanks to these monies. Mule, deer, all the other ungulates have had similar recoveries. What's that done? It's allowed wolves and mountain lions to make a recovery as well. Right now, money generated by Pittman-Robertson is working to conserve wolves around the Great Lakes and run the wolf conservation program in Oregon.</p><p end="1685" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="1621">Non-game benefits as well. It's not just about hunters having more. Here in New York State there's efforts in the Albany Pine Bush area to protect the endangered Karner BlueButterfly. This is a butterfly so rare that even the loss of a few could be devastating to the population. This program has received significant funds from Pittman-Robertson paid for by hunters. The truth is, most of the budgets for wildlife management, which takes place on some of those federal lands that Wayne mentioned, come from these fees. Eighty percent of Wyoming&#8217;s budget comes from that. In Michigan it's 76. In Colorado it's 70. A third component is the federal Duck Stamp. Again, this was an idea made by hunters, lobbied by hunters, supported by hunters. It's generated $800 million in money for wetland conservation since its introduction with 98 cents of every dollar going to purchase wetlands or acquire easements that feed into the national wildlife refuge system that we can all enjoy.</p><p end="1743" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="1685">The Duck Stamp has preserved six and a half million acres of wetlands. Here in New York it's 20 thousand acres. I don't think that's so small. A fourth source of hunter-</p><p end="1743" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="1685">generated income comes from the many nonprofit hunter-run conservation groups.</p><p end="1743" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="1685">These groups are organizations like Ducks Unlimited, the Boone and Crockett Club,</p><p end="1743" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="1685">Rocky Mountain Elk Foundation, Pheasants Forever, and many more. Let's look at Ducks Unlimited as just one example. This group protects wetlands for ducks, but because hunters know that wildlife needs intact, functioning healthy ecosystems to live, it also benefits insects, fish, salamanders, mink, martin, shrews, beavers, all the animals that depend on a healthy wetland. In 2014 and 2015 alone, DU raised $238 million that went to wildlife conservation.</p><p end="1815" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="1743">Eighty-five percent of that money goes directly into waterfowl habitat restoration and acquiring lands. I don't think that's a small number. With the money that is raised, DU has conserved more than 13.5 million acres of wetlands across North America. This doesn't take into account all the volunteer hours that hunters give working on grass roots conservation projects. What's important to note here is that these groups and all this money is all driven by people's love of hunting. They love the sports. They love the animals. They love the places. It's their desire to preserve these species, to preserve these places that drive all these efforts. When you consider these facts, this history, the billions, literally billions of dollars raised by hunters for conservation, the millions of acres preserved, the hundreds of species that have benefited, I think it's clear that hunting plays a very critical role in wildlife conservation, and that's why I hope that you will agree with me tonight and support this proposition.</p><p end="1873" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="1815">Thank you.</p><p end="2519" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="2462">So, well, just to close, though, it's great to talk about Teddy Roosevelt. But what about now?</p><p end="2519" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="2462">What about now? Right now is --</p><p end="2519" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="2462">Yeah.</p><p end="2589" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="2519">-- if land is being developed. We always need to protect healthy habitat for wildlife, and that is what hunters always advocate for.</p><p end="2704" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="2646">I think absolutely not, and I think you're being really disingenuous, Adam. I mean,</p><p end="2704" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="2646">you're obfuscating market hunting, people killing predators because they're competing with livestock, with sportsmen. And you know and I know that they are not same thing.</p><p end="2704" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="2646">I'm sorry. I couldn't hear you over the applause.</p><p end="2704" is_meta="true" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="2646">laughter</p><p end="2767" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="2704">But --</p><p end="2767" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="2704">No, Wayne. Let me finish. Do not interrupt me.</p><p end="2767" is_meta="true" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="2704">laughter</p><p end="2767" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="2704">That's John&#8217;s job.</p><p end="2767" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="2704">Sure.</p><p end="2833" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="2767">No one --</p><p end="2833" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="2767">-- is hunting them for food. They're killing -- John, they're --</p><p end="2833" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="2767">Right.</p><p end="2833" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="2767">That view is invalidated by the fact that the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service just listed them as threatened or endangered and when they wrote the rulemaking they said that trophy hunting was one of the causative factors in the decline.</p><p end="2888" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="2833">Now there are multiple explanations for the decline of lions. Certainly herdsman,</p><p end="2888" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="2833">habitat loss, but when you're killing, Adam said it was 500 a year, the last year that it happened was 720 lions out of 20,000 that are surviving. How is that not going to have an effect?</p><p end="2888" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="2833">Well, to get back to wolves for a minute, &#8211;wolves are reintroduced --</p><p end="2888" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="2833">I think it's really simple.</p><p end="2888" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="2833">Yeah. I'm sorry. What the Fish and Wildlife Service has also found is that there are instances in which hunting can benefit lion populations, and it's because we tend to get obsessed on the 1 percent, the Cecil.</p><p end="2944" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="2888">We really need from a conservation focus to be focused on the 99 percent. The money raised by killing one old male lion who's probably starting to prey on cattle, possibly starting to prey on people because he's no longer able to catch the gazelle. That money then gets funneled back into protecting the 99 percent of the lion population.</p><p end="2944" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="2888">Conservation is a resource --</p><p end="2944" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="2888">That lion if not killed by a hunter, who is willing to pay money into the conservation system, will be killed by the local villagers.</p><p end="3067" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="3011">I think you could put that up at auction at any number of the sportsmen's conventions and people would pay it.</p><p end="3067" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="3011">Conservation does not come for free. It is a very capital intensive effort. You know,</p><p end="3067" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="3011">something we talked a little bit about photo tourism and ecotourism and that's great.</p><p end="3067" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="3011">We need that, too, but the reality is in Africa it's not possible everywhere.</p><p end="3122" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="3067">Thank you. I did want to say just about the lions that --</p><p end="3122" is_meta="true" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="3067">laughter</p><p end="3122" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="3067">While we're on the subject. Botswana just outlawed trophy hunting. There are more lions in Botswana than any other country in Africa. They outlawed all trophy hunting of these animals and the wildlife authorities there say we can make much more money by keeping the living capital there. You can watch a lion a hundred times. You can watch a lion 500 times. You can monetize that each time, aggregating more dollars for the economy for rural communities, for the government. You can shoot the animal only once.</p><p end="3189" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="3122">The arithmetic is so plain to me.</p><p end="3189" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="3122">The numbers are undeniable. I mean, how many people are interested in trophy hunting? A few tens of thousands? They're the ones who are aging. They're the declining numbers, not those old lions.</p><p end="3189" is_meta="true" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="3122">applause</p><p end="3189" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="3122">And how many millions of us glory in seeing elephants and lions and consider it the experience of a lifetime to see them and to take a picture of them? That's fine. Leave them there. We want them to stay alive because they're wonderful creatures. So just look at the underlying numbers. If you have people paying for wildlife watching concessions and you have millions doing it, then you have just the few thousand people who want to shoot these animals and run away with their heads and their hides.</p><p end="3245" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="3189">I mean, it's so clear. Look at the numbers. Adam quoted many of the numbers. The trophy hunting concessions in Africa are miniscule compared to wildlife watching which is why Botswana and Kenya and Rwanda have banned all trophy hunting.</p><p end="3245" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="3189">Are we back to wolves or are we talking about --</p><p end="3245" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="3189">I don't think it can, first of all, but it doesn't have to be an either/or thing, especially when you're talking --</p><p end="3245" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="3189">Yeah. It doesn't need to be and it shouldn't be an either/or thing, especially when you're talking about North America. When you're talking about North America where the wildlife populations are high and sustainable and, by the way, it's not, "Trust us." It's not, "Trust hunters." We don't set them.</p><p end="3307" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="3245">I don't think you should trust anybody, except the biologists and the professionals who study and develop the populations. When those populations are healthy and stable,</p><p end="3307" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="3245">there is plenty for hunting, wildlife watching, all kinds of activity. The problem, really, is habitat. It's not if certain animals are hunted, you're not going to see them at all in North America. Anybody have any trouble seeing white-tailed deer or wild turkey around when you get out of the city? That's not the case at all. You can do both. What causes problems is habitat loss.</p><p end="3307" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="3245">I mean, I agree with Wayne and Adam. The numbers are undeniable. You know, there was a study released by the World Wildlife Fund last year that showed that 74 percent of the wildlife conservancies in Namibia, including the ones that incorporated phototourism into their conservation programs, 74 percent would not be economically viable if they were to take the trophy hunting revenue out of their program.</p><p end="3360" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="3307">May I?</p><p end="3360" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="3307">No.</p><p end="3360" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="3307">I thought you were pausing.</p><p end="3360" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="3307">Okay.</p><p end="3360" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="3307">We also have to look at where the money goes to. You know in Tanzania, the wildlife division, receives almost nine times as much funding from hunting as it does from photo tourism. In Zimbabwe, their wildlife --</p><p end="3360" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="3307">Because of the way that their laws are structured. Now, that's not to say that maybe those laws shouldn't change, but that's up to the people of Tanzania. It's not up to Adam, it's not up to Wayne, it's not up to me. That's not up to anyone in this room. It's up to the people of Tanzania. In Zimbabwe, between 60 and 90 percent of the revenue that their wildlife division depends on comes from hunting.</p><p end="3420" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="3360">Thank you.</p><p end="3420" is_meta="true" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="3360">laughter</p><p end="3420" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="3360">You know, I'll just close by saying, you know, the United Nations World Tourism Organization released a study last year, and what they found was 50 percent of the photo tourists operations do not contribute a single penny to anti-poaching operations.</p><p end="3420" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="3360">That is abysmal.</p><p end="3420" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="3360">Okay, thank you. So Catherine keeps invoking Zimbabwe which is run by a horrible dictator named Robert Mugabe. It's a corrupt country. They are selling wildlife off to whomever wants to buy it. And the United States Fish and Wildlife Service, the leading wildlife authority in the United States, banned elephant trophy imports into the United States for a reason, for conservation lines of reasons.</p><p end="3492" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="3420">The U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service has placed the lion on the threatened and endangered list for conservation reasons. I don't know why we keep going back to Zimbabwe here, but I would like to turn the question back to Catherine or Anthony. If one of your enthusiasts within the world of trophy hunting wanted to trophy hunt a whale, you know, if they wanted to shoot a whale because they were rare, because they were big, because they were beautiful -- would that be acceptable, if they paid a million dollars for it? Maybe some of that money would go back to protect the tiny little piece of ocean space. Would it be okay to kill a whale?</p><p end="3492" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="3420">And I also think that -- this is something really important.</p><p end="3543" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="3492">Let me just say -- I think something has been missing from this debate -- is the fact that hunters -- people, human hunters are natural predators of many game animals. We've always been. Hunters have evolved. Humans have evolved as hunters, and the animals have evolved with us. Hunting animals is part of a long, acceptable part of the ecosystem, of the natural circle of life. And as long as it's done in a way that is respectful, that benefits not one animal of that species, but the entire species, as a way that lifts up the entire ecosystem, as a way that's done holistic, and to make the world and the habitat stronger and better and improve habitats -- I think that's a perfectly acceptable thing.</p><p end="3614" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="3543">I'm not going to hunt a whale.</p><p end="3790" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="3737">Sure. A couple things I'd like to clear up first. The commercial trapping of wolves and shooting wolves from planes -- we're not talking about commercial activities here.</p><p end="3790" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="3737">That's not what we're here to discuss. We're talking about regulated sport hunting.</p><p end="3790" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="3737">That's what we're talking about, not commercial activities. And when you're talkingabout wolves, again, the funds from hunters were instrumental in reducing the wolves to the greater Yellowstone ecosystem.</p><p end="3847" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="3790">And since wolves have been listed -- and they've been hunted -- the numbers have continued to go up. The wolf numbers have not gone down. I'm in agreement with Adam. No one -- no hunter wants numbers to come up and then they crash again, and they wipe them all out. That's not what's wiped these animals out in the first place. It was unregulated market hunting, commercial hunting, loss of habitat. We want the numbers to continue to grow. The numbers of wolves have continued to grow in the Yellowstone ecosystems, despite being hunted. They've expanded their range. They're in Idaho, Utah, Washington, Oregon. The important point here is that hunters are the ones helping manage those populations. And why do the biologists want to limit the wolf populations? It's not hunters, it's other activities. It's other people. It's ranchers,</p><p end="3847" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="3790">frankly. Ranchers will only tolerate so many wolves, because they eat livestock.</p><p end="3910" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="3847">And so, the state has decided that that's what they have to do, and so, they hire commercial shooters to trap those wolves and to shoot those wolves. The states. I would love wolves to expand their range, but the truth is, we don't live in a country that was like it was 100 years ago. There's not going to be wolves here in New York -- as much as many of us would maybe want them -- it&#8217;s not going to happen. People won't support it. Livestock won't support it. Farmers won't support it. It won't happen. And the habitat is not there. It's too fragmented.</p><p end="3966" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="3910">Because, as a conservationist, given the state that are in right now, I can't focus on one lion. I have to focus on the whole population. And we can invest tons of energy and resources into mourning Cecil. That's not going to bring him back and it's not going to do anything to conserve the lions of Southern Africa.</p><p end="3966" is_meta="true" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="3910">applause</p><p end="4019" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="3966">You know, I really think --</p><p end="4019" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="3966">And it's something I would --</p><p end="4019" is_meta="true" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="3966">speaking simultaneously</p><p end="4019" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="3966">Let Wayne go.</p><p end="4019" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="3966">And then -- but then let me go.</p><p end="4019" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="3966">Well, you know, I'm always amused by this argument. You know, whenever you do something to hurt an animal you try to attach some sort of social benefit or you try to rationalize it.</p><p end="4084" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="4019">The fact that these are old animals, I mean, this is crazy. Who's out there aging the animal? And who's assessing and what's a post-reproductive lion anyway? I mean,</p><p end="4084" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="4019">they're able to have reproductive activity until a ripe healthy old age. None of the researchers thought that this was a post-reproductive animal that Walter Palmer shot.</p><p end="4084" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="4019">And the fact is, the people are doing it as a head-hunting exercise.</p><p end="4084" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="4019">Yeah. I have a two-pronged respond to the question of who's out there doing it. If we look at the wildlife agencies of African nations, if we look at the wildlife agencies of all of the states in the United States, if we look at the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, all agencies that support hunting and recognize its value to conservation, these agencies are the world's greatest brain trust of wildlife biologists. They have more wildlife biologists on staff than Adam's group, than Wayne's group, than my group, than work at Field and Stream.</p><p end="4143" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="4084">These people know what they're doing and we're not saying trust us. We're saying trust them. The other point I wanted to make about Cecil is what didn't get caught up in the media and particularly the social media, was that Cecil was part of a study that was funded by hunters. The research study that Cecil was part of was funded in part by Dallas Safari Club, which is a conservation organization based out of Texas whose membership is primarily hunters.</p><p end="4143" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="4084">I think you answered it in your question. It's about the population.</p><p end="4205" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="4143">It's not about the individual animal. That's what conservation is. It's to build up a healthy balanced ecosystem full of biological diversity and plants, and one animal will not change that. The fact is, animals die all the time. We die all the time. There's natural predator and prey cycles. What matters is the overall biological health and thesustaining of the levels of the population. If the population goes down, you're right.</p><p end="4205" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="4143">That's not conserving it. The goal is for the population to go up.</p><p end="4265" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="4205">It certainly does happen, but again, we need to listen to the scientists. You know, we are listening to the greatest brain trust of wildlife biologists on the planet.</p><p end="4318" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="4265">They have concluded that yes that will happen, and maybe that is a moral issue and that is an ethical issue and we can debate that in another forum, but what those scientists have determined is that that is not a conservation issue.</p><p end="4318" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="4265">It's not something that affects the overall population.</p><p end="4446" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="4387">And can I just add to that quickly?</p><p end="4446" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="4387">You know, I'm no scientists, so when I bring up these issues, it's based on the science that I've been informed of and it's the scientists like Craig Packer, who is an eminent lion biologist, who talk about infanticide in lion prides. That's not a moral issue for me,</p><p end="4446" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="4387">though it's grotesque. It's a scientific and conservation issue.</p><p end="4574" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="4511">Well, ecosystems are self-sustaining. I mean, there are natural decimating factors that limit the growth of populations. There are density dependent species where lack of access to food or space or mates -- Look at national parks in the United States. Every national park in the U.S., with the exception of one, forbids trophy hunting and forbids sport hunting entirely. So we're managing those populations through Mother Nature who does it quite well and has done so for eons.</p><p end="4574" is_meta="true" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="4511">applause</p><p end="4574" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="4511">And if you look at the range of national parks from Arcadia in Maine to Everglades in Florida to Yellowstone, to Yosemite and hundreds of units of the NPS, all of the national parks are not hunted.</p><p end="4625" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="4574">That should tell us all we need to know about the maintenance of the systems. Now,</p><p end="4625" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="4574">there may be issues with deer locally in Middle Atlantic states where there's not a lot of winter kill, but that's not a conservation issue. That is an entirely different issue about whether you can sustainably hunt those animals year after year. But if we're talking about conservation and protecting rare species and maintaining the integrity of ecosystems, that's different question.</p><p end="4625" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="4574">There has been no proven way for humans, a nonlethal way, to control populations that is cost-effective, birth control, contraceptives, that sort of thing. We don't live in one giant national park. Not everything has that intact ecosystem.</p><p end="4682" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="4625">The fact is, there's a lot of people in this world, and it's growing every day. This habitat is cut up by roads. The habitat won't support predators. It cannot just be left to its own. It absolutely cannot. So, hunters have always been a part of that. We are a natural predator. We are a natural part of that ecosystem and always have been, for the history of both humans and animals. And when it's done in the right way, it's an absolutely effective and valid way to protect wildlife.</p><p end="4753" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="4682">I assume that question was directed at me.</p><p end="4753" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="4682">I don't represent the hunting sector. I don't represent the hunting industry, and I don't represent the hunting sector in Tanzania. I think that would be a better question to ask them, about why they&#8217;re resisting it. I can say, at the IUCN, there has been increased discussion about the need for transparency within hunting programs. And personally,</p><p end="4753" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="4682">it's something that I would support.</p><p end="4805" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="4753">No. It's much more complicated than that. There's a lot of reasons to hunt. You know,</p><p end="4805" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="4753">sport is one of them, but I kill animals for food, and the majority of American hunters do. Every state and province in the United States and Canada has rules about harvesting the meat and making use of the meat. Many times you have to pack up the meat before you even pack out a cape or horn if you're in a wilderness area. To me, I'm a locavore. I like to know where my food comes from. I like to know that my meat is organic, that it's free range, that it's lived a humane life. And for me, there's no better way to know that than through hunting. I'm very proud when I feed my family that meat. That's why I grow a garden.</p><p end="4868" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="4805">I can go to the green market. Sure. I could go to the grocery store. But that connects me to the natural world in a much deeper way. And I think that's a very valid reason.[applause]</p><p end="4868" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="4805">Okay. Catherine and Anthony have continued to rely on state wildlife agencies. And Anthony just said, well, he eats the meat, he's a locavore. That's a compelling argument. But those same state agencies allow commercial and sport trapping of animals. No one is eating those animals, the bobcats, the beavers, and those animals suffer for hours when they're caught in steel-jaw traps or Conibear traps, or snares.</p><p end="4868" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="4805">You're defending those agencies. Do you defend no utilization of the meat and animals languishing in traps for hours on end, with some states allowing trap check requirements of 96 hours --</p><p end="4925" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="4868">But that was their exchange, was the moral --</p><p end="4996" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="4925">Can I just answer one thing very quickly?</p><p end="4996" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="4925">Very quickly.</p><p end="4996" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="4925">No. [laughs] No. They were -- please, believe me, they were. But the point is, he says our guns are not natural. But --</p><p end="5176" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="5114">No, but I can address what Wayne said. I mean, when it comes to wolves, I think one thing we need to recognize is since they were delisted, and the state agencies opened seasons, they've only been increasing in number and they've only been increasing in range. Now, when it comes to habitat threats, wolves are highly adaptable. It's a myth that wolves are wilderness dependent species. And anyone who wants to challenge me on that, I would say go to Europe. You'll find wolves in the suburbs of Rome. Wolves are opportunistic, and they are -- I love wolves, because they can make a living anywhere. Now, in terms of, you know, do we need to control their numbers, it depends -- in relation to what?</p><p end="5234" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="5176">You know, managers have different goals based on habitat carrying capacity. They want so many elk, so many mule deer, so many cattle. And they're going to control whatpreys on those animals in relation to what the other societal goals are. Now, in terms of are there cost-effective ways? Maybe. Maybe that's a great idea for our next prize.</p><p end="5288" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="5234">Teddy Roosevelt was an architect of the National Wildlife Refuge System and even as an inveterate hunter he thought that there should be places where there was no hunting and national wildlife refuges were set aside as refuges. It's only because of the political lobbying that places called refuges are now somehow hunting grounds. On the broader issue of license fees, you know, there are so many different ways that we can monetize appreciation of wildlife and many states, because of declining revenue for hunting, take general funds for the purpose of supporting wildlife and most of the endangered species programs come from those general funds, not from hunting dollars at all.</p><p end="5288" is_meta="true" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="5234">applause</p><p end="5288" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="5234">You know, Wayne's hitting on something that I think is really important and some place where we might have some common ground here.</p><p end="5349" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="5288">The budgets for state wildlife agencies is declining and that is a huge problem for every single one of us in this room who cares about wildlife, and there are other ways to monetize the enjoyment of wildlife. Something that the sportsmen community, you know, has long supported is expanding the excise tax beyond firearms and ammunition to include things like kayaks and binoculars and tents and backpacks. And it's been really hard to get that through Congress and, you know, I would hope that, should this come up again as legislation, both, U.S. and Born Free USA would support expanding that excise tax, because there are other ways that we can monetize the enjoyment of wildlife and fund our agencies.</p><p end="5407" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="5349">Yes. Wildlife would be worse off if hunting didn't exist. Wayne has mentioned the U.S.</p><p end="5407" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="5349">Fish and Wildlife Service several times. The U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service has said repeatedly it's the funds generated by hunters that allow them to do their work and to manage wildlife habitats. They have said that hunters are the reason why we've gone from 10,000 elk to 120,000 elk. They're the reason why that have driven this great success of great game populations that benefit all animals all across the states.</p><p end="5464" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="5407">It would certainly be worse off. Again, the world wildlife fund report showed that in the absence of hunting 74 percent of wildlife conservancies in Namibia would not be financially solvent. This is home to elephants, lions, giraffes, all turned over to raising cattle. Is that really what we want? Or do we want those lions and those elephants and those giraffes?</p><p end="5524" is_meta="false" speaker="Catherine Semcer" start="5464">So not only hunters can enjoy being out in the wilderness with them, but photo tourists as well.</p><p end="5524" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="5464">Morning doves, dozens of birds, would be better off if they weren't shot for target practice. Wolves would be better off if they weren't shot for their heads. You know,</p><p end="5524" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="5464">hunting is going to be around for a while. There's a deeply committed small segment of the American population that favors it, but let's not make the argument because it's untrue that somehow this is a big protector of wildlife in general. It's not.</p><p end="5524" is_meta="true" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="5464">applause</p><p end="5585" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="5524">I hope you will vote, "Yes," on tonight's proposition because I think we've demonstrated with some simple unassailable facts who sport hunting has and continues to conserve wildlife. Hunters continue to generate a billion dollars a year. They preserve tens of millions of acres of critical habitat. They've helped hundreds of species. I don't think those are any numbers to laugh at. But I'd like to close by talking about a more personal relationship between predator and prey. In Field and Stream over the last 10 years,</p><p end="5585" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="5524">we've profiled about 150 regular folks who are doing exceptional grassroots conservation work. These are not biologists. They're not professionals. They're volunteers.</p><p end="5648" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="5585">These are people who care enough to spend their weekends building nesting boxes,</p><p end="5648" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="5585">installing water features on public land to help endangered animals. They work together to get different public and private groups to work together to preserve land so it remains forever wild. What these heroes of conservation have in common is their passionate love of wildlife and wild places that has been inspired and driven by hunting.</p><p end="5648" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="5585">It's simple. When you love something, you'll fight to protect it. I'm a backpacker. I'm a birdwatcher. There's a lot of things I do outside. But, for me, and 37 million other people like me in this country, there's something unique about hunting, the way it connects me to a natural ecosystem. It immerses me in the natural world and it makes me part of the system in a way that is ancient and really powerful. This gives me and millions of others this connection to the natural world. It makes me a participant and it opens my eyes to how easily man can destroy it by not protecting habitat.</p><p end="5712" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="5648">Look, hunting's not for everyone. It doesn't need to be. It shouldn't be. That's fine.</p><p end="5712" is_meta="false" speaker="Anthony Licata" start="5648">People react to different activities in different ways. But all of us need to work together to preserve habitats for future generations and that would be much easier to do if we all worked together towards the same goal. And that, more than anything, is why I hope you will vote, "Yes," tonight.</p><p end="5712" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="5648">You know, clearly there are many broad-minded, deeply committed hunters and they do care about the environment and they care about protecting species. But overall, as a community, if there was a deeply felt committed practical understanding of conservation, the hunting community would not tolerate dumbing millions and millions of pounds of led ammunition into the environment that is poisoning millions and millions of animals every year.</p><p end="5770" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="5712">They wouldn't tolerate exotic game hunting on fenced-in enclosures, which is horribly unsporting and inhumane but also threatens to unleash invasive species into our habitats that has so many ecological consequences. If they had a deep commitment to conservation, they would be right by our side in defending the Endangered Species Act from so many attacks. They would have been right by our side when we worked to pass the California Desert Protection Act to protect eight million acres of the fragile California Desert. Going back a little ways, they would have been at our side in defending and advocating for the Alaskan National Interest Lands Conservation Act, the biggest public lands protection act in contemporary times. When we're looking at the big fights for conservation, when we're looking at protecting predators like grizzly bears and wolves and mountain lions and African lions, they're on the other side.</p><p end="5829" is_meta="false" speaker="Wayne Pacelle" start="5770">So, you know, as I said, hunting is a long, storied action. There are lots of people who believe in it intensely. I get it. Those who are involved in food gathering, it makes sense in so many ways for them. But let's not mistake that activity which contributes almost nothing to conservation as some broader socially beneficial enterprise. It's not.</p></transcript></debate>