<debate url="https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/individuals-and-organizations-have-constitutional-right-unlimited-spending-their-own"><speakers><speaker name="Floyd Abrams" position="for"><description>1st Amendment Authority &amp; Partner, Cahill Gordon &amp; Reindel</description><bio>Floyd Abrams, one of the leading legal authorities on the First Amendment and U.S. constitutional law, is a partner and member of the Executive Committee... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Nadine Strossen" position="for"><description>Fmr President, ACLU &amp; Professor, New York Law School</description><bio>Nadine Strossen, professor of law at New York Law School, has written, lectured, and practiced extensively in the areas of constitutional law, civil... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Burt Neuborne" position="against"><description>Professor, NYU Law &amp; Founding Legal Director, Brennan Center for Justice</description><bio>Burt Neuborne is one of the nation&#146;s foremost civil liberties lawyers, teachers, and scholars. He is the Inez Milholland Professor of Civil Liberties... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Zephyr Teachout" position="against"><description>Assoc. Professor, Fordham Law &amp; Fmr. Nat&#226;&#128;&#153;l Dir., Sunlight Foundation</description><bio>Zephyr Teachout is an associate law professor at Fordham Law School. She writes about political law, with a focus on corruption: her book Corruption... Read More</bio></speaker></speakers><results><result against="49" for="34" submitters="live" undecided="18" when="before" /><result against="67" for="31" submitters="live" undecided="3" when="after" /><result against="62" for="12" submitters="online" undecided="25" when="before" /><result against="62" for="37" submitters="online" when="after" /></results><transcript><p end="543" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="490">I met some journalists. A time came in the late 1960s when I met a bunch of journalists. I was very impressed, almost awed by what they were doing, the skill with which they were doing it, and the national service that I thought they were doing by supporting the First Amendment.</p><p end="543" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="490">My partner, I am very honored to be with one of the great civil liberties lawyers, and I mean this, in the country's history, Nadine Strossen.</p><p end="602" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="543">Not at all difficult, I've been doing this since at least the late 1970s when the ACLU controversially and successfully defended the free speech rights of Nazis to march in Skokie, Illinois.</p><p end="654" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="602">I have enormous faith in free speech, and I love to try to spread that.</p><p end="654" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="602">Yep, thank you.</p><p end="654" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="602">Well, maybe they're not getting it wrong. This is an issue that divides the free speech community, and it's a very, very hard one.</p><p end="712" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="654">Where I think they've gone wrong is that they're willing to tolerate the degree of inequality that uncontrolled spending brings into the democracy, and I think it destroys any notion of a truly egalitarian democracy.</p><p end="712" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="654">Oh, my teammate is my colleague at Fordham Law School, Zephyr Teachout.</p><p end="892" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="840">Thank you.</p><p end="892" is_meta="true" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="840">applause</p><p end="892" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="840">Thank you. I'm delighted to be here at the National Constitution Center defending a proposition that is supported by the constitution's grand opening words. You all know them. "We the people." As those words underscore, we individuals are sovereign.</p><p end="892" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="840">Therefore, we have no right more essential than the right to engage in our own politicalspeech -- speech about public affairs, speech about political campaigns. As the Supreme Court put it, speech concerning public affairs is more than self-expression. It is the essence of self-government. Especially essential is our right to criticize candidates,</p><p end="892" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="840">officials, and policies.</p><p end="958" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="892">Therefore, it's hard to imagine a greater violation of our precious free speech rights than for the government -- in other words, incumbent officials -- to limit our right to criticize them and their policies or to limit our right to advocate alternatives. It's likewise anathema for government to limit our right to band together with other like-minded individuals to amplify our voices. The Supreme Court first so held in landmark cases from the civil rights area involving the NAACP, which was a corporation. And from them,</p><p end="958" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="892">what I've said so far, individuals and our organizations clearly have a constitutional right to unlimited political speech. So, that means there's only one aspect of tonight's resolution that's really at issue. And that is whether we also have a constitutional right to unlimited spending in support of our political speech.</p><p end="1026" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="958">But logically, the answer to that question clearly has to be yes, because unlimited spending is a pre-requisite for unlimited speech. When the government limits how much we may spend on our speech, it necessarily limits the speech itself, in quantity and or quality. Think about it. Suppose the government imposed maximum spending limits on IQ Squared or on the National Constitution Center or -- dare I say, on the Brennan</p><p end="1026" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="958">Center for Justice? All of which are corporations, by the way. Those spending limits would clearly limit the amount that could be said by any of those fine organizations.</p><p end="1026" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="958">Every communication requires some spending. And since costly TV ads are so important in election campaigns, you have to spend a lot to reach a critical mass of the voters. So,</p><p end="1026" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="958">for government to limit what we may spend on our own political speech, including our criticism and our dissent, is for the government to limit our criticism and dissent.</p><p end="1080" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="1026">And that violates not only the rights of all of us dissidents, but also the rights of everyone to hear us. That point was well-made back in 1957 by three of the greatest,</p><p end="1080" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="1026">most liberal egalitarian justices ever to grace the Supreme Court bench -- Chief Justice Earl Warren, Hugo Black, and William O. Douglas. They were reviewing the very first federal law to limit spending on political speech. It banned such spending by corporations, and by labor unions on a rationale that we continue to hear, including from our esteemed opponents tonight, namely that these organizations are so rich and so powerful that they could be unduly influential. They could drown out others. But these justices resoundingly rejected that rationale as anti-democratic.</p><p end="1143" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="1080">As they explained It is we the people who are sovereign. It is there are vitally important that we the people have access to every view of every group in the community. After all, if there are any groups that are disproportionately powerful in the political process,</p><p end="1143" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="1080">it's the Constitutional media with their unique impact on public opinion. Yet we wouldn't even dream of letting the government limit what even the most powerful media company could spend on its political views. Even those who want to limit what the rest of us spend draw the line at the media even when they're part of conglomerates. But since media moguls have the right to unlimited spending on their political speech, surely it follows that the rest of us must have the very same right,</p><p end="1143" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="1080">otherwise it unfairly amplifies the voices of the rich and powerful people in groups who can afford to buy a media outlet.</p><p end="1204" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="1143">So that's just one of the reasons why spending limits actually undermine their stated goal, namely of leveling the playing field. Another reason is that spending limits favor incumbents and the two major particular parties, which should hardly surprise us because after all it's the incumbents who pass these laws. Now, our opponents are going to argue, and they already have, that these limits promote equality and integrity in our political system. Certainly these are extremely worthy goals. But as I've already noted, the goals are not in fact served. They are underserved by spending limits as Floyd will amplify on that further. For these reasons, please vote yes on the motion for unlimited political speech and therefore the unlimited spending that facilitates it and against government limits on what we the people may say and hear about it.</p><p end="1681" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="1618">Good evening. I want to start with a point that Nadine made, which I don't think was responded to, and that is that without the ability to spend money, we don't have political speech, at least we don't have enough political speech to have a chance to win most elections. Look around this room. Imagine that this was not the national Constitution center but a political hall, but otherwise just the same, with all you people here. We couldn't have this event, we couldn't have a debate without paying for the lights, the microphones, the cameras, everything in the room.</p><p end="1748" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="1681">There are people here, I want to assure you not the speakers, who are being here tonight. And none of this could occur if people didn't spend money to back it up, to make it happen, to allow it to happen. Now, Burt talked about -- he used the phrase about "One man, one vote." We have never ever lived in a system of one speech, one person, or limited speech per person. We don't say that. We wouldn't imagine saying that to our newspapers or our media entities, however large they are. If you were to take Burt's point literally, you would say, "It is -- we cannot persist in the notion that Rupert Murdoch can have all the money and power he has," or that the Philadelphia Inquirer could have all the power that at least it once had in Philadelphia and that it certainly does to a significant degree today.</p><p end="1800" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="1748">It's perfectly true to say that people with money have more influence and power than people who don't. That's the way of the world. How do we deal with that? We can deal with equality as best we can as a public. We can have laws. Some of them we have already. We can have better laws about people being able to vote instead of closing polls early in the day. We can limit the money if that's what we're after. We can have higher taxes. I'm not advocating anything today. I'm just saying it doesn't violate the First Amendment to have a wealth tax. It doesn't violate the First Amendment to crackdown on banks. It doesn't violate the First Amendment to have tougher antitrust laws. It does violate the First Amendment to limit speech.</p><p end="1866" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="1800">And that is what the negative side of this proposition necessarily is urging on you.</p><p end="1866" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="1800">Indeed, Burt did it. He is always straightforward. He was straightforward tonight. What is the argument? Too few people have too much power. And, therefore, what? They should not be allowed to speak as much as their money might allow, or, to put it differently, because they have more money and are prepared to spend it on political speech, our Congress, the very people who as Nadine pointed out have the most direct personal interest in passing legislation which will keep them in power -- that the Congress can pass Constitutional legislation limiting the amount of their speech. The Supreme Court put it very well in 1976 in the Buckley case referred to by Burt.</p><p end="1919" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="1866">I want to read you one line. The court said, "The concept that the government may restrict the speech of some elements in our society in order to enhance the relative voice of others is wholly foreign to the First Amendment." That's what the court said. That's what the law is right now. And I think it is a glorious articulation of First Amendment principle. And these were not the five supposedly rabid rightwing conservatives who gave us Citizens United. This was Justice Brennan, this was Justice Thurgood Marshall, this was Justice Potter Stewart, three of the most stalwart defenders of the First Amendment in our history.</p><p end="1990" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="1919">And what they were saying is, "You can deal with problems in a lot of ways, you can deal with the equality problem in lots of ways, but the one way you can't deal with it is by shutting up the voices of others or limiting the voices of others, wholly foreign to the First Amendment." This is one of the things that makes us so special in the world. I mean, it's only we, and we should be proud of it, but only we have a first amendment as strong, as totally controlling over what Congress can do as we do. So I would urge on you that while to some degree I understand that it seems not fair that people who have more money should have more power, if you want to deal with it, and we should sometimes, if you want to deal with that, don't deal with speech.</p><p end="2042" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="1990">One of the First Amendment principles that's first is hurt speech last. So, I urge you to vote yes on this resolution.</p><p end="2042" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="1990">John Donvan:Thank you. Floyd Abrams.</p><p end="2042" is_meta="true" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="1990">applause</p><p end="2042" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="1990">And the resolution is this: Individuals and organizations have a constitutional right to unlimited spending on their own political speech. And here to argue against this motion -- Zephyr Teachout. She is an associate professor of law at Fordham Law School and a former National Director of the Sunlight Foundation. Ladies and gentlemen, Zephyr Teachout.</p><p end="2042" is_meta="true" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="1990">applause</p><p end="2042" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="1990">Thank you so much. I want to point out, first of all, that my worthy opponents both relied heavily on arguments about limiting the press from speaking. That's an interesting debate, but that is not the debate we are having tonight.</p><p end="2095" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="2042">There is a separate clause in the constitution, a freedom of the press clause, which is put in there to protect especially particular kinds of institutions that play particular roles in our democracy. What I do think we are debating is we're having a debate about reality and we're having a debate about history. Both of my opponents, very persuasively argue, but I would argue they mostly argue from abstraction. Burt started his argument talking about money and how it actually influences politics. And I want to talk about history, because I think this is a constitutional debate in the most fundamental sense.</p><p end="2095" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="2042">It's about who we are, how we want to constitute ourselves, and what our most fundamental principles are.</p><p end="2162" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="2095">So, instead of starting with a text of the First Amendment, sort of separated from its own purpose and principles, I want to return to the Constitutional Convention across the street, 230 years ago and look at the core purposes of the constitution itself,</p><p end="2162" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="2095">because only once we really understand the constitution and what it is for, and what it was for, can we understand the place of the First Amendment in it. I've spent a lot of time reading the transcripts of the debates of the Constitutional Convention. And I'll tell you, there's one fear -- the core principle is representative democracy. Figuring out a system where the public good could be represented. It's a really difficult puzzle. And there's one fear that dominated over every fear, and that was the fear of corruption.</p><p end="2162" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="2095">They talked about corruption more often than they talked about violence, more often than they talked about the threat of faction, more often than they even talked about this -- current problems of the day.</p><p end="2224" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="2162">The threat was that this beautiful new country would fall victim to the power of money to distract representatives from their job to tend to the public good, the same way that they had seen Britain do. Pierce Butler said, "Look at Britain. You know, there we've built the fairest society ever. And yet, corruption has destroyed that fabric." So, they weren't worried about some technical question of non-representative democracy. They were worried about how money -- in all these different guises -- could come in and take away this sort of precious young country. At the time, the concerns were focused around gifts from kings -- the king of France kept giving these really luxurious snuff boxes to diplomats. And there was a lot of anxiety that that would lead people like Benjamin Franklin to forget that his obligation was to this country and not to France.</p><p end="2283" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="2224">Another major concern was that people would go into office in order to get good jobs later -- or at the same time. Butler also said, "A man takes a seat to get an office for himself, for his friends. This is the source from which flows venality and corruption." If you look at the constitution, there's not just the First Amendment when it comes to money and politics. There's dozens of clauses. And each of these clauses is communicating that what the founders cared about was protecting against this thing which is the danger to all republics. So, when Alexander Hamilton was asked, "What were you doing at the convention?" he said, you know, "Our job was to protect against -</p><p end="2283" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="2224">- but to create every practicable obstacle against corruption." And Mason said, "If we do not provide against corruption, we will soon be at an end."</p><p end="2339" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="2283">For the next 200 years in this -- Courts understood that protecting against corruption was one of the core jobs of law itself. And so you would never see a lobbying case,</p><p end="2339" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="2283">lobbying was illegal in this country for a long time -- a lobbying case or a money in politics case without a serious investigation about -- of whether the laws that issue -- or the structures that issue might lead representatives to forget their obligations to the public and instead serve other masters. 200 years after 1776, in 1976, you saw courts starting to forget that. I'm not going to go into the full history here, but my objection to the proposition is not what's in it, it's what's not in it.</p><p end="2405" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="2339">If you can't talk about the First Amendment without also talking about why it's there and without also talking about the ways in which it might lead to money taking over this extremely precious and rare thing, which is representative democracy. So starting in 1976, the character of money in politics has gradually dwindled and become smaller and smaller in all our court cases until recently, in Citizens United and McCutcheon vs. FECwhere the great tradition of the First Amendment is weighed against basically a corruption which the justices call the same as bribery law instead of the old corruption that our founders understood. So I urge you to reject this proposition because so much is at stake; representative democracy itself.</p><p end="2585" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="2523">Well, the First Amendment is the central thing we have to think about. It is the text that the Constitution has that gives us the answer. But the answer is not self-evident in the First Amendment. It's not as though God spoke from the mountaintop, and we know that the First Amendment says that unlimited spending is protected under the First Amendment. The text itself doesn't say so. Our history for 200 years doesn't say so. The Constitutional convention doesn't say so. And representative democracy doesn't say so. So it's not that the First Amendment -- it's not that we have to get around the First Amendment. It's that they're misreading the First Amendment. Read directly, the First Amendment is democracy's best friend. And they are reading it as a kind of conspiracy to destroy it, and therefore --</p><p end="2585" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="2523">We apparently have very different views of democracy and --</p><p end="2642" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="2585">And I think there's something extremely paternalistic and antidemocratic in the assumptions that both of my esteemed colleagues are making, that they're assuming that just because somebody spends a lot of money on ads that we the people are going to be duped and necessarily vote for that person? Or if information gets out that somebody has received a lot of campaign contributions and is voting accordingly that we the people are going to support that politician? The record speaks to the contrary.</p><p end="2714" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="2642">But the text talks about "Congress shall make no law abridging the freedom of speech."</p><p end="2714" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="2642">The Supreme Court consistently and correctly has said that any measure that abridges,</p><p end="2714" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="2642">i.e., cuts back on speech, makes it more difficult and burdensome to engage in speech is an abridgment. If you are told that you cannot spend as much money as you would like to speak as much and effectively as you would like, that clearly is an abridgment.</p><p end="2714" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="2642">Yeah, no, and I want to be just very precise about the way in which we imagine political reform working. It's not political reform mandated by the Supreme Court, but the public demanding a set of rules, Congress enacting those rules, and then the court, I would say, should only then intervene in these democratically demanded rules when there is something truly disturbing, some violation of the First Amendment which requires it, because the court itself --</p><p end="2769" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="2714">No, I was -- yes, but I was responding to your first argument that basically there -- what we want to do is empower Congress to actually respond to the constantly changing game of the corrupted [unintelligible].</p><p end="2769" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="2714">It's not clearcut.</p><p end="2769" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="2714">She left out the three most important words. The First Amendment doesn't say "Congress shall not -- shall pass no law abridging speech." If that's what it said, they couldn't outlaw extortion, they couldn't outlaw bribery, they couldn't outlaw threats. It says "Congress shall pass no law abridging the freedom of speech." The freedom of speech is not a self-evident idea.</p><p end="2828" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="2769">You have to figure out what goes inside the freedom of speech and what goes outside the freedom of speech otherwise why are those three words there?</p><p end="2828" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="2769">What you're missing is that the one area of speech which is most protected is political speech. There's nothing that we protect more than that. There's no area in which we give the Congress less leeway to act for a variety of reasons, not least that the single most important purpose for adopting the First Amendment was as a protection against the government, against the government influencing, affecting, limiting, chilling speech.</p><p end="2828" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="2769">That's why Thomas Jefferson, sitting in Paris, said he wouldn't support the Constitution at all unless there was a Bill of Rights which contained a clear, unambiguous -- what became the First Amendment.</p><p end="2887" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="2828">No, but Floyd, you're making two different arguments, and I want to separate them out,</p><p end="2887" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="2828">because one is a very important argument that I think we should pay attention to.</p><p end="2887" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="2828">When Congress passes laws that increase their own power or entrench their own power, we should be very wary of them, and we should be wary of them because it's abasic democratic principle against corruption, not because it's a first free speech principle but because it's an anticorruption principle. And then there's a separate principle which is embodied in the First Amendment totally distinct, which is the principle that we should be free from government censorship and government telling us what to think, whether or not we can say something about a particular invasion, what we think about a particular policy issue. And that is not threatened when --</p><p end="2887" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="2828">That is not threatened when Congress passes a law saying that a corporation cannot spend more than $60,000.</p><p end="2947" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="2887">Sure. I concede -- there's no speech here, you can't have speech anywhere. It costs money to run a democracy. The question is since it costs money to run a democracy,</p><p end="2947" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="2887">are we going to essentially say that the people with the money get to control the democracy --</p><p end="2947" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="2887">They &#8211;</p><p end="2947" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="2887">-- or are we going to try to pass laws that say, "Look, we have to figure out how to fund this thing"? But the way we don't want to fund it is to let the top 1/10 of 1 percent of the population have a disproportionate say in what democracy is --</p><p end="2947" is_meta="true" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="2887">talking simultaneously</p><p end="2947" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="2887">They don&#8217;t --</p><p end="3004" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="2947">And I also --</p><p end="3004" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="2947">No, we --</p><p end="3004" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="2947">-- I really -- I also have to make this point because Burt suggested that you have to choose between equality principles, which I hold as dear as First Amendment principles and free speech, the opposite is true, when the ACLU challenged the initial Federal Campaign Finance Law in Buckley versus Valeo in 1976, we argued that, that violated equal protection as much as it violated free speech because it is an incumbent protection act, as all of these laws are.</p><p end="3004" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="2947">Well, I mean, my position is that, of course, speech costs money. The question is,</p><p end="3004" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="2947">"Where do we find it?" Now, Nadine says, "Don't worry. Money doesn't always win." Well, look, I'm one of these poor souls that's rooted for the Mets for many, many years."</p><p end="3004" is_meta="true" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="2947">laughter</p><p end="3004" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="2947">I live in New York City and I have to face Yankee fans every day.</p><p end="3004" is_meta="true" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="2947">laughter</p><p end="3067" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="3004">Now, guess what? The Mets beat the Yankees every once in a while but over time the team with the most money to buy the best players wins the Series.</p><p end="3067" is_meta="true" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="3004">talking simultaneously</p><p end="3067" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="3004">Well, why don't you get an owner who spends some money?</p><p end="3067" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="3004">Well, that's true, but -- that's true in politics. The team with the most money wins, and the rich win in this country because they control the democracy.</p><p end="3067" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="3004">Burt, that is the worst --</p><p end="3067" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="3004">-- argument.</p><p end="3067" is_meta="true" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="3004">laughter</p><p end="3067" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="3004">Look, we have a disagreement here not just about what the First Amendment means but about what democracy means. To me there is nothing more inconsistent with the notion of democracy than stifling speech, period. When a government comes in and says either, "You can't say that," or, "You can't say it too often, it's just going to have too much of an effect.</p><p end="3125" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="3067">And we're telling you, we, the government, the Congress, we're telling you we're not going to allow that. And it's in your interest. It's really pro-democratic that we're doing that. You'll like it." That's why we have a first amendment.</p><p end="3183" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="3125">Yes, well, Floyd, there's something --</p><p end="3183" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="3125">-- that you repeatedly do which is sort of make an elision between unlimited speech and speech itself.</p><p end="3183" is_meta="true" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="3125">applause</p><p end="3245" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="3183">And if you go back to the founding era and the first 200 years of this country, there is a great support for actual limits, like you need a seven-year residency before you can run for certain offices. You can't have elections without districts, but that doesn't mean you need unlimited districts.</p><p end="3245" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="3183">[unintelligible] --</p><p end="3245" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="3183">The key is the people. And Floyd talks about the government as if the government is some alien other as opposed to one of the most extraordinary places in world history where we have figured out, in our fumbling way, but pretty well, how to have the government actually represent the --</p><p end="3245" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="3183">-- will of the people.</p><p end="3245" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="3183">Yeah.</p><p end="3245" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="3183">Oh, sorry. The government is the other.</p><p end="3245" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="3183">It is --</p><p end="3303" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="3245">And when we have --</p><p end="3303" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="3245">Yeah. I don't want to limit the kinds of criticism. I want to empower the public, the people, to say that we need certain kinds of rules about bribery.</p><p end="3303" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="3245">We have them.</p><p end="3303" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="3245">And those rules about bribery implicates speech, but they're important rules. And one of those rules about bribery -- the founding fathers would have thought of all our campaign finance laws as anti-bribery laws. That's how Teddy Roosevelt talked about them. And that's how all the progressive populists talked about them, is understanding that these are anti-bribery laws, because whether or not you're in the same room and having a quid pro quo, you know that somebody's basic obligation to the public is lost when there's 2 million dollars spent to quash their campaign from a private interest.</p><p end="3373" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="3303">Well, bribery is already a crime. The far broader concept of corruption that Zephyr has advocated here is one that says any time there happens to be an overlap between a position that somebody who contributes to a campaign advocates and what the candidate advocates -- that's corruption. That's not corruption. That is democracy in action.</p><p end="3426" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="3373">We spend money in support of candidates or issues because we agree with the positions they have already taken. When they are in office, they take those positions. They listen to their constituents. And by the way, every study that's been done to try to show a connection between spending and action shows that politicians are most influenced by their party, by their ideology, and by their constituents, not by donors.</p><p end="3426" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="3373">If I had enough money to buy more time on this program -- if I could have 12 minutes and Floyd could --</p><p end="3486" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="3426">So would I.</p><p end="3486" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="3426">And &#8211;</p><p end="3486" is_meta="true" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="3426">laughter</p><p end="3486" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="3426">-- the fact of the matter is, money buys influence. Why do you think large corporations give to both Republicans and Democrats? You think it's because of seventh grade civics?</p><p end="3486" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="3426">It --</p><p end="3486" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="3426">The idea that you were somehow not influenced by and not enormously grateful to some person who has independently spent money to put you into office is a fiction.</p><p end="3486" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="3426">There's no difference between contributions and independent spending in the sense that the politician who knows that his or her staying in office depends on continuing to get that money -- that's a politician who can't do what Zephyr said the founders wanted.</p><p end="3486" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="3426">The founders wanted -- maybe this is an ideal that is impossible to achieve.</p><p end="3539" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="3486">But the founders wanted a representative democracy where the representatives would think, "What's good for us all? What is the common good? Not what's my largest donor want? Now, whether or not you could do that &#8211; &#8220;</p><p end="3539" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="3486">That's a great question.</p><p end="3603" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="3539">Do you want to do it?</p><p end="3603" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="3539">It's a great question. But in each of those situations, you have to answer the antecedent question that I asked, is that is, is it speech, is it religion, or is it the press? Because if it isn't, then you don't get a freedom of -- "get out of jail" card. So if I make up a phony religion and run around and tell people that my religion consists of stealing money from other people so that I can advance my own principles, I would expect anybody in this room and a court to tell me bologna, you're not entitled to be treated as a religion because you are not engaged in religion. And I'm suggesting when you're spending astronomical amounts of money, you're not engaged in speech.</p><p end="3603" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="3539">I wanted to repeat -- okay.</p><p end="3603" is_meta="true" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="3539">applause</p><p end="3603" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="3539">I want to repeat Burt's last line. He said if that's what you're doing, you're not engaged in speech.</p><p end="3671" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="3603">The problem that they're addressing is nothing but speech. Their problem is the money goes, and it buys lots of ads. It buys speech. If it didn't buy that, it's nothing. That's their articulation of the problem. It just cannot, in my view, be plausibly argued that this is not a speech issue or not a freedom of speech issue. If you wanted to say to us,</p><p end="3671" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="3603">there are other interests you're not thinking enough about, or sometimes freedom of speech gets trumped by some national security issue or something like that, you know,</p><p end="3671" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="3603">we could have that debate. But this debate, we're having a debate now where our opponents are telling us that all these ads aren't even speech, that all this money that they find so offensive, which is going into the purchase of what? Things designed to persuade you.</p><p end="3726" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="3671">Or a political purpose, whatever the ultimate --</p><p end="3726" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="3671">-- whatever the aims are, even taking the most venal aims --</p><p end="3726" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="3671">Well, let me --</p><p end="3787" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="3726">Okay, so my partner's taking this question, although I'm happy to pile on.</p><p end="3787" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="3726">A metaphor: Suppose I had a huge megaphone or some way to amplify my speech, and I kept turning it up, and I kept turning it, and it kept getting louder, and it kept getting louder. At some point, although I was technically involved in speech, I would be involved in an exercise of power. And so what I'm saying is that at some point spending morphs into power when it is so high --</p><p end="3787" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="3726">-- that what you're doing now --</p><p end="3787" is_meta="true" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="3726">talking simultaneously</p><p end="3787" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="3726">That's a completely --</p><p end="3787" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="3726">It's not a fair analogy because -- then that's why I reject this drowning out metaphor that's often used by my opponents here, because it is true that if I shouted really loud then maybe you wouldn't literally be able to hear them.</p><p end="3845" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="3787">That is literally a drowning out. But to amplify speech by spending more money so that it reaches more people or that it's more effectively created or more persuasive does not drown out anybody else's speech. Moreover, it does not translate --</p><p end="3845" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="3787">The argument they're making is so out -- I want to talk how radical this is because --</p><p end="3845" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="3787">-- it is against --</p><p end="3845" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="3787">I love being [unintelligible].</p><p end="3845" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="3787">-- what Constitutional lawyers thought for the first 200 years of this country, and that they recognized the importance of protecting the ability to speak one's conscience did not extend to the ability to spend unlimited money. These are separate ideas. And ifwe equate them, we really equate them at our peril. And it is very similar to the equation that you just heard Nadine talk about, which is --</p><p end="3845" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="3787">-- saying that constituents [unintelligible].</p><p end="3905" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="3845">Wait, no.</p><p end="3905" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="3845">We enthusiastically endorse that.</p><p end="3905" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="3845">I mean, that --</p><p end="3905" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="3845">That could only --</p><p end="3905" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="3845">That could only literally be true in what I assume is a hypothetical situation that somebody literally bought up every single minute of TV time so the other person didn't have a chance to --</p><p end="3905" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="3845">Every study shows and elections show that these ads reach a point of diminishing returns. You know. How often do you turn off the TV or hang up on the robo calls? So there is a diminishing marginal return from extra expenditures.</p><p end="3960" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="3905">We are --</p><p end="3960" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="3905">And that's why they spend it because they know it doesn't work.</p><p end="3960" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="3905">-- smart enough not to be persuaded just because somebody is advertising more and more.</p><p end="3960" is_meta="true" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="3905">applause</p><p end="3960" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="3905">Okay. Well, by definition, any political speech is going to be dissenting from either --</p><p end="3960" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="3905">from one candidate or another candidate from one policy or another policy, right?</p><p end="4031" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="3960">You are -- even if ostensibly -- let's say I'm arguing in favor of the Supreme Court decisions protecting free speech, that is to disagree with those who take an opposite position; members of Congress who pass campaign -- limits on campaign spending. So every opportunity to comment on a government policy, by definition, involves the right to dissent.</p><p end="4031" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="3960">I just want to also --</p><p end="4031" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="3960">-- point out what I continue to see happening. So they keep saying this is a debate about reality and talking about the kinds of realities that we see. I think it was explicitly in the most recent Supreme Court decision, a debate about reality. The majority used the word "reality" a lot, and the dissent was talking about what's really happening. And I think your question goes to this, if the First Amendment is for protecting dissent, let's talk about what unlimited money in politics is already really doing in the last four years and what it is really doing in the last four years is corrupting our system so it makes it impossible for candidates to actually do their best job and serve the public.</p><p end="4091" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="4031">And that's the reality, not the word dissent, but the reality, the political reality.</p><p end="4091" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="4031">And I don't --</p><p end="4091" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="4031">I don't think the last four years reflect anything of the sort. I think we've had a lot of unpleasant disagreeable and, from my own political perspective, outrageous speech,</p><p end="4091" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="4031">but we haven't lacked for speech, and we haven't lacked for all sides being represented in a public debate. And indeed that happens more and more with the internet and more and more because it is easier for less and less money to get messages out. That's the reality.</p><p end="4091" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="4031">And more competition.</p><p end="4200" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="4137">No, and, first of all, there is a right to shout, "Fire," in a theater if the theater is on fire.</p><p end="4200" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="4137">You want people to shout it. And by paraphrasing that the way 99 percent of people do wrongly, you miss the central point which answers your question, which is that only if the speech in that case is false and, therefore, it leads to a harm -- directly leads to a harm that can't be averted in any other way, then and only then may you restrict speech as a last resort. So if we could show that there was some harm that is definitely going to occur and can only be averted by restricting speech, then we can do so. That is exactly why we can have laws against bribery even though bribery is committed through speech, laws against extortion.</p><p end="4265" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="4200">So let me tell you the two harms, Nadine. The first harm is the destruction of political equality, the fact that we all know we live in a country now where it is a sham to say that we have a fundamental egalitarian democracy. We have a plutocracy that's run by the rich, and that harm seeps into every piece of our democratic fiber, including the alienation that turns people off from democracy and keeps people from voting in the first place. And the second harm is corruption, the corruption that Zephyr talked about,</p><p end="4265" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="4200">the fact that we have representatives -- who don't have to be bribed. They don't have to be in the same room and get a quid pro quo.</p><p end="4322" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="4265">A wink and a nod and a day at the country club is plenty of time to send the message that, "We expect you to support us on this."</p><p end="4322" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="4265">And I'll ask the last thing, whose telephone call do they take after the election, your telephone call or the guy that gave him $2 million? That's the corruption.</p><p end="4322" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="4265">And if you --</p><p end="4322" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="4265">-- and I disagree with both of them. And let me say that -- so, again, we've had all these trials, there is no evidence, we're just hearing conclusory allegations here, but in 100,000 pages of testimony, and in these cases not a single instance could be proven ofthat kind of alleged harm, which is exactly why the Supreme Court has said, "Well, we can recognize just the potential appearance or the risk of harm."</p><p end="4384" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="4322">Another requirement, prerequisite, before limiting speech, as I said, is that the limitation is necessary. If there is a less restrictive alternative that will protect the values that are being asserted, prevent the harm, that's less restrictive of speech, you have to use that. And what we advocate, and the Supreme Court has upheld, is disclosure, immediately disclose, fully disclose where the money is.</p><p end="4384" is_meta="true" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="4322">applause</p><p end="4384" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="4322">And we, the people, can be trusted to hold people -- politicians accountable accordingly.</p><p end="4437" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="4384">The -- well, my -- I'm sorry. I thought you were addressing it to us.</p><p end="4562" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="4504">Yeah. No, I would -- I also took some issue with the framing of the question. And actually, Floyd alluded to this. He said we might take a -- I might take a different stance if I saw that there was another value that was outweighed. So, I would -- might maybe frame it, you know, "Do the people, through their representative electives, have the power to protect against corruption in ways that don't then infringe upon the core right to dissent and express one's views? or something else -- that I do think these framing questions matter a great deal.</p><p end="4618" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="4562">I understood the question to cover for-profit as well, and to be framed in a way to be --</p><p end="4618" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="4562">for-profit, non-profit, and individual.</p><p end="4618" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="4562">Well, and it also covers not-for-profit, because I think I heard Burt trying to carve that out.</p><p end="4618" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="4562">Yeah.</p><p end="4618" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="4562">And we --</p><p end="4618" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="4562">Yeah. I don't -- I don't have a problem with not-for-profits speaking.</p><p end="4618" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="4562">Well, that's what I'm saying. You tried to carve it out of the restrictions, and yet the laws haven't done so.</p><p end="4618" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="4562">Well, but --</p><p end="4618" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="4562">The laws haven't --</p><p end="4618" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="4562">-- we're not -- we're not debating -- we're not debating whether the statutes were well-</p><p end="4618" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="4562">drafted. We're debating a proposition. Let me answer --</p><p end="4618" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="4562">Unions --</p><p end="4618" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="4562">-- would be covered too. Of course.</p><p end="4679" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="4618">Burt --</p><p end="4679" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="4618">In the First Amendment.</p><p end="4679" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="4618">Burt &#8211;</p><p end="4679" is_meta="true" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="4618">applause</p><p end="4679" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="4618">-- I mean, I -- I've spent most of my life representing large corporations with -- no, with enormous power called the New York Time, and called CBS, and called NPR. I could represent this -- this is a corporation here. Our hosts here are corporations. The National Constitution Center is a corporation. And it doesn't have blood, and it doesn't have a soul. Stop.</p><p end="4679" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="4618">Floyd, you're the best &#8211;</p><p end="4679" is_meta="true" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="4618">applause</p><p end="4746" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="4679">I would certainly have spoken last.</p><p end="4746" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="4679">I want to answer that by saying --</p><p end="4746" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="4679">-- if the government had a law saying that the amount of time for each of us must be equal because otherwise it just wouldn't be fair, that would be a terribly and obviously unconstitutional law.</p><p end="4804" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="4746">It isn't fair -- it isn't fair to have a situation in which we get -- I want to posit it in our favor now -- in which we get all the time and they get just a bit. But the purpose of the First Amendment I think is different than you think. One of the results of the First Amendment is more things are said, hopefully more people get educated. But we don't limit the First Amendment if people don't get educated or if less is said. The First Amendment is designed to protect us first from the Congress, the entity that they think should pass laws limiting speech. That's the beginning and almost the end of it.</p><p end="4866" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="4804">Tonight's debate ultimately turns on the following question: How much faith do we have in our democratic egalitarian ideals?</p><p end="4919" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="4866">Are we willing to assume, as our Constitution does, that our fellow citizens can be entrusted with the right to decide which speakers and ideas to accept and which to reject? Are we really going to trust we the people? Sure, many of us have a healthy distrust of powerful, wealthy people in groups. But no one has anything approaching the power or wealth of the United States government. Here's what--one judge put it this way: The government has unlimited resources for touting its agenda. Those on the outside must rely on private wealth to make their voices heard. So it violates democratic egalitarian ideals that we hear our opponents espouse for incumbents to limit what the rest of us may spend to make our voices heard.</p><p end="4983" is_meta="false" speaker="Nadine Strossen" start="4919">Basically you have government insiders trying to justify these limits on all of us, the outsiders, by speculating, well, maybe some people will have dangerous ideas, or they're suspect speakers because they happen to be organized in corporate form. And that might lead to some potential appearance of corruption. But that kind of paternalism has always been rejected in our free speech tradition. We can't say because speech might lead to a risk of crime that it can be suppressed, much less to anappearance of a risk of crime. And we've cited many examples where people -- it's as inaccurate as it is insulting and condescending to say that we are automatically going to vote for the candidate who spends the most money or trust the candidate who's in the pocket of high financiers. So please show your trust in the people by voting for the proposition.</p><p end="5044" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="4983">Please, show your support for the people by voting, because the people want these laws. Every single law that we're talking about are laws that were overwhelmingly supported by the people and overwhelmingly passed by a representative democracy. It is five members of the Supreme Court and a group of ideologues who are telling us that we cannot have these laws because there is some magic formula in the Supreme Court that tells us that our democracy has to be dominated by the rich. Floyd correctly --</p><p end="5044" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="4983">because Floyd is -- has values that I share. We've worked together so many times.</p><p end="5044" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="4983">Floyd says there's many things wrong with this country, and we should fix it.</p><p end="5114" is_meta="false" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="5044">We should fix our tax system, we should fix all sorts of things that are desperately wrong. And I tell you, we can't fix it. There is no way that fixing a system that is rigged in favor of the rich -- and if you allow the rich to control who gets elected to fix that system. Our system is broken. It's broken because a few of us have so much power that we can control what the rest of us do, not every time, of course not every election is dealt that way. But over time, and through most of what we do, the rich have an immensely larger political influence than any of the rest of us. And unless we can do something about dealing with that, unless we the people can pass legislation that will limit their ability to spend unlimited amounts to carry out their policies, those are the policies that you had better learn to live with because there will never be a representative democracy in this country that will change those policies until we change the power structure of how we run our elections.</p><p end="5171" is_meta="true" speaker="Burt Neuborne" start="5114">applause</p><p end="5171" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="5114">I want to close with a story and I hypothetical. Suppose we had a situation in which a not for profit or for profit company made a movie denouncing a leading candidate for the presidency of the United States. Suppose it were a crime for that movie to be shown on television, a crime for that to be shown on cable, a crime for it to be financed and shown in either of those places.</p><p end="5223" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="5171">That is what the Citizens United case was about. Those are the facts of the Citizens United case. It was a not for profit. It could have been a for profit. That doesn't change what this is about. This is a situation in which once you say that, look, we'll leave it to Congress to draw some lines, and they represent the people. Congress after all is doing the people's work in a representative democracy. Sometimes they are. The view of the First Amendment of Congress is Congress is dangerous. Congress is something we need protection against. Congress is something we have to be really sure doesn't get involved with speech of anyone.</p><p end="5283" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="5223">And in this respect, speech includes not just individuals but institutions, labor unions,</p><p end="5283" is_meta="false" speaker="Floyd Abrams" start="5223">corporations or the like. So I would urge you that we have really a wonderfully representative audience here tonight. And it is very important that that audience focus on the underlying value of the First Amendment. That value is keep the government out of speech areas. That's what the First Amendment is about. And I urge to you vote yes on this proposition.</p><p end="5283" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="5223">Thank you.</p><p end="5348" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="5283">I urge to you oppose the proposition, and I'm also going to tell a story, but it's a much more recent story. I started running for governor in New York on the Democratic party line about two months ago. And so I'm sitting in my office, and I have a staff of six. And some of our job is getting on the fundraising, and some of our job is talking to the press,</p><p end="5348" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="5283">but there's something that we talk about a lot. I happen to -- I was excited to hear you mention antitrust. I happen to care a lot about taking on the monopolies in our current system. So I am actively opposing the Comcast merger. So because it is 2014 and not 1973, what we talk about is what the risk in my opposing that Comcast merger means because of the potential millions of dollars that could be spent against my campaign,</p><p end="5348" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="5283">defaming me, telling all kinds of barely true things about me.</p><p end="5411" is_meta="false" speaker="Zephyr Teachout" start="5348">So we sit in fear while we talk about that. And because it is not 1972, I'm not -- or I'm not Jack Kennedy, I have to worry about these things. I have to think about, "What is it that I could say that the Koch Brothers could spend unlimited money on?" I'd like to think it's not influencing me, but I will tell you it is hard for it not to influence you, it is hard not to say, "I'm just going to pick one target and not tell the truth about those other targets," because you can feel the potential power of those incredibly wealthy interests wanting to spend money to keep me quiet. So I have a commitment in the campaign, but I have an emotional experience right now of the effect of money in politics, and that's the thing the founders talked about is, "How do we make our representatives care about the public? And if we don't figure out the right relationship between money and power, we are moving towards an oligarchy, not a democracy, and that is the most unconstitutional thing we could move towards."</p></transcript></debate>