<debate duration="6750" url="https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/its-wrong-pay-sex"><speakers><speaker name="Melissa Farley" position="for"><description>Clinical and Research Psychologist with San Francisco based Nonprofit Prostitution Research &amp; Education and an Associate Scholar with the Center for World Indigenous Studies</description><bio>Melissa wrote Prostitution and Trafficking in Nevada: Making the Connections (2007) and Prostitution, Trafficking, and Traumatic Stress (2003). She... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Catharine MacKinnon" position="for"><description>Specialist in Sex Equality Issues under International and Constitutional Law</description><bio>Catharine specializes in sex equality issues under international and constitutional law. She pioneered the legal claim for sexual harassment and,... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Wendy Shalit" position="for"><description>Author</description><bio>Wendy received her BA in philosophy from Williams College in 1997. Her first book, A Return to Modesty: Discovering The Lost Virtue (1999) argues... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Sydney Barrows" position="against"><description>Author of Mayflower Madam</description><bio>Sydney is perhaps better known to millions as the "Mayflower Madam," found herself moonlighting as a phone girl at an escort service after having... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Tyler Cowen" position="against"><description>Holbert C. Harris Professor of Economics at George Mason University and Director of the Mercatus Center</description><bio>Tyler has written numerous books on the relationship between commerce, the arts, and morality, including In Praise of Commercial Culture and most... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Lionel Tiger" position="against"><description>Charles Darwin Professor of Anthropology at Rutgers University</description><bio>Among Tiger's books are Men in Groups (1969, 1987), which introduced and developed the concept of male bonding, The Imperial Animal (1971,1989), The... Read More</bio></speaker></speakers><results><result against="50" for="20" submitters="live" undecided="30" when="before" /><result against="46" for="45" submitters="live" undecided="9" when="after" /><result against="100" submitters="online" when="before" /><result against="100" submitters="online" when="after" /></results><transcript /></debate>