<debate duration="5339" url="https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/more-we-evolve-less-we-need-god"><speakers><speaker name="Heather Berlin" position="for"><description>Cognitive Neuroscientist</description><bio>Heather Berlin, Ph.D., M.P.H., is a cognitive neuroscientist and assistant professor of psychiatry at the Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Michael Shermer" position="for"><description>Founder, The Skeptics Society &amp; Best-Selling Author</description><bio>Michael Shermer is the publisher of Skeptic magazine, a monthly columnist for Scientific American, and a Presidential Fellow at Chapman University... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Dr. Deepak Chopra" position="against"><description>Integrative Medicine Advocate &amp; Best Selling Author</description><bio>Deepak Chopra, M.D., founder of the Chopra Foundation, is a world-renowned pioneer in integrative medicine and personal transformation. He is... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Dr. Anoop Kumar" position="against"><description>Emergency Physician &amp; Author, &#8220;Michelangelo&#8217;s Medicine&#8221;</description><bio>Anoop Kumar, M.D., is a board-certified emergency physician practicing in the Washington, D.C. metro area, where he also leads meditation gatherings... Read More</bio></speaker></speakers><results><result against="31" for="47" submitters="live" undecided="22" when="before" /><result against="26" for="67" submitters="live" undecided="7" when="after" /><result against="38" for="54" submitters="online" undecided="9" when="before" /><result against="38" for="59" submitters="online" undecided="4" when="after" /></results><transcript><p end="124" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="63">Thank you.</p><p end="124" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="63">Returning champion.</p><p end="124" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="63">Well, we did last time.</p><p end="182" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="124">Yes. Well, this was at the urging of my wife, to give Deepak's world view a first-world try. And I have to say, I did feel much better after the weekend of meditating. Of course, it doesn't hurt to be in Carlsbad, California at the beach of a five-star resort, getting massages, and drinking tea, and doing yoga every day.</p><p end="240" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="182">If you're not feeling better, you're doing something wrong.</p><p end="240" is_meta="true" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="182">laughter</p><p end="240" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="182">Well, Dr. Heather Berlin is the perfect debate partner for me tonight because she studies consciousness from a neuroscience perspective. And of course, Deepak's whole interest is in consciousness, and they have very radically different views. So, I thought it'd be good to have somebody who not only studies this professionally from a purely -- a neuroscience perspective, but also does some clinical work.</p><p end="240" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="182">Thanks for having me.</p><p end="300" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="240">Yeah, no. That's true. I was 5 years old when I first came to the realization that I was going to die, which kind of freaked me out a bit. So, I asked my dad, "Where -- dad, you know, where do my thoughts come from and can I keep them when I die?" And he said, "They come from your brain." And I said, "Okay. How?" And he said, "Actually, we don't know." And I said, "Well, what can I be when I grow up to figure that out?" And he said, "Well, I guess, a psychiatrist?" And so, that sort of -- from that moment on, it became my mission to try to understand where my thoughts come from, how my brain produces my consciousness, with the ultimate idea that perhaps I can keep my thoughts when I die. I still haven't found the answer for that, but it's been a quest my entire life.</p><p end="300" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="240">Maybe tonight. Maybe tonight.</p><p end="420" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="360">Okay. So, I'm going to argue in support of the motion from several different angles. But first I'm going to put my cards on the table and say that I am not an atheist. I was raised Jewish, culturally more than religiously, but I still remain open to the possibility that there's some higher creative power in the universe, some benevolence that I can't quite comprehend that might deserve the name God. But remember, we're not here to debate whether God exists. We're here to debate whether God is becoming less needed as humanity evolves. And however, we measure that need -- whether it's a need for explanations, a need for comfort, or a feeling of belonging, or just to give us a higher sense of meaning or purpose, the answer is clear. The more we evolve, the less we need God.</p><p end="481" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="420">Now, I'm going to go through these various forms of need one by one. But first, we should be clear what we mean by "evolve." We're not talking about biological evolution or changes in gene frequency. We're talking about cultural evolution, or just the development of humanity. And scientific progress over the past several hundred years has completely transformed our knowledge of how the world works. And each major scientific breakthrough has had to overturn some religious dogma, right? So, we've gone from believing in special creation to an understanding of how all living things descend from a single common ancestor by blind trial and error process -- natural selection. We've gone from believing that God placed the earth in the center of creation to an understanding that we inhabit a tiny blue dot in a vast cosmos with 100 billion galaxies. We've gone from believing that diseases were curses caused by evil spirits and bad karma to an understanding of the deep mechanisms of disease at the cellular and molecular level.</p><p end="545" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="481">But we still live in a world where people reject life-saving medicine on religious grounds. Just the other day, there was a news story about a 2-year-old boy who died because his parents chose prayer over medical treatment. So, the more our understanding evolves, the less we need God. Now, using God to explain natural phenomenon is an argument known as "God of the Gaps." Throughout history, if there was a gap in our understanding, it was by default to say God must explain it. But the more science illuminates our world, and gives us a real understanding, the fewer gaps are left for God to inhibit -- inhabit. So, when you hear from our opponents, be vigilant. They might tell you that the materialistic science can only explain so much. But we still need God beyond the limits of our understanding. That's a God of the Gaps argument. Just because science can't explain something yet, it doesn't logically follow that God wins by default. And if God is just another name for scientific ignorance, that's hardly a god worth celebrating.</p><p end="605" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="545">Now, my own field, neuroscience -- 350 years ago, Rene Descartes had argued that our perceptions had to be accurate because God would never deceive us. And our brains were made of physical mechanisms, but our conscious minds are an immaterial essence, a spirit that interacts with the physical brain through the pineal gland. But today, neuroscience is revealing that Descartes was wrong. Our perceptions are biased and inaccurate, which may explain the persistence of supernatural beliefs. And consciousness doesn't interact with the brain. Consciousness is what the brain does. And there's no reason to believe that consciousness existed before brains existed. Now, some people think they've experienced God directly, with or without drugs. But --</p><p end="605" is_meta="true" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="545">laughter</p><p end="605" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="545">-- neuroscientists can now induce religious or transcendental experiences by stimulating specific brain areas with powerful magnets, giving people out of body experiences and sensation with oneness with the universe, not to mention hallucinations that would rival the Book of Revelations.</p><p end="660" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="605">So, the more our understanding of the brain evolves, the less we need God. And evolutionary and cognitive psychology are also helping to explain the origins of our need for God, for comfort, morality, sense of belonging, and why that need is diminishing. Religions traditionally provided a space for communal activities, a sense of trust among in-group members, and a disincentive to free-riders. So, belief in God has done a lot of good throughout history. But our modern societies now provide laws and social safety nets to help us when we fall, and to disincentivize bad behavior. And our social reputations are online now. I mean, when it comes to people like Harvey Weinstein, I'd say that public shaming, social rejection, and criminal charges carry a lot more weight than the fear of hell. I mean, after all, he didn't hire priests for redemption; he hired lawyers and publicists.</p><p end="660" is_meta="true" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="605">laughter</p><p end="720" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="660">And the very existence of countries like Denmark and Sweden -- majority atheist countries that are high-functioning and relatively free from suffering -- tells us that living without God is fully compatible with human psychology, as long as the need make sense of the world is satisfied by science and our need to belong is satisfied by our social networks and communities. So, the more our societies evolve, the less we need God. Of course, for many people, life is not as comfortable as it is for those Scandinavians, and God is a source of comfort for those who are suffering, or who have lost loved ones, or who are stricken by poverty or disease, and I get that. But if we're determined to work together to alleviate poverty, disease, and suffering, and make people happier in this world. And if we're aware of the fact that people tend, on average, to turn to God less often when they feel safer, happier, healthier, and more stable, then we have to admit that the motion is correct: The More We Evolve, The Less We Need God. Thank you.</p><p end="720" is_meta="true" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="660">applause</p><p end="1143" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="1088">Thank you. Thank you. Thank you so much. The resolution, that The More We Evolve, The Less We Need God, I think is supported overwhelmingly by evidence from three lines of inquiry: evolutionary theory, history, and the social sciences.</p><p end="1203" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="1143">Now -- so first, John mentioned a synonym for "need" or -- necessary; God is necessary. Necessary for what? I contend that our starting point is the survival and flourishing of sentient beings -- that's us and other animals -- and the central problem with group living -- we're a social primate species -- the central problem with group living is trying to figure out how to get selfish genes that build these survival machines that just want to have -- maximize their own utility or benefits to cooperate with other survival machines built by selfish genes. And the problem is -- is figuring out how we tilt the incentives or create a choice architecture to get people to be nudged toward increasing or attenuating -- I'm sorry -- extenuating their better angels and squashing down or lowering our inner demons. So, it's this constant conflict between our inner demons and our better angels.</p><p end="1262" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="1203">And so, when we began to coalesce from these tiny bands and tribes of hunter gatherers into these giant chieftains and states around 10,000 years ago, this was the central tension: how do we do this? So, the two tools or technologies that evolved to do this were God and government. So, government basically gives everybody a copy of the rules and says, "These are the dos and don'ts, and here's the penalties if you violate them." Of course, there's not sophisticated police systems at the time. So, people got away with it. But you don't really get away with it, because there's an eye in the sky that sees and knows all that you're doing and can impose punishments in the next life. So, this is God or religion. So, for thousands of years, it was kind of a toss-up between anarchy of having no state or government organization, and tyranny -- having either oppressive governments or religions oppressing their people. And -- but something -- history -- then evolved about four centuries ago.</p><p end="1325" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="1262">The Scientific Revolution discovered that the universe is knowable and that it's governed by natural laws that we can discover and understand, beginning with the physical sciences -- Galileo and Newton -- into the biological sciences and medicine, all the way to the social sciences. And so, in the Enlightenment, there developed a number of theories about how best we should live with one another. So, there was [unintelligible] essentially to create -- to find the Newton of the social sciences. How best should we live? And that led to pretty much most of the moral progress we've made over the last several centuries. That is to say -- the abolition of slavery, and torture, the death penalty, the death increase in civil liberties and civil rights, the expansion of the moral sphere, the bending of the moral arc, if you will, toward greater justice for more people in more places, more of the time, I argue, has primarily been the result of science, and reason, and these Enlightenment values like natural rights -- not the function of religion or belief in God.</p><p end="1381" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="1325">In fact, I would argue that with a few exceptions, that almost all the progress has been the result of secular forces -- that is justifying why you're making certain social changes or passing laws based on reasons, good reasons, and evidence, rather than appealing to a higher supernatural power. The problem with religion is that the creator of the universe has set down many different rules of how we should live together. And there's no means to determine which is the right one. There's nothing in religion -- there's no methodology in religion comparable to science, in which we say, "We're going to -- let's run an experiment and see which one is the best, which one most closely matches reality." And I'm not just talking about physics and biology; I'm talking about social sciences. We have 50 different states with 50 different state constitutions and 50 different sets of laws -- say, gun control laws, or tax laws. You can study those and determine which is the best set of methods we should use.</p><p end="1451" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="1381">Religion has nothing like that. The problem with religion is that it's more of a sort of group cohesiveness method that drives people to be more tribal and xenophobic. And then, finally, in my third line of inquiry on the social sciences, I'll cite just one study -- among many -- by Gregory Paul [spelled phonetically] of -- correlating the differences between rates of religiosity, belief in God, Biblical literalism, belief in the afterlife, and heaven and hell -- in 20 different leading democracies in the Western world. As a function of their societal health, societal health is measured by rate of homicide, suicides, STDs, abortions, teen births, marriage, divorce, alcohol consumption, life satisfaction, corruption indices -- adjusted per capita income, income inequality, poverty, employment levels, incarceration, life expectancy and so on. Well, you can't believe this, but it turns out that the higher the rates of religiosity in a nation, the more people believe in God in a nation, the worst they score on these indices of societal health.</p><p end="1502" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="1451">And America stands out by far, with no one even a close second, as the most religious of the Western democracies and the worst on all of these. We have the highest homicide rates, suicide rates, teen STD rates, pregnancy rates, and so on. Income inequality, and alcohol consumption, life satisfaction, employment levels, and on, and on, and on. Now, I'm not saying that those things have -- are caused by religion. But if religion and belief in God is such a great force for driving moral progress, how come it fails so abysmally here and every other nation where religiosity and belief in God is high? Therefore, I urge you to vote for our side, that The More We Evolve, The Less We Need God. Thank you.</p><p end="1502" is_meta="true" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="1451">applause</p><p end="2046" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="1981">Proud of it.</p><p end="2104" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="2046">Yes.</p><p end="2169" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="2104">So, I mean, the way we experience the world that we find ourselves in is via first-person subjective experience, which we'll call consciousness, right? That's how -- yes -- we come up with the laws of science. And it's subjective, right? Only I know my own consciousness. I don't know anybody else's. We know that we can knock it out in patients. [unintelligible] lesions from parts of the brain, they can experience nothing. When you're in a deep dreamless sleep, you're not experiencing anything. And we can map out -- we can make correlation between consciousness and the brain. However -- and this is something, since I was 5, I've wanted there to be consciousness outside of the brain. I've been looking for it. I've been trying to find any bit of evidence for it, okay? And you can't trust your own experience because it's subjective, right? The way that we can understand reality in the most objective way that we have discovered is through the scientific method. But -- so what I'm really curious, and I can't get my mind around, is where they're coming up with there proclamations of knowing that consciousness exists outside of the material world, and then calling that God.</p><p end="2220" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="2169">I mean, to me, it seems a bit just like a fairytale. I can say -- I can also make a proclamation about consciousness and what it is. But without any evidence, I don't understand how they're coming to these conclusions.</p><p end="2283" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="2220">To say that consciousness is God is also just a subjective kind of thing that you're creating by your experience, right? You're using your subjectivity to make the claim that consciousness is God. So, I don't understand where the evidence for that is.</p><p end="2403" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="2342">Yeah. I think I figured out what was going on here after the --</p><p end="2403" is_meta="true" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="2342">laughter</p><p end="2463" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="2403">After my experiences at Deepak Center, and there was no illegal drugs -- or even legal drugs involved -- so, I've wrote a chapter in my latest book about Deepak. And so, I made a distinction there between the weak consciousness principle and the strong consciousness principle. So, the weak consciousness principle is that in order to experience consciousness, you have to be conscious. In order to experience something, you have to be alive and experiencing. And it's something that's, well -- it's what [unintelligible] calls a deepity [spelled phonetically]. It's like, it sounds deep until you think about it for a second. You go, "Well, yeah, obviously."</p><p end="2463" is_meta="true" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="2403">laughter</p><p end="2463" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="2403">You know, it's like imagining -- imagine being dead. You can't do it, because to imagine something, you have to be alive, okay? So -- the -- but what they're arguing is something stronger than that, the strong consciousness principle -- that consciousness brings about -- if I understand you correctly, Deepak -- brings about the physical instantiation of our brains and bodies, that the consciousness is primary -- it's already there. And we're just a temporary hold or instantiation of consciousness in the physical body.</p><p end="2520" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="2463">Well -- I mean, we -- to get the ultimate answer, "Which worldview is correct," we need to have some way to test it, to experiment with it. How do we know? I mean, if you just say, "It was my internal experience and your internal experience, and we'll never get anywhere," then it's a late-night conversation that's fun, but that's it. Can we do better than that? And yes; we know from neuroscience, for example, that you can -- as Heather mentioned -- knock out parts of the brain. And the function, the mind, the consciousness, whatever word you want to use -- that was doing whatever it was doing there -- is gone. And it's gone forever. Alzheimer's -- when Aunt Millie's brain dies from Alzheimer's, the memories disappear -- they're not going anywhere. They're just gone, because the brain tissue is gone. So, no brain, no mind. The mind isn't anywhere without the brain.</p><p end="2707" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="2640">So, there's lots of experiments which show that morality -- in babies, even -- they're more likely to choose a good puppet over a bad puppet if they watch it do something bad or good. And we can also see that if you get a huge lesion to the prefrontal cortex. People can become unethical and lose their sense of morality. We know it's tied to brain development and brain function. You know, and they talk a lot about this deep understanding, and the infinite, and you know, places where we can get to via meditation or spiritual practices. You don't need god for that, or traditional God. You can get to deep understanding -- they're all different brain states. We can manipulate them in the lab. We can talk to people and have them get an appreciation and a deep understanding. That doesn't mean that you then get to call that God. So, I still don't -- you know, I don't see that connection. And so, all these needs -- we have need -- compassion, and love, and understanding, and morality. But again -- of course we don't experience them without consciousness. That's how we experience the world. But I think what you're saying is that if we didn't have consciousness, if we didn't exist, the world wouldn't exist, because matter only exists via consciousness.</p><p end="2760" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="2707">So, is that true? If none of us were here, if none of us were experiencing the world, it wouldn't exist?</p><p end="2823" is_meta="true" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="2760">laughs</p><p end="2823" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="2760">Well, and I have a lot of insecurities --</p><p end="2823" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="2760">-- apparently. [laughs]</p><p end="2883" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="2823">That's the God of the Gaps argument. That's just --</p><p end="2883" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="2823">-- [unintelligible] understand -- here it is --</p><p end="2883" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="2823">Yeah. Well, okay, so?</p><p end="2883" is_meta="true" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="2823">laughter</p><p end="2883" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="2823">But --</p><p end="2883" is_meta="true" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="2823">speaking simultaneously</p><p end="2883" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="2823">[inaudible] or not.</p><p end="2883" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="2823">Deepak, Deepak --</p><p end="2883" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="2823">Let me just ask you --</p><p end="2883" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="2823">Okay. So, let's just do our thought experiment, okay? So -- the asteroid hits the earth and all sentient beings, all conscious life is wiped out on earth. Does -- is the moon still there? Is the [unintelligible] galaxy still there? Is stuff still in the universe?</p><p end="2944" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="2883">I rest my case.</p><p end="2944" is_meta="true" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="2883">laughs</p><p end="2944" is_meta="true" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="2883">laughter</p><p end="2944" is_meta="true" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="2883">applause</p><p end="3005" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="2944">-- conscious. Is this conscious?</p><p end="3005" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="2944">Right. Exactly. I'm not saying that --</p><p end="3182" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="3120">There's so many things. Okay. First, let me just talk about just this pure, subjective experience that you're sort of talking about as God. When we talk about consciousness, it's true. We don't need language. We don't need to be able to call this a cup or a hand. Babies have it. It's pure subjective experience. It's feeling pain, seeing the color red. We don't even need a sense of self for it, okay? So, that's what we're talking about when we we're talking about pure subjective experience. And we all have it. The question is, how can we get more of it? We experience the world via consciousness. Period. That's how we humans experience the world. So, how do we get more of it? We can have different aspects of it. We can see it in a different way. We can have a deeper understanding. All that is great. But that doesn't mean it exists outside of us. And I can even give you that consciousness may be fundamental. It's a property of the universe. We have theories in consciousness -- the integrated information theory of consciousness, that says any system that has a high degree of integrated information that's differentiated -- integrated meaning it has an effect on each other -- will have a property of consciousness. Yet, it is still instantiated in matter.</p><p end="3241" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="3182">That means brains happen to be one of those systems. But other things that have a high degree of integrated information -- degree of integrated information might have the property of consciousness. I can even --</p><p end="3241" is_meta="true" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="3182">laughs</p><p end="3241" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="3182">That is a good question. No. [laughs] I think the problem is is the --</p><p end="3241" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="3182">We are conscious. We --</p><p end="3241" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="3182">-- the word is too broad. I mean, we -- you know, as Vicinstein [spelled phonetically] pointed out, we just -- you know, we have -- we only have language to express our words -- our thoughts between each other.</p><p end="3305" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="3241">So, we look for synonyms. You know, consciousness is experience. It's the immeasurable potential. It's invisible. It's all modes of knowing. These are just different ways of saying the same thing. And it -- so, it doesn't really get us anywhere. There's no specific actionable points. Like, what do I do? So, the motion on the table is, you know, what difference does it make? What does it matter? And so, we have to have some definition. That was why I started off with the, you know, survival and flourishing of sentient beings. So, what does it take to do that? And now we have some idea about that. Now if -- now, I should say, just parenthetically, that I kind of went hard on religion. I know that the Quakers and Wilberforce advocated for the abolition of slavery and so on. There are, you know, certain individuals that help the process along. But their biggest opponents were their fellow religious people, their fellow God-believers. So, it's not God itself that's going to get us there. It's some rational argument, some secular reasonable argument. So, the fact that Christians sometimes say, "Well, I've reinterpreted Mark 3:9, and Jesus really meant women should vote" -- okay, fine.</p><p end="3363" is_meta="true" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="3305">laughter</p><p end="3363" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="3305">But you're getting there after the movement has already made it progress due to secular rational arguments.</p><p end="3363" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="3305">Yeah. And I would say, you know, if we think -- if you want to re-define consciousness as saying all of these things -- compassion, and being kind to others, and doing things that are actually real in this world to help people -- again, you don't need the concept of God, or a higher spirit, or something that happened before the Big Bang in order to do those things, in order to live helpful, kind lives, to make everybody's lives better. So, in a sense, I don't think that the more we evolve, the more we need God in this definition as well, because we can find it in other ways. We can get better and improve humanity in other ways without having some either real or false belief system. Either way, we can be compassionate. We can have a deep understanding. We can think about the infinite. We could do the right thing, and we don't need God.</p><p end="3420" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="3363">Science didn't do that.</p><p end="3420" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="3363">People do that.</p><p end="3602" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="3540">Can I say something?</p><p end="3602" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="3540">I mean, this is just a circular argument, because all you're saying is that --</p><p end="3602" is_meta="true" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="3540">applause</p><p end="3602" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="3540">-- all you're saying is the only way we can know anything is via our subjective experience, through -- via our consciousness. And therefore, everything is flawed -- or you're saying, therefore, then, consciousness is fundamental, and that's all there is.</p><p end="3661" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="3602">But you just -- I mean, you can't say we can only know the big bang happened because it's subjective, and therefore, subjectivity occurred before the big bang, or that's what made the big bang. I mean, it's -- none of it makes sense. And I'm also wondering where you're getting this knowledge from, this grand knowledge that all of us don't seem to have. It's like you're almost preaching it to us, like, "Oh, please. Tell us, what's the answer?" When I don't see where you're getting these answers from.</p><p end="3661" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="3602">Oh, so from objective scientific method?</p><p end="3661" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="3602">That's where you're getting it from?</p><p end="3661" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="3602">Because that's where I'm getting it from.</p><p end="3661" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="3602">My only way to experience the world is via consciousness.</p><p end="3720" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="3661">Well, I think what most --</p><p end="3720" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="3661">-- people in the Western world mean by God is an omniscient, omnipotent being that brought the universe into existence and created us, and loves us, and created an afterlife, and so forth. That's kind of a standard version of that. And the belief in that is really what we're talking about. Do we need -- Dan Danna [spelled phonetically] calls this belief in belief. Do we need to believe that people should believe, because it's good for society? No. I've pretty strongly made that case. Whether there really is such a god is a separate debate. And so, but if you just broaden it and say, "Well, it's just consciousness" -- well, all of this that -- we're just repeating what I call the weak consciousness principle, by definition. It's just circular.</p><p end="3780" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="3720">It's -- to be conscious -- to experience consciousness, you have to be conscious. Yeah. No kidding.</p><p end="3780" is_meta="true" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="3720">laughter</p><p end="3780" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="3720">As opposed to what? Where else would the concepts come from that we have of the big bang? Of course, they come from our brain. So, what? That doesn't advance us any further to knowing something more about it.</p><p end="3961" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="3906">I -- so, you know, I think --</p><p end="3961" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="3906">Well, we have these huge egos, and we think consciousness is so important. But actually, when you really look at it, most of what's happening that's affecting our behavior, the decisions we're making, and even helping us survive is happening outside of awareness, unconsciously, okay? And that's what much of the brain is doing. I'm actually more interested in the neural basis of these unconscious processes. And I think as we evolve, it's inevitable that unless we kill ourselves first -- hopefully we don't -- that in 500 years, we're going to start integrating with technology, we're going to have neuro-prosthetics. They're going to increase our ability to have memory capacity, need for sleep, maybe make our dreams more vivid. We can actually record from your brain and see what you're dreaming now, you know? We can see these images. It all is happening in the brain, as far as we can see. But we don't even need consciousness.</p><p end="4021" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="3961">You know, I think that ultimately, if the world -- the machines might take over, and maybe everything is just running on auto-pilot. But the fact that we put so much emphasis on this one little bit of the way that we experience the world, I think, is very egotistical.</p><p end="4021" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="3961">A collection of my experiences over time. I don't even think there's a real me. I think the concept of me is another invention of my brain, and it can change. And I could knock it out in people where they have no sense of self. So, I'll give you that. There is no I. I'm a collection of molecules that organized itself in such a way -- like Carl Sagan said, you know, we are the cosmos --</p><p end="4021" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="3961">-- [unintelligible] to know itself.</p><p end="4021" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="3961">I'm not going to get into this debate, but it's basically --</p><p end="4091" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="4021">It's --</p><p end="4091" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="4021">-- all -- the only way I can --</p><p end="4091" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="4021">-- know the world is through my subjective experience.</p><p end="4091" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="4021">Yeah. We're just back to where we were.</p><p end="4091" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="4021">Yeah.</p><p end="4091" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="4021">Yeah.</p><p end="4210" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="4140">Yay, so the whole, you know, Marxist, Leninist movement was a faux religion, in essence. They didn't do these things in the name of atheism. Atheism isn't even a thing to be. It's just lack of belief in God, full stop. They believed in certain economic doctrines and ideological doctrines that were, in fact, quite anti-Enlightenment, not at all in favor of equal rights, and free speech, and all the things that we think of when we think of civil liberties and civil rights.</p><p end="4262" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="4210">They were quite against that. So, actually, your example is one I make, it -- to show how what happens when you go off the rails of these core principles of Enlightenment values, particularly rights.</p><p end="4445" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="4392">Well --</p><p end="4500" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="4445">Okay. So, can we have a sense of purpose without God?</p><p end="4568" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="4500">And for me as a scientist, that's not hard to answer. The excitement of discovery, the story of how we humans have used reason and science to illuminate the universe around us, while improving the quality of life for billions of people. That story is far more inspiring than any story told in a religious text or here on this stage. At -- and that story has the benefit of evidence behind it. It has the benefit of perhaps being true, at least to the best of our knowledge. The fact is, people do find other sources of meaning and purpose when they lose their sense of religion, or even God. Atheists, as a group, are not wallowing in depression or existential angst, and they're no more likely to behave immorally than believers are. And we scientists are enthusiastic, engaged, and optimistic about the real-world benefits our work is generating. For instance, the U.N. Sustainability Goals -- none of which require a belief in God -- include ending hunger, and poverty, providing education, and clean water for everyone, protecting the environment, reducing inequality.</p><p end="4623" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="4568">If that's not a sense of purpose, I don't know what is. And insofar as competing visions of God or what God is, are still a motive for violence in the world, or for oppressing women, homosexuals, or non-believers -- then belief in God is currently holding us back. Now, many people still believe in God, and they need God in their lives, and that's okay. But that's not the motion you're being asked to vote on. The motion isn't does less of each of us needs God, the motion is the less we need God -- we, as a human species, all of us together. And I'm sympathetic to the comfort that belief in God can give people, and I wouldn't be arrogant to claim that everyone needs that comfort, especially when more and more people clearly do not. It's an empirical fact that we humans, on average, need God less than we used to for explanations, for community, and for comfort. And if you agree, or even if you think the modern world has diminished any of the needs that God has once filled, then logically, the motion is correct.</p><p end="4685" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="4623">We need God less. And I urge you to vote for the motion.</p><p end="4685" is_meta="true" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="4623">applause</p><p end="4801" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="4742">Well, I think our side made a compelling case, that the more we evolve, the less we need God. So, let me take a crack at our questioners -- where are we going to be in 500 years? Now, with the proviso that the super forecasters, after five years' predictions, fold at randomness [spelled phonetically]. So -- this is the best I can do. I think what we've been experiencing over the last several centuries will continue.</p><p end="4860" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="4801">That is, the expansion of the moral sphere to include more sentient beings, more of our own species, as deserving of equal rights and equal treatment. When I wrote my book on this, "The Moral Arc" in 2015, the gay marriage thing hadn't yet been settled. That's done. We can tick that box. Next, I think, probably, will be animal rights, and then possibly, probably within a century or two, that of rights for AI -- for intelligent beings -- for data, so to speak. You know, beyond that, it's hard to say. I think the idea of consciousness, if we use it in the terms like our -- the civil rights activists did, consciousness raising -- what does that mean? We're expanding our consciousness to include the perspective of other people. What would it feel like if I was treated that way? So, to this extent, something like the Golden Rule, which was discovered long before any organized religions, it's a principle of reciprocal altruism and evolutionary theory. It makes perfect sense that I have to make my case for you to treat me that I would want -- for me to treat you the way I would want you to treat me.</p><p end="4920" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="4860">That's about as fundamental of human psychology as it gets. And I think that's what we've been getting better at over the centuries. And despite the little down-ticks we have occasionally, of negative things that make the news, the good news -- follow the trend lines, not the headlines -- continues to go in our own time and will continue for centuries to come. I think that the -- and the fastest growing religious group in the world are the nones, the people that have no religious affiliation. And atheism is growing, and so on. I think we don't need that. The tools -- the things that we call religion and belief in God are actually just certain tools. We need love, and family, and meaningful work, and productivity, and the basic necessities of life, and once we have those, we don't need the superstitions from our Bronze Age ancestors. Thank you.</p><p end="4920" is_meta="true" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="4860">applause</p><p end="5160" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="5100">I mean, these are things that I've thought about before --</p><p end="5160" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="5100">-- you know, if I can expand my consciousness, and it can be outside of my body, and I could be one with everything, that would fantastic. It sounds great. I love that idea. I'm not against it. But as far as I know, and the years of people trying to understand this, and using consciousness -- we've had it the whole time. Right? We haven't yet come to any -- not even a shred of evidence.</p><p end="5160" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="5100">No. I mean, I wish. I wish --</p><p end="5160" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="5100">I want it.</p><p end="5160" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="5100">But it's unfortunate that we just haven't gotten there yet. And I hope that we will at some point, but I just --</p><p end="5160" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="5100">-- think we haven't --</p><p end="5160" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="5100">Yeah.</p><p end="5160" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="5100">And that's an experience --</p><p end="5160" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Berlin" start="5100">-- of your brain.</p><p end="5221" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="5160">Yeah. I think the idea that consciousness through -- discovery of consciousness, through, say, meditation is an excellent technology or tool for understanding yourself better, understanding other peoples better -- perhaps even this consciousness raising thing I was talking about.</p><p end="5281" is_meta="false" speaker="Michael Shermer" start="5221">I don't think you need any of the metaphysical backdrop to get the benefits of the technologies or tools you're proposing. And to that extent, I think if everybody meditated instead of whatever they do in Vegas or whatever causes people to go crazy, that would be good. You know --</p></transcript></debate>