<debate duration="5872" url="https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/no-fracking-way-natural-gas-boom-doing-more-harm-good"><speakers><speaker name="Deborah Goldberg" position="for"><description>Managing Attorney at Earthjustice</description><bio>Deborah Goldberg is a Managing Attorney at Earthjustice, the world&#146;s first and largest nonprofit environmental law firm, where she focuses on legal... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Katherine Hudson" position="for"><description>Watershed Program Director at Riverkeeper</description><bio>Katherine Hudson is the Watershed Program Director at Riverkeeper, a member-supported watchdog organization dedicated to defending the Hudson River... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Joe Nocera" position="against"><description>Columnist, Bloomberg View &amp; Co-Author, "Indentured: The Inside Story of the Rebellion Against the NCAA"</description><bio>Joe Nocera is a Bloomberg View columnist. He has written business columns for Esquire, GQ, and the New York Times, and is the former editorial director... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Sue Tierney" position="against"><description>Managing Principal at Analysis Group; Former Assistant Secretary for Policy at U.S. Dept. of Energy.</description><bio>Susan Tierney is a Managing Principal at Analysis Group, where she specializes in the electric and gas industries. She has consulted to companies... Read More</bio></speaker></speakers><results><result against="38" for="38" submitters="live" undecided="13" when="before" /><result against="42" for="42" submitters="live" undecided="5" when="after" /><result against="42" for="57" submitters="online" when="before" /><result against="42" for="57" submitters="online" when="after" /></results><transcript><p end="480" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="422">That's right. My love for birds is what woke me up to the risks that climate change poses for bio-diversity. And I got involved in fracking because we&#8217;re not going to be able to deal with climate change unless we end our addiction to fossil fuels.</p><p end="538" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="480">That's right. It was a bit of an unusual start for me. But I found myself working as a probation officer in New Brunswick, New Jersey. And it is actually what pushed me to go to law school, because I realized that I wanted to be part of the system -- I thought I could make a difference if I was -- and not on the receiving end of the system.</p><p end="598" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="538">Yes I have.</p><p end="598" is_meta="true" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="538">laughter</p><p end="598" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="538">Yes I have.</p><p end="655" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="598">Yes.</p><p end="655" is_meta="true" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="598">laughter</p><p end="655" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="598">What it means is that I was a pretty mediocre artist and so then I thought well, art history, that's kind of right, and then I was a pretty mediocre art historian, so I did whatever anybody in that circumstance would do. I became a policy wonk.</p><p end="655" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="598">Only because we did it around the breakfast table.</p><p end="776" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="722">The motion before us tonight is No Fracking Way: The Natural Gas Boom is Doing More Harm Than Good. Yes, the gas boom is doing more harm than good, but why? What is going on? Simply, the gas companies are rushing forward in the face of too many unknowns and too little control. In essence, these companies are engaged in an uncontrolled experiment, which is resulting in extreme and, in some cases, permanent harm to people, communities, and the environment that cannot be compensated for by any possible benefits.</p><p end="837" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="776">What my partner, Deborah Goldberg, and I will be talking with you about tonight is what those harms are that are being faced across the country because of the natural gas boom: the health risks for individuals, the impacts to the environment, and the costs for local communities. And why, in the face of the unknown, in the face of the harms, gas companies are so intent on rushing forward hoping to figure it out along the way.</p><p end="837" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="776">Well, what exactly is fracking? Deborah and I use the term fracking to refer to the entire cradle-to-grave process of natural gas extraction, from site preparation through transmission to end uses. The process begins with cutting access roads through the existing landscape and stripping a site about the size of five football fields to serve as amulti-well pad. Then the drilling rig will arrive, along with thousands of truckloads of equipment, water, sand, and chemicals that will be used to drill thousands of feet into the ground and miles horizontally.</p><p end="896" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="837">This is followed by the actual fracturing of the well which involves repeatedly, for a month or more, forcing two to eight million gallons of water and hundreds of undisclosed chemicals underground, under pressure, to fracture the rock, allowing the gas to escape. Then something must be done with the large quantity of contaminated wastewater, up to several million gallons per well, that will come back up along with the methane now released from the shale. If not properly handled, the methane may find its way into nearby drinking water wells. It may also be released into the air either intentionally or as a result of leaks. The methane gas that is captured is then processed and forced through gathering lines and into high pressure pipelines that will need to be constructed from numerous wellheads for hundreds and thousands of miles to the place where the gas will be burned, permanently carving up the landscape and communities that lie in between.</p><p end="961" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="896">To give you a clearer idea of how this fracking process is impacting people and communities, imagine that you'd go home tonight and find out that your next-door neighbor has signed a lease with a gas drilling company without asking you. What can you expect from this industrial activity going on next door? Even though you didn't choose to lease, you will be exposed to the same risks of contamination to the water you drink and the air you breathe as your neighbor. You will be subject to the same threat of leaks and spills of the fracking wastewater, which contain known carcinogens and radioactive material. Fracking-related spills occur on average once every three days in Colorado. Moreover, the industry has no safe disposal plans for this waste. Much of it is currently injected into underground wells, but this practice has been linked to earthquakes, and there's growing evidence that these wells are leaking. The gas well itself, and associated processing compression in storage tanks, will leak toxic and smog-</p><p end="961" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="896">forming air pollutants.</p><p end="1029" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="961">The once pristine air in fracked parts of Wyoming is now worse than the air in Los Angeles because of this. The few studies we do have show increased risks of cancer and respiratory diseases in gas land communities linked to these releases.</p><p end="1029" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="961">Like your leasing neighbor, you will be unable to escape noise that can sound -- the constant day and night truck traffic, estimated by New York State at 4,000 truck trips per well. There will be 24/7 noise that can sound like a jet engine, and glaring lights all nightlong during the drilling and fracturing of the well over the next month or more. You will also potentially have gas pipelines cross your property whether you agree to it or not,</p><p end="1029" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="961">and you will be subject to the same increase in your taxes as your drilling neighbor when your town has to repair the road damage caused by the heavy truck traffic that comes with fracking that will tear apart your rural and suburban streets, and when your town has to meet the increased demands for community services from transient drill crews.</p><p end="1080" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="1029">Proponents argue that the economic benefits outweigh these risks so far. But what are the supposed benefits of this industrial activity almost literally in your backyard, or down the street from your children's pool? The economic benefits for you will be limited. There will be access to cheap natural gas at least for a little while, but it won't last for very long because the amount that can be forced out of the earth is limited and will run out. But even more important, it will not remain cheap, because the industry will be doing everything it can to increase the price of gas, including exporting America's gas to other countries where they can triple -- yes, triple the price -- on the U.S. market today. The drilling will bring jobs, at least while the drill rigs are in town, but not very many and not for long, and these gas industry jobs are some of the most life-</p><p end="1080" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="1029">threatening in the country.</p><p end="1136" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="1080">Oil and gas workers are seven times more likely to die on the job than the national average. And fracking can destroy businesses that could sustain local economies into the future after the fracking boom is over, like agriculture, recreation, and tourism.</p><p end="1136" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="1080">What is clear is that gas companies are not willing to wait. The natural gas boom is moving forward as a large uncontrolled experiment with every individual, family, and community who has not signed a lease being forced to participate without their consent. Whatever transitory benefits fracking may provide is outweighed by all of the harms that it currently brings. But even more important, there are some harms that simply cannot be compensated for. If you can no longer live in your home or continue to work your family farm, if you lose your health, the health of your child, if you lose your life as hundreds of oil and gas workers have.</p><p end="1200" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="1136">If you lose access to drinkable water or breathable air as individuals in communities across the fracking states have, there is no good that can outweigh such harm.</p><p end="1200" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="1136">Until we have a much better understanding of the processes and the true risks, until there are mandatory rules in place to control these risks and eliminate the extreme harm, and until the industry actually follows those rules, the only defensible course ofaction is a cautious one. The only reasonable and fair answer is, "No, no fracking way."</p><p end="1200" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="1136">Thank you. In Kate's opening statement, there's one word that she didn't use, and that word is "coal."</p><p end="1258" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="1200">We're going to use that word a lot on our side of the ledger tonight, because part of the case for natural gas is it's the best single way to diminish our use of coal. And coal is without question the most environmentally hazardous fuel that we have in America.</p><p end="1258" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="1200">You know, Fred Krupp from the Environmental Defense Fund was in Aspen not very long ago, and he did a panel on fracking, and he said, you know, "I'm a realist. I'm also an environmentalist. Fracking is here, and we have to regulate it.&#8221; It's not that impossible.</p><p end="1258" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="1200">We regulate banks. We regulate children's toys.</p><p end="1258" is_meta="true" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="1200">laughter</p><p end="1258" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="1200">We regulate automobiles.</p><p end="1319" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="1258">We do regulate banks, actually. But when it comes to gas, we are in the golden age of gas, that's what we're in. It's not like we have a little bit of gas that we're busy trying to extract here and there, and it's going to run out tomorrow.</p><p end="1319" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="1258">We have something on the order of 2,000 trillion cubic feet of gas. We use about 24 trillion cubic feet a year. So, we have about an 80 to 100-year supply right now. That means, among other things, that gas is incredibly cheap. Right now it's in the two-dollar range. It probably -- yes, it probably will go up to the four or five-dollar range, which still makes it much cheaper than most other fuels and makes it very competitive with coal.</p><p end="1319" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="1258">Gas has -- cheap energy is an enormous boon for the country, just cheap energy across the board.</p><p end="1377" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="1319">It increases our GDP. It has enormous ramifications well beyond jobs. Natural gas also has the ability to be a transformative fuel and a bridge fuel as we think about moving to renewal. Excuse me, one second. So the economic benefit is one kind of benefit.</p><p end="1377" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="1319">A second kind of benefit obviously is the energy security benefit. I'm going to read something from the Wall Street Journal that ran just a few days ago. "America will halve its reliance on Middle East oil by the end of this decade and could be completely rid of it by 2035 due to the declining demand and the rapid growth of new petroleum sources in the western hemisphere. Shale rock is one of those sources." Now, who made this projection? It was OPEC itself.</p><p end="1439" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="1377">Think about a world where you don't have to worry about cartels, you don't have to worry about being dependent on our enemies for oil, a world where foreign policy is not dictated by our need for oil. The ability of the United States to have its own resource once again in a way that we never thought we were going to is a tremendous gift that's been handed to us, and fracking is the way that we're taking advantage of it.</p><p end="1439" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="1377">Now, the third aspect that I want to talk about is the environmental benefits, which is real and which is happening now. As recently as 2009, 45 percent of the power generation in the country was coal, 23 percent was natural gas. Today, it's about evenly split.</p><p end="1497" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="1439">There is a rush to natural gas and away from coal. This is a great thing for the country.</p><p end="1497" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="1439">Natural gas has half the CO2 emissions than coal, 90 -- coal has 90 times more sulfur dioxide, five times more nitrogen oxide. Coal is the dirtiest fuel we have. And so, if facilities could switch to natural gas, it has the potential to transform the country.</p><p end="1497" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="1439">You know, in Europe, where they like to think of themselves as extremely environmentally sensitive, their emissions are actually going up because they're building more coal fire power plants. In America, our emissions are flat and going slightly down,</p><p end="1497" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="1439">according to studies. And a large part of the reason is because we're having this rush to natural gas.</p><p end="1557" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="1497">The same is also true of China, of Mexico, of Russia, and of a handful of other countries that are relying on other sources than gas. We have -- what we actually have is a minute and 31 seconds.[laughter]</p><p end="1557" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="1497">Oh, I am?</p><p end="1557" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="1497">I have actually made my case.</p><p end="1557" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="1497">I'm good.</p><p end="1557" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="1497">I don't need seven minutes.</p><p end="1618" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="1557">To start, I'd like to bring the focus back to the motion that we've been asked to debate.</p><p end="1618" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="1557">We aren't here tonight to decide whether or not fracking is a gift or if it's a Trojan Horse.</p><p end="1618" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="1557">We are here to decide whether or not the natural gas boom is doing more harm than good. So, what characterizes a boom? It's big. It's sudden. And it blows a lot of smoke.</p><p end="1618" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="1557">And the natural gas boom is doing all of that to an extreme.</p><p end="1680" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="1618">It's too much. It's too fast. And the hype is just over the top.</p><p end="1680" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="1618">So, why do I say that it's too much? The most serious health and environmental impacts of fracking are largely due to very intensive gas development. We have 500,000 gas wells in this country, nearly 3,000 in one county, 11 compressor stations belching carcinogenic air emissions in a tiny town of only two square miles. Our bodies and our ecosystems can absorb a certain amount of abuse and still bounce back. But at a certain point, it's just too much, and the insults overwhelm the resilience.</p><p end="1680" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="1618">Take Pennsylvania, for example. In the beginning, Pennsylvania was letting the frackers take their wastewater, which is contaminated with very high levels of salt, to sewage treatment plants, where it was diluted with the sewage, and then discharged into rivers and streams.</p><p end="1737" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="1680">In short order we had a water quality violation in the drinking water supply for 350,000 people. And what's more, Pennsylvania realized that if they continued to let the frackers take that amount of wastage through its treatment plants, they would salinate every freshwater stream in the state in a period of two years.</p><p end="1737" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="1680">The same dynamic operates on a global level. Our atmosphere can absorb a certain amount of greenhouse gas emissions. But if we release too much, the climate warms to a point of catastrophic change. And the natural gas boom is taking us to that tipping point, because the way that fracking is done now releases very large amounts of methane into the air. And methane is a very potent greenhouse gas, almost 72 times as potent as carbon dioxide, depending on the time frame that you look at.</p><p end="1803" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="1737">A recent study showed that the leakage from fracking is about four percent of production and the scientists recognized that at that level gas loses its entire climate advantage over coal when it's burned for electrical power.</p><p end="1803" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="1737">The intensive development isn't really even good for the industry. Right now the industry is losing money on every dry gas well that's drilled. But it's even worse for solar,</p><p end="1803" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="1737">wind, and other clean energy sources, because they are displaced when the price of natural gas drops so low.</p><p end="1803" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="1737">The boom is not only too big, but it's way too fast. It is out ahead of the science. We do know as a result of lots of public pressure that some of the chemicals that are used in this process are toxic, but there are many chemicals that have never even been tested as to their toxicity, and we have no clue what they're going to do to our health or environment, in the short or the long term.</p><p end="1870" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="1803">We don't know where the wastewater that stays down below -- and that can be as much as 90 percent of the waste water in the northeastern shale -- is going to migrate in 20, 30 years or more.</p><p end="1870" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="1803">The development is also way ahead of the protections that we have. Instead of doing science and getting the safeguards before we move forward, we are flooring the accelerator and we're responding to crises. When you move too fast you cut corners and you have accidents, and that's particularly troublesome when you're talking about climate change, because the single most important factor for the social and environmental impact of climate change is the speed at which it progresses. We move too fast with climate change and we don't have time to prepare or to adapt, and so the climate scientists are telling us that we have to address the most potent greenhouse gases right now as fast as we can, and on that list is methane.</p><p end="1920" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="1870">The hype and the hoopla is clouding our vision and making it impossible for us to hear the facts. There are hundreds of millions of dollars being spent to ensure that this industry can continue to operate without the science and without the protections we need. $320 million spent on lobbying the federal government in just two years. As a result, what we are hearing now is not how we're going to end our addiction to fossil fuels, but instead, a hundred years of gas. Now, a hundred years of gas is based on extracting every molecule of gas from all of our reserves, even those that we haven't actually discovered yet, when it is well known that only about 10 percent of those reserves tend to be economically feasible to develop.</p><p end="1978" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="1920">And if we switch our power plants over to gas and our transportation systems over to gas, and our heating and cooking systems, and then on top of that we export liquid natural gas to other countries, how long is that abundant resource going to last? And at what price to our health and environment?</p><p end="1978" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="1920">The boom mentality produces magical thinking. The idea that this industry is going voluntarily to abide by a golden rule or a golden age of gas is just a fairy tale. This industry fights every protection we try to put in place, federal and state, often when it's even in its economic interests to comply. What all this means is that we are in the middle of an uncontrolled experiment. If we get this wrong, there is no turning back.</p><p end="2042" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="1978">And so we need to take the opportunity now when, we have a glut and we are not desperate for gas, to do the science and get the protections in place before it's too late and the natural gas boom that looks so exciting now goes bust in the face of the next generation.</p><p end="2042" is_meta="true" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="1978">applause</p><p end="2042" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="1978">Good evening, everybody. Joe told you about the upsides of the natural gas boom, and Deborah and Kate told you about some of the risks.</p><p end="2096" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2042">I just want to start by saying if it were only as simple as my opponents tell you, then life would be pretty easy. Let me tell you why their position, that the costs of developing natural gas are simply not worth the benefits, is wrong.First, what they didn't tell you is that there is absolutely nobody in the United States, no entity, that could actually introduce this proposition and make it so. There are hundreds of millions of decision makers in our energy system. If we rely on a regulated market,</p><p end="2096" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2042">consumers and suppliers all around the country, every one of you is making energy choices every day, they don't have the authority to completely stop this, no single state could stop this, nor could the federal government. On the consumer side, Americans tend not to think very much about energy.</p><p end="2171" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2096">What they think about is getting to their job or getting to the shop where they hope to find lots of options, whether they can power their computers, or keep their homes warm or cool, and it's those realities that people don't think about energy that much.</p><p end="2171" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2096">That makes this a really hard issue to deal with. Everybody wants energy 24/7. They want it pretty cheap. Many say they'd like it to be clean, and many really suffer when prices go up. That's the reality, and that makes this issue very gray and not as black and white as my opponents would tell you.</p><p end="2171" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2096">Deborah and Kate have set up in some sense a false dichotomy. They make it seem as though natural gas is evil and so everything else is pure. We know that that's not the case. Surely we should be developing more wind and solar power. I'm sure everyone in this audience agrees with that. Right now, seven percent of America's energy supply comes from renewable energy; most of that is from the Roosevelt-era hydroelectric facilities, those gigantic projects, none of which we would be able to build again for environmental impact reasons.</p><p end="2215" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2171">The other major portion of renewables right now comes from biofuels such as ethanol,</p><p end="2215" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2171">with its own problems from an environmental impact point of view. Wind and solar are expected to grow, but even if they're 10 times as much as they are today, we're still talking about a long way to go and a small portion of the supply, and I hope we get there. It's very hard.</p><p end="2215" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2171">But these and every other energy choice are really pretty hard and very complicated.</p><p end="2215" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2171">Why else would Japan be restarting its nuclear plants so soon after the Fukushima disaster? It's because they need energy. Why else would Pennsylvania be opening up its shale gas resources for development?</p><p end="2277" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2215">They'd like some jobs and economic benefits associated with it. And, in fact, why are coal states fighting so hard against the U.S. EPA Air Toxics Rules that would reduce theamount of coal burning in coal fired power plants? Surely the coal industry has something to do with that, but also there are a lot of jobs in that state tied to coal.</p><p end="2277" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2215">So what has clean cheap gas provided for us in this pretty gray landscape so far? Joe told you about how natural gas is taking market share from coal in the power sector right now. In 2012 alone, Southern Company, which is one of the biggest owners of a coal fired power plant fleet in the country, expects to generate almost half of its power from natural gas. That's three times the amount from gas as it was five years ago. And this is astonishing. Coal has dropped from 70 percent of its fleet to 30 percent of its fleet -- of power generation.</p><p end="2338" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2277">Now, certainly in a compartmentalized way, Americans often get really agitated about energy choices, but it's usually when it hits their backyard, as Kate and Deborah have told you. Unfortunately, every form of energy is in somebody's backyard. Many communities are split about shale gas. Absolutely that's true. Of course, some communities are split when they think that there's going to be a Wal-Mart coming because it affects the quality and tenor of their life in those areas. But think about it,</p><p end="2338" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2277">every type of energy facility that you can think of has split communities, whether it's a wind farm in Cape Cod, the power lines across the Midwest to tie the America's Saudi Arabia of wind to the people using wind in other parts of the country, nuclear plants,</p><p end="2338" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2277">the case for shutting down existing coal plants, splits communities apart. These splits typically come down to jobs versus the environment, and that's surely the case here.</p><p end="2401" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2338">Where I do agree with Kate and Deborah is that shale gas development does have important environmental and community impact. Should we regulate natural gas development more? Absolutely we should. Is regulation improving? Absolutely it is.</p><p end="2401" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2338">Colorado and Pennsylvania are the prime cases for advancements that are leapfrogging for best practices. The federal government is, too. Should we drop the so-called Halliburton loophole, which exempts water injections associated with hydraulic fracturing from the Safe Drinking Water Act? Why not? Wouldn&#8217;t that provide a lot of more public trust than we have right now? Should we tighten up emissions of methane from the whole process? Absolutely we should. But do we think that the United States should take shale gas off the table? No. That's unrealistic. It's not even sensible.</p><p end="2401" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2338">If we somehow -- someone in the United States could decide to do that, because it did more harm then good, what would we get?</p><p end="2466" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2401">We'd probably get a little bit more renewables, maybe a little faster. We would get a lot more coal use, and we'd have mountaintop mining, we'd have coal ash piles, some of which have recently spilled into rivers, we'd have much higher CO2 emissions that contribute to global warming, and we'd have unhealthy levels of mercury emissions and other toxic chemicals. There's a solution to all of these issues. There are best practices.</p><p end="2466" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2401">There should be much more aggressive attention to this. What I really wish is that people would stop demonizing this fuel, because it makes it impossible to find sensible solutions in the middle. There are sensible solutions in the middle. We should be working on enabling those to develop over time. Our main argument is that the two principal sources of energy in the United States, coal and oil, are much more damaging to the environment than is natural gas, and that's for the communities where those are used as well as to the nation as a whole.</p><p end="2517" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2466">Thank you.</p><p end="2638" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="2579">Well, first of all, I think we do know a lot. In any kind of boom, it is correct. Industry goes in, and the environmentalists have done a great favor to the country because they've gotten on top of the fracking issues early -- but we do know that there's methane leakage, and there's science going on right now to figure out what that leakage is and how to make the well casings better. And that's one of a dozen examples where the issue of the chemicals -- you can go to websites now and see some of the -- most -- all of the chemicals. Certain states have passed laws that demand that the chemicals be revealed. So, what's basically been happening over the last four or five years, you have cases like in New York State -- which stopped fracking until they could study it. And now they're getting ready to open it up in a small way, in a safe way. It can be done.</p><p end="2707" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="2638">Well, let me be very clear either right from the start that neither of us have argued that it should stop right now. What we have argued is that the boom is the problem, that it's going much too fast, and it's outstripping both the science and the protections. So, we think that what -- for example, what New York has done, makes a great deal of sense, is stop for a while, when it's not necessary, we have a glut coming from other places -- and take a look at what the impacts are -- and figure out what needs to be done.</p><p end="2707" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="2638">Well, we learned, we have learned more recently. But the fact of the matter is, there's a great deal that we don't know. And the reason that we don't know that is that theindustry has done everything in its power to keep us from getting the data that we need in order to really do the study. So, for example, I just submitted a Freedom of Information request to New York State Department of Environmental Conservation,</p><p end="2707" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="2638">asking them for the results of water quality studies that they had done in connection with oil and gas development in the state.</p><p end="2757" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="2707">And what they told me was, &#8220;We don't have any. We don't ask for that.&#8221;</p><p end="2757" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="2707">So, how are you going to do serious science if you don't have a baseline test of the conditions? And additional studies during operation? And follow-up afterwards? You know, we are learning something because of public pressure, but there's a long way to go.</p><p end="2757" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2707">John, yeah. I'd like to weigh in on this one. One of the things that the debate about what we know about the science focuses on is the question of how much methane emissions are leaking from the entire life cycle, from the production well all the way to the consumers' burner tip. And we actually -- there's a great deal that we know about that.</p><p end="2757" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2707">We don't know everything. We should know a whole lot more. Deborah pointed out --</p><p end="2819" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2757">We lack --</p><p end="2819" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2757">No. We should not slow things down, but we should absolutely insist on better measurements. We should measure what is a baseline for conditions prior to drilling --</p><p end="2819" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2757">There are a number of different harms. One of them is the multi-billion dollar contribution that lower natural gas prices have provided for the United States economy.</p><p end="2819" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2757">Another reason is the development of chemical jobs and industries that are coming back to the United States because natural gas is a feedstock that's supportable. The greenhouse gas emissions that have been reduced in the last three years because of --</p><p end="2819" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2757">when you take aside and account for the effects of the economy having crashed, there are much lower greenhouse gas emissions.</p><p end="2876" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="2819">I think that the benefits that have just been recited are questionable. For instance,</p><p end="2876" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="2819">luring the petrochemical industry back into this country, is that really what we want? Or shouldn't we instead be trying to move towards a green economic future for our children, rather than having --</p><p end="2876" is_meta="true" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="2819">applause</p><p end="2876" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="2819">-- a fossil-fuel based industry come back?</p><p end="2876" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="2819">Well, it's a big country. We need lots of different kinds of jobs. Of course we need green jobs. We need other kinds of jobs, too.</p><p end="2876" is_meta="true" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="2819">applause</p><p end="2876" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="2819">I'm speechless.</p><p end="2941" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="2876">No, I want to actually go to the subject of jobs, because one of the characteristics of the extraction industry is the boom and bust. And what is happening already is that there is -- when the rigs come into town, there are lots of jobs that come up. Truck drivers, they need a lot of truck drivers. They frack the wells and they leave. And then the economy busts. And the record is that those economies are in worse shape than before the extraction industry came into town.</p><p end="2941" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2876">What our opponents are saying is that when we look at a microscope about the impacts on localities, there are -- there are -- there are tremendous challenges that's going on in those communities. I don't think Joe or I would say that that's not the case. But every person in this audience drives a car, whether it's a Prius or something else, and there is extraction going on for getting that oil somewhere.</p><p end="3005" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="2941">Coal mining is all over the country and Colorado is an example of a state where they've said the environmental benefit of a natural gas fired fleet of power plants outweigh the risks and the harm. So there are tradeoffs and compensations across these areas. The wind farms, you want to talk about disrupting areas -- by the way, I'm a huge fan of wind farms. I'm in favor of [unintelligible] wind. I'm probably one of the few people who is very eager to say that, but as a result of that there are lots of community impacts in a variety of different places that people are talking about.</p><p end="3005" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="2941">I have a question for the side that's arguing against fracking. I'm just interested in clarity on the positions you have staked out and it doesn't -- you don't necessarily have to be agreeing with each other, but I feel as though you're not necessarily, because Kate Hudson is saying having the petro chemical industry retake root here, particularly in new parts of the country, is not a very attractive idea.</p><p end="3070" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="3005">At the same time, Deborah, you're saying well, we're not against fracking, we just want fracking to be good, to work beneficially and without harm. So, is this team against fracking, against the petro chemical industry, you know, working here? Or is it not?</p><p end="3070" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="3005">I think that we are not saying stop everything all at once and I don't think Kate is saying that either. We know that we need some natural gas, probably to keep the lights on for a while. The really big problem is that the focus on this industry and the power and wealth of this industry is actually derailing the attempts that we have been making in the past to put a price on carbon, for example, to move ourselves to an energy -- an economy that would actually be sustainable in the future. So, neither of us are saying that there aren't advantages in some situations between putting in a gas plant, say,</p><p end="3070" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="3005">instead of a coal plant, if we really knew what the lifecycle methane emissions were.</p><p end="3121" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="3070">And both of our opponents have admitted that we don't. And we actually --</p><p end="3121" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="3070">But John, let me talk about the methane emissions and what we know about the science there. There has been one study by Cornell University that looks at the methane emissions and has concluded that the methane emissions that are associated with the entire lifecycle of natural gas make it worse than coal. The study has been tremendously critiqued by peers for a number of ways in which that study does not rely on what people know to be the case about emissions. For example, the intergovernmental panel on climate change suggests that you use a hundred-year warming potential, an element that you would use to calculate how much global warming potential there is from a fuel.</p><p end="3186" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="3121">The Cornell folks have used something very, very different than that, which greatly increases the harm that methane would show relative to coal emissions. There are two or three other technical reasons where the peer critiques have said these all exaggerate the emissions. Most of the reasonable science has said and there's a tremendous body of evidence on this, that coal -- when you combust coal at a power plant it will have twice as much emissions of greenhouse gas, including methane, than coal.</p><p end="3186" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="3121">May I respond to that?</p><p end="3186" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="3121">So there's not one study, but there is a variety of studies, and they rely on estimates of emissions that have information that comes principally from the industry. I know of only one study that actually went out into the field and measured the emissions from the gas well, and that study showed that our methane emissions are about four percent of production.</p><p end="3236" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="3186">Now, I agree that we could reduce those if we had better regulations in place, but the industry is out there fighting those regulations. We just had a new EPA rule that was designed to address the emissions from the fracking system, and there was a new rule put in place that would decidedly make it better in terms of methane emissions because they would put the gas pipelines in before they actually let the gas go, and the industry successfully delayed the implementation of this green completion system for another three years.</p><p end="3236" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="3186">But John, I really --</p><p end="3296" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="3236">No. I think --</p><p end="3296" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="3236">No, I think --</p><p end="3296" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="3236">I think the dynamic is actually pretty different. I think the dynamic is that industry began as -- fracking was not started by Exxon or Shell. Fracking was basically a bunch of small companies who really developed the technology as innovators often do and then the big boys came in. The environmentalists correctly said, "This needs to be cleaned up, and it needs to be regulated, and it needs to be looked at more closely." And what has happened is that the objections and the rising concern has basically caused industry,</p><p end="3296" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="3236">especially the big guys, to say, "You know what? We really would like to be on the right side of this, and we are going to try and get there."</p><p end="3356" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="3296">And there have actually been -- you know, Shell, one of the big oil companies, they recycle most of the water that they inject in the well. There are lots of things like that going on. Now, part of the problem is that you can't rely on industry best practices. You have to regulate it. And part of the problem is that the regulation is mostly done by the states, not by the federal government. And so you're sort of dependent on appropriate state regulation. Pennsylvania, when they began, didn't regulate it very well. They've learned a lot. They are regulating it better. It is getting better in Pennsylvania.</p><p end="3356" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="3296">Well, I would like to point out that one of the reasons why we're stuck with state regulation is because the oil and gas companies lobbied their way out of at least a half dozen federal environmental laws and requirements, and so now it's with the states.</p><p end="3422" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="3356">And I'm not particularly impressed by the example of Pennsylvania, which the communities in that state and the environment in that state suffered greatly while the state played regulatory catch-up. And it is still the case that the industry is given a tremendous break. In addition to that, at the state level, across the country, there are not enough regulators to police that. So even if you had half decent regulations, you don't have the staff to put in the field to make sure that those regulations are being complied with.</p><p end="3476" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="3422">Eighty years of fracking is not okay. We need to get off of fossil fuels a lot faster than that.</p><p end="3476" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="3422">Okay, so --</p><p end="3476" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="3422">Okay, so --</p><p end="3476" is_meta="true" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="3422">applause</p><p end="3476" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="3422">-- so you want a situation where all jobs are green jobs, and you don't have a petro-</p><p end="3476" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="3422">chemical industry because they're bad guys, and you have a situation where you want to -- let's assume you could shut down fracking tomorrow, let's assume that, and your vision is that the consequence of that would be that this would cause a rush to renewables, but that's not what would happen. It would cause a rush to coal. The market is buying energy based on its price, and one of the reasons renewables have had so much trouble is because they have a hard time competing with coal.</p><p end="3540" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="3476">Coal is the hardest thing to compete with because it's cheap. So you think that -- what you're trying to avoid, I understand, is another 100-year cycle of fossil fuel, and that's admirable, but it's also unrealistic, and what you have with natural gas is a fuel that is cleaner than coal and maybe could help you get to renewables. And I --</p><p end="3603" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="3540">Well, I agree with Joe that if there is a moratorium on natural gas development,</p><p end="3603" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="3540">unconventional gas around the United States, we're going back to coal.</p><p end="3603" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="3540">It is the answer to the question whether you like it or not. It is the answer to the question. That is what will happen in the United States.</p><p end="3603" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="3540">No, there are policy triggers that are pulling renewable energy development into markets around the country. That is the case.</p><p end="3661" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="3603">Well, I would say first of all Joe was very careful to talk about national -- or energy security and not energy independence, and I don't think that most economists and energy experts think that what we want is independence in the sense that we aren't going to do any trade on energy issues with any other country. What they are talking about is we want to be doing that trade with people who are our friends. And part of what has happened because we've been so focused on gas -- and again I really object to the idea that the alternative is, "Stop it now or 100 years."</p><p end="3728" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="3661">That is not what we're -- that's a straw man -- that's not what we're arguing here. But what we have done is we have ceded a lot of the industry that is developing, for example, photovoltaic solar energy, to China. And so if we are not going to actually speed up our development of the renewable energies here, and instead we're going to be diverted into a 80 years of gas, then we are going to be at a point sometime when we don't have the resources -- the renewable resources, and we're going to be importing them sometime. That's not energy security.</p><p end="3728" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="3661">The reason --</p><p end="3728" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="3661">I don't actually see where the energy security is going to come ultimately if, in fact, the goal of the gas companies, which has been made clear by 15 applications that have been made to the federal government, to export the natural gas to the European and Asian markets, where they can get four to five times as much money for the gas as they can in the domestic market.</p><p end="3775" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="3728">So once we start exporting that gas, how is that helping our national energy security right now?</p><p end="3775" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="3728">The geopolitics of natural gas and oil are pretty compelling when you look around at a lot of different areas of the world. Parts of Western Europe have been held hostage by getting natural gas across pipelines crossing the Ukraine from Russia, and that has created tremendous problems so that the ability for them to be able to get natural gas from friendly areas is a very compelling story. Same is true for China. China actually has a very large shale gas deposit. They are very interested in learning the knowhow in the United States associated with this technology.</p><p end="3839" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="3775">If China is able to use natural gas, they may not build as many Soviet-style nuclear reactors. They may not have challenges with the Middle East oil problem, which is --</p><p end="3839" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="3775">that their own internal demand is driving.</p><p end="3839" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="3775">The thing that -- you mentioned China and you mentioned the solar industry moving to China, and I think it gets to the point that you don't really want to sort of deal with,</p><p end="3839" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="3775">which is cost. Solar is moving to China because it's cheaper, and solar is cheaper -- and the problem renewables have and have had is that they're in this constant struggle to get the cost down to where it's cost-effective to use, and it's cheaper in China. That --</p><p end="3839" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="3775">I was on the board of one of the now bankrupt solar energy companies, Evergreen Solar.</p><p end="3839" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="3775">It was more cost effective to build the next manufacturing facility and then ship the panels back to the United States to meet the solar market because of China's subsidies for the industry.</p><p end="3895" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="3839">So manufacturing is moving to China, but the United States' demand for solar is not going to mean we're not going to get solar back. We will get solar panels back.</p><p end="3895" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="3839">Right, but the question was, energy security. And the concern was being at the mercy of a country that isn't really aligned with our interests. And I think that we would mostly agree that unless things change very much, China is not the one that has completely bought into our value system. And so, we are -- we're not going to get the energysecurity. We may get the cheaper panels, but we are going to be dependent on a hostile country.</p><p end="3961" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="3895">So --</p><p end="3961" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="3895">Full disclosure would be a marvelous thing. I think Joe and I would agree that thatshould be the case. There is a very narrow piece of the fracking fluid that is what we would call &#8220;intellectual property.&#8221;</p><p end="4021" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="3961">In other words, if you could put all the ingredients out there and allow fracking and transparency on that issue, that should be the case.</p><p end="4021" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="3961">And your second point was -- I don't remember. Sorry.</p><p end="4021" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="3961">Oh, there are many, many green completion approaches. Environmentally friendly fluids. So, they are on the marketplace, they can be used.</p><p end="4021" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="3961">We should.</p><p end="4021" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="3961">Well, I mean, there are a lot of things that we could do and we should do. But they're not happening. And this huge resistance to that is happening. And so, you know, there's a great deal of talk about this disclosure system that was created by the Groundwater Protection Council and the industry. And they're not disclosing everything. For the most part, they're disclosing only what is regulated as hazardous under our worker health safety issues.</p><p end="4086" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="4021">There are a couple of states that have now said that you must disclose everything to the Agency. But they are not disclosing everything to the public. And transparency remains a huge issue. You know, the Secretary of Energy Advisory Board Subcommittee on Fracking -- on which Sue Tierney served -- talks about transparency in a much broader way, so that we get the data about our water quality, and get the data about our air quality. None of this is available to the public right now.</p><p end="4086" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="4021">And we are involved litigation -- this very minute -- to try and get the court record froma case involving public health unsealed so that public health professionals in Pennsylvania can actually see the allegations and use them as part of a database to help prevent and treat health problems in Pennsylvania. And we're fighting the industry --</p><p end="4086" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="4021">-- to try to get that transparency.</p><p end="4086" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="4021">I just want to mention the Secretary of Energy Advisory Board was unanimous in saying that there should be better disclosure, much better transparency.</p><p end="4139" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="4086">There must -- much better regulation in all the ways that I just --</p><p end="4139" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="4086">I -- and we need to move forward on that. Stop demonizing natural gas as part of that.</p><p end="4139" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="4086">And the more that people are moving to the sides of the room -- no one is finding any middle ground on this.</p><p end="4198" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="4139">I have one answer for that, which I think is very compelling to me. In the period from 2006 through 2011, when we had dozens and dozens of coal plants being proposed around -- new ones around the country that would lock in large new coal plants for another 50 or 60 years, the changing price of natural gas relative to coal killed those projects. There's a lot of credit given for environmental opposition to those plants and I will give them some credit, but at the end of the day it was natural gas projects that killed those.</p><p end="4263" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="4198">So, John, let me try this. I'm on the Natural Climate Assessment study right now on the impact of a changing climate on the energy sector. You're absolutely right that places will be drier. There will be more pressure on energy supplies. But I want to give you the water use for different fuels. Biofuels, ethanol, 5,000 gallons of water per mmbq of energy. Coal, 23 gallons of water per mmbq of energy. Conventional gas is two and shale gas is two.</p><p end="4319" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="4263">Wind is wonderful, and we'll quintuple it. We'll do 10 times the amount and we still willhave a little bit.</p><p end="4319" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="4263">Yes, that's true.</p><p end="4319" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="4263">Around the country for decades and decades, underground injection has been the water treatment process of choice.</p><p end="4389" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="4319">There are parts of the country where that cannot work because of the geology underground. Pennsylvania's an example where there are very limited areas to be able to do that.</p><p end="4389" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="4319">I haven't really looked globally. The answer to that question is how much fracking do we do? It varies a great deal, you know, on a local basis, and that's where the water consumption takes place. So, for example, in the west we do have major problems with drought. We have forest fires right now. It's projected to get much worse. In the east we have a lot more water than we have in the west, and the water contamination issues are more serious from our perspective than the water quantity, but on the other hand, if you look locally at, you know, head water streams where we have native trout, you can back up your truck into one of those streams and you can drain it dry and that has happened in Pennsylvania.</p><p end="4441" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="4389">So I can't say I really have the answer to your question, but --</p><p end="4441" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="4389">The country --</p><p end="4441" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="4389">The country has historically, in other forms of energy production, oil, for instance, set aside land and said thou shalt not drill here. And, you know, New York is doing the same thing with its watershed and it doesn't seem to me unreasonable to say yes, fracking is a good thing for the country, but it has some risks and therefore there are certain places we won't do it. That seems like a completely reasonable approach.</p><p end="4441" is_meta="true" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="4389">applause</p><p end="4441" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="4389">I would agree. But to me that means that you're agreeing with us that we need to scale back. Because we have --</p><p end="4441" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="4389">That's actually saying you would do it surgically where you know you want to protect things, such as the unfiltered water supply of New York City, which is the way it's supported there.</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="4441">And it's great that we found this common ground, because that isn't what the industry is saying in New York.</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="4441">We are not the industry.</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="4441">Can I just --</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="4441">I just wanted to say that I think that the picking out special places that will be protected from fracking has some serious environmental justice issues around that. So the cities,</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="4441">the people who live in New York City, their drinking water will be protected, the other people in other parts of New York City, their drinking water will not be protected?</p><p end="4502" is_meta="true" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="4441">applause</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="4441">I think that's --</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="4441">Actually --</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="4441">-- I think that&#8217;s a policy question.</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="4441">Most of New York --</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="4441">-- City's water supply, as you know, comes from the aquifers upstate. So we're talking about all of New York City [unintelligible].</p><p end="4502" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="4441">No, she's talking about all of New York State, right? The -- you know, we do want to see every community protected, not just ones that have a huge amount of political power in down state.</p><p end="4560" is_meta="true" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="4502">applause</p><p end="4560" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="4502">And we don't want to be in a situation where the industry is going into the most economically depressed, most politically powerless areas, and that's where people arenot only unable to make a living, but they're now being asked to shoulder disproportionate burdens on their health just to keep food on the table.</p><p end="4560" is_meta="true" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="4502">applause</p><p end="4619" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="4560">I'll say.</p><p end="4619" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="4560">No, I think that the -- I'm not sure actually whether it's 9/11 itself. I think that the using of the national security energy independence argument to support moving forward with natural gas is playing off of the concerns that the nation has had around 9/11, but I think as we talked about, we think that that is not actually very realistic. And so --</p><p end="4619" is_meta="true" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="4560">talking simultaneously</p><p end="4619" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="4560">The country has been trying to -- every president in my memory practically has talkedabout the importance of weaning ourselves from OPEC oil which --</p><p end="4619" is_meta="true" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="4560">applause</p><p end="4678" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="4619">-- and yet here we are finally in a position to actually do something about it because we have our own resource that -- a resource that we really didn't even know we had 20 years ago. And so 9/11 may have spurred the urgency to do this. I mean, my goodness,</p><p end="4678" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="4619">we have invaded countries, and we have -- our entire foreign policy towards the Middle East is consciously or subconsciously about oil. And so the idea that we can change the way we think about other countries, the way we can deal with foreign policy, because we no longer have to sit around and worry about whether they're going to give us our oil or not seems to me like a wonderful thing.</p><p end="4678" is_meta="true" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="4619">applause</p><p end="4678" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="4619">The vast majority of the oil that we use in this country is used for the transportation sector.</p><p end="4737" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="4678">Natural gas is not going to replace that. Natural gas can be used --</p><p end="4737" is_meta="true" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="4678">talking simultaneously</p><p end="4737" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="4678">--the power sector, but not for the transportation sector.</p><p end="4737" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="4678">She's wrong.</p><p end="4737" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="4678">Well, let me just pick up on Kate's --</p><p end="4737" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="4678">Every thoughtful well documented study that looks at how the United States will transform and decarbonize its economy includes shifting more of the transportation sector to electricity and natural gas, putting carbon capture and sequestration on natural gas facilities, but there is a role for fossil in that decarbonized world, and oil isabout this much and it's in the aviation sector.</p><p end="4737" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="4678">You know --</p><p end="4737" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="4678">There is --</p><p end="4737" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="4678">But I was just going to say that Joe recognized Fred Krupp as somebody who he thought was reasonable and authoritative.</p><p end="4802" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="4737">And the Environmental Defense Fund has recently done a study, looking at the climate impacts of shifting from coal to gas, and I will tell you that they do find, they do agree that we would do better, assuming that our methane emissions don't rise to the level of four percent, but they absolutely disagree that if we shift our entire transportation system from oil to gas, that we are going to have net climate benefits over as much as 100 years. So I think we can agree that there might be a small part. There's natural gas buses in New York City. There might be small amounts, but shifting the whole sector over is just a non-starter.</p><p end="4802" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="4737">Let me say two quick things about that. First of all, what EDF has actually said is that if methane leakage can come down and, the idea that we can't have any technology to make things better seems to me pretty unreasonable. Technology does make things better, and the idea that we're always going to be stuck even if in fact, if we are today,</p><p end="4802" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="4737">at four percent methane leakage, is not necessarily the way it's going to play out.</p><p end="4857" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="4802">Secondly, it's already happening. Not only are buses fueled by natural gas in cities, but large trucking companies are beginning to convert to natural gas, and large energy companies are beginning to think about putting natural gas stations on the interstatehighway.</p><p end="4857" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="4802">That's not what we have advocated. So I would say, "No," once again.</p><p end="4922" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="4857">We have been fracking wells not for shale gas for many decades, but the shale gas fracturing, which includes two technologies used together, the horizontal drilling and the hydraulic fracturing, has been used, seriously, only for about a decade, and it's the impacts of the shale gas drilling that are driving all that opposition, because we are not prepared for the volume of the wastewater, and we have nobody out there in the federal government and in many states that are looking cumulatively at all of the impacts.</p><p end="4976" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="4922">It is wastewater. But [unintelligible], I'm sorry, I don't understand the question.</p><p end="4976" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="4922">Where is the wastewater going that's coming out of the well?</p><p end="4976" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="4922">In Ohio.</p><p end="4976" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="4922">There's one commercial well that takes shale gas wastewater in all of Pennsylvania and -</p><p end="4976" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="4922">-</p><p end="4976" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="4922">They -- they're not taking this --</p><p end="4976" is_meta="true" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="4922">talking simultaneously</p><p end="5034" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="4976">Because it's so much fun when you are.</p><p end="5034" is_meta="true" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="4976">laughter</p><p end="5102" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="5034">Okay, but water is going to be one of the central issues of the century that we live in.</p><p end="5102" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="5034">There's no question about that, and there's also no question that we have to work hard to avoid polluting our water, and that's why I advocate that there are areas that we shouldn't frack, and I also think -- this is why I also -- on this side of the table, we're not saying, &#8220;Frack horribly.&#8221; We're not saying, &#8220;Hey, let's put the worst wells in we can and let them leak and damage the environment.&#8221;</p><p end="5102" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="5034">What we're saying is if you do it responsibly, if you do it in a regulated way, you minimize the possibility. You don't eliminate it. You don't eliminate all risk.</p><p end="5153" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="5102">Well, I was worried about that actually, when we were going into this, because it seems to me that we're probably much closer than the organizers of this event might have thought.</p><p end="5153" is_meta="true" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="5102">laughter</p><p end="5153" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="5102">So, we're trying to make for a lively debate --</p><p end="5153" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="5102">I don't -- I don't agree. I think -- I -- I think that --</p><p end="5217" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="5153">The people on this side believe that the issues of the economic benefits, the security benefits, and even the environmental benefits make fracking -- the benefits far outweigh the costs. And that is our view. And I don't think you&#8217;ve said anything that really has changed our minds on that. The issue we're -- do we care about having it done right? Yes, we do. Do we think the benefits are tremendous for America? Yes, we do.</p><p end="5217" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="5153">And --</p><p end="5217" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="5153">We think the benefits would still be there --</p><p end="5217" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="5153">-- if we added 50 cents to the price of natural gas to cover these things? Yes. The benefits are huge.</p><p end="5217" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="5153">But I would say --</p><p end="5217" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="5153">-- that the question here is not whether we can do it right at some point in the future,</p><p end="5217" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="5153">but whether we're doing it right now. Right now --</p><p end="5217" is_meta="true" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="5153">applause</p><p end="5277" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="5217">You don't have to.</p><p end="5277" is_meta="true" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="5217">applause</p><p end="5277" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="5217">On some level, I gave my closing argument about two seconds ago.</p><p end="5348" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="5277">I do feel that it's clear that natural gas has reduced emissions. It is demonstrably better than coal. It is offering us the possibility -- wonderful possibility -- to wean ourselves from Mideast oil. And it's been incredibly economically beneficial for the country to have gas plentiful and cheap. I want to say -- I really want to end on, on this spot. Our opponents -- I want to think about it this way.</p><p end="5348" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="5277">When you're arguing against fracking, you're not arguing for a future of renewables. You may think you are, but you're not. You're arguing for the status quo. You're arguing for a world where coal is still the dominant power generation, where oil is still the fundamental fuel that we use to transport ourselves.</p><p end="5396" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="5348">You know, all the problems that we have today that have been brought about by the way we use energy are still with us. And so, what I would ask the other side to think about is, what does the future look like if we don't have fracking? What does the future look like if we don't have this wonderful source of natural gas, this abundant source of gas that we've been given. I don't think the future looks all that well -- all that good.</p><p end="5396" is_meta="false" speaker="Joe Nocera" start="5348">Thank you very much.</p><p end="5461" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="5396">Having heard what our opponents have said here tonight, you might think we should not be concerned about the impacts of fracking. In their view, any problems we have now will be fixed with golden rules, more regulation, and hopes of improved technology. I think of a few reasons to remain concerned. One, there will always be accidents, spills, mechanical failures, and human error. Two, the gas industry has consistently fought enforceable rules and there is insufficient state and federal staff to ensure compliance with what rules do exist. Three, the idea that the industry as a whole will comply with voluntary best practices -- as I think our opponents have acknowledged -- in the face of falling gas prices, is unlikely.</p><p end="5461" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="5396">Given the continued risk of harm and all of frackings costs weighed against its limited benefits for most, it is beyond dispute that the natural gas boom is doing more harm than good. Simply ask the mothers of children who attend the Red Hawk Elementary School in the Front Range town of Eerie, Colorado.</p><p end="5519" is_meta="false" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="5461">Last fall there were children who stayed home from school with intestinal and breathing problems due to the hundreds of oil drill rigs -- gas drill rigs in the region. Then, the industry insisted on locating gas wells a few hundred yards from the school and a short distance from a school playing field. Parents and children joined together to protest the new well and the town put a temporary moratorium on new permits, but that does not apply to the already permitted elementary school site. So this summer, as drilling takes place, teenage boys will have football practice in the shadow of operating drill rigs. The families of Eerie make it clear, if this uncontrolled experiment, which is the natural gas boom, is allowed to continue, homeowners, farms, schools, and hospitals whose neighbors agree to lease will have no choice. But we have a choice now. The shale gas boom is doing more harm than good and we urge you all to say -- to vote no fracking way.</p><p end="5587" is_meta="true" speaker="Katherine Hudson" start="5519">applause</p><p end="5587" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="5519">I was --</p><p end="5587" is_meta="true" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="5519">applause</p><p end="5587" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="5519">I was also secretary of environmental affairs in Massachusetts, head of the environmental police, head of environmental regulation. I came into this field because I grew up in southern California and couldn't stand the fact that we couldn't see the mountains from where I lived. I went into energy because it seemed to me it was an unbelievably complicated world in which you had these environmental impacts, which were so compelling, and yet you had everybody using cars and a variety of things. In the 30 years that I've been in the energy and environmental fields, I have never seen more polarizing and demonizing discussions as now exist on shale gas, and I saw nuclear plant debates, I saw transmission line plants, everything.</p><p end="5638" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="5587">This is one where the science and the information is -- the gap between what we know and what people say we know is wider than I've seen in any other field. The reason I bring this up is this polarizing part of it makes it impossible for the two sides to find the middle ground, and that's why this issue is we need to stop demonizing this particular fuel, because if we do that we kill it and we kill not only the benefits that Joe just described, but we get back to coal. And that is the reality that we face and I urge you,</p><p end="5638" is_meta="false" speaker="Sue Tierney" start="5587">for that reason, to vote against this proposition.</p><p end="5700" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="5638">I'd like to close with two of my favorite quotes from my opponents. In February of this year, Joe Nocera wrote, "How much methane leaks into the air as a result of fracking?"</p><p end="5700" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="5638">Incredibly, nobody knows. In May of this year, Sue Tierney said on NPR, "Fifty years from now, are we really going to be wondering if we really screwed up because we went on this big gas boom? You really wouldn't want to be F-ing that up," and I agree. We don't know, and we really don't want to be messing that up.</p><p end="5700" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="5638">And that means we need to scale back, slow down, and resist the boom mentality. We have to scale back. We do not have to drill hundreds of thousands of wells just because we can. We don't have to drill near elementary schools, and we can protect our state forests and our parks.</p><p end="5754" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="5700">We need to slow down. We need to take the time to let the science catch up with the practice and the safeguards catch up with the science, and we need the resources to ensure that the rules we have in place are vigorously enforced. There's no rush. The gas has been there for millions of years. It's not going away. Finally, we have to ignore the advertising slogans on both sides, the demonizing goes on on both sides, filling the airways, and stop living in a fantasy world of endless fossil fuel consumption without consequences. We need to restart the conversation about putting a price on carbon,</p><p end="5754" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="5700">and we need to develop a real meaningful energy policy, not &#8220;all of the above.&#8221; That's no policy at all. Does that make sense to you?</p><p end="5754" is_meta="true" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="5700">applause</p><p end="5824" is_meta="false" speaker="Deborah Goldberg" start="5754">Do you want to limit the intensive gas development and the breakneck speed of fracking until we answer the open scientific questions and put policies in place to ensure that we are not messing up? Then you should vote for us, because you recognize, as we do, that until we have those safeguards in place and until we have that information, we have nothing but an uncontrolled experiment and the natural gas boom is doing more harm than good.</p></transcript></debate>