<debate duration="5867" url="https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/obamacare-now-beyond-rescue"><speakers><speaker name="Dr. Scott Gottlieb" position="for"><description>Practicing Physician &amp; Former Deputy Commissioner, FDA</description><bio>Scott Gottlieb, M.D., is a practicing physician and a resident fellow at the American Enterprise Institute. From 2005 to 2007, he served as the FDA... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Megan McArdle" position="for"><description>Writer &amp; Columnist, Bloomberg View</description><bio>Megan McArdle is a Washington, D.C.-based blogger and journalist who writes about economics, business, and public policy. Currently a columnist for... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Jonathan Chait" position="against"><description>Political Commentator &amp; Columnist, New York Magazine</description><bio>Jonathan Chait is a daily columnist at New York magazine, where he contributes lead pieces of political commentary to nymag.com, along with short... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Dr. Douglas Kamerow" position="against"><description>Family Physician &amp; Former Assistant Surgeon General</description><bio>Doug Kamerow, M.D., is a family doctor and specialist in preventive medicine; a chief scientist in health services and policy research at RTI International... Read More</bio></speaker></speakers><results><result against="53" for="16" submitters="live" undecided="31" when="before" /><result against="58" for="33" submitters="live" undecided="9" when="after" /><result for="100" submitters="online" when="before" /><result for="100" submitters="online" when="after" /></results><transcript><p end="506" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="444">Well, the reason that I wrote the book is that I think the key to succeeding, to find out what works. And the best way to find out what works is to fail and find out what doesn't. And I would say we are finding out what doesn't work.</p><p end="568" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="506">Well, the vast majority of them really don't know what the law does. They're not policy wonks, and when Mitt Romney said he was for it, it sounded like a good solid Republican idea. When Barack Obama said he was for it, then it became a Socialist plot to destroy America. And if you don't know what's in the law, that's a pretty sensible way to think about what the law does.</p><p end="568" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="506">Doug Kamerow.</p><p end="1591" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="1532">To hear Doug Kamerow describe it, it's amazing, and I want to sign up. But, you know,</p><p end="1591" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="1532">these debates often tend to sort of devolve into "Who doesn't want people to die?"</p><p end="1652" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="1591">So that's not actually what's on the table here. The issue is not "Are Democrats Socialists? Are Republicans stupid and venal and terrible people?" The issue is, "Is this law, Obamacare, accomplishing what it set out to do? Is it making Americans better off,</p><p end="1652" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="1591">and can it survive in its current form?" As you listen to the administration, it's impossible for Obamacare to fail because every time they don't hit some number that they've been promoting, they just change the terms and redefine its success as whatever's already happened. So, for example, just a few months ago, Kathleen Sebelius, who's the secretary of Health and Human Services, was saying that success in the exchanges was seven million people signed up by March 2014. And then they had a few problems with the exchanges, and then suddenly success wasn't having seven million people signed up, success was having a healthy demographic mix in the pool -- in the insurance pools on the exchanges.</p><p end="1706" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="1652">Then they said that we got -- needed about 40 percent of the people to be young adults,</p><p end="1706" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="1652">which is between the ages of 18 and 35. And then we got some data on the demographics. And so far about 20 to 25 percent of the people who've signed up are young adults, and we got many more old people than we expected, which, for a few reasons that should be fairly obvious, could make insurance cost a lot more than we were hoping, so in the most recent conference call, they said that success would be signing up as many people as possible, which is this beautifully circular reference, right,</p><p end="1706" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="1652">of however many people you've signed up is the number that was possible. It's the self-</p><p end="1706" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="1652">licking ice cream cone of policy programs. But for the rest of us, I don't think it's enough for Obamacare to merely exist. It has to actually do something and do something that we want. So what did we want? What were we promised? We were promised lower costs for government and individuals, and we've heard some of that.</p><p end="1770" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="1706">The administration likes to claim that this has already happened. This hasn't. Health care cost growth has indeed slowed, but health care cost growth started slowing in 2004 when Barack Obama was a junior state senator from Illinois. He had not even beenelected to the U.S. Senate, much less to the presidency. You see a big decline in 2005 to 2007 -- in 2003 to 2005, another between 2007 and 2009, but it actually leveled off in 2010 right when Obamacare comes in and cost growth is kind of bumping along if you look at the OECD figures on that. Kaiser projects -- you remember we heard that the average family was going to save $2,500 a year on their premiums? That didn't happen.</p><p end="1770" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="1706">Kaiser is now projecting that premiums will go up. We wanted people to get healthier as a result of this law, but then we got the Oregon Medicaid Study, which is the gold standard in studies of Medicaid, and it looked at the three things you really want to look at, in preventative care, it looked at hypertension control, cholesterol control, and it showed no statistically significant results.</p><p end="1831" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="1770">More than half of the expansion in Obamacare comes through Medicaid. We wanted people with preexisting conditions, all of these millions of people with preexisting conditions we were told were out there to be able to buy insurance. But when they set up pools in order to cover people with preexisting conditions, they were expecting to get 400,000 people between 2010 and 2013, instead they got a quarter of that number,</p><p end="1831" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="1770">and they only managed to get that by lowering their requirements and doing an aggressive outreach campaign to sign more people up. And we wanted expanded health care coverage, right? But at this point, we can't even say that there are more people insured right now than there were on January 15, 2013. We -- the administration says that there have been four million people added to Medicaid, but half of those people came in states that didn't even do the Medicaid expansion. So definitionally they were already eligible for Medicaid. Of the other states, some of those people were already eligible or may even be renewing their coverage.</p><p end="1888" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="1831">The administration can't even say that these are people who are getting new coverage.</p><p end="1888" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="1831">Some of them may just be going back on to Medicaid just like they were last year. We have 2.2 million people on the exchanges, but five million people had their policies cancelled. No one, I think, predicted that at this point this late in the game you wouldn't even know whether we've increased the insurance numbers and the administration refuses to certify that that is actually happening. Meanwhile, we were not supposed to hurt anyone who had insurance, right? If you liked your plan and you liked your doctor,</p><p end="1888" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="1831">you could keep them. We all know that that has not happened, so five million people have had their plans cancelled, and many people who are buying new plans are seeing that their doctors are not -- the best hospitals and doctors in their area have been kicked off the network in order to keep the premium costs down on the exchanges. So,</p><p end="1888" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="1831">it was also supposed to be really popular, , right? Because we had all of this great stuff,</p><p end="1888" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="1831">this giant Rube Goldberg apparatus layered on top. We didn't take anything away, we only gave.</p><p end="1948" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="1888">And it's kind of time for a Dr. Phil moment, how is that working for you? Nothing is working the way the administration said. So you can say it does not really matter whether it is unpopular, right? The point is not to be popular, and yes, some people have gotten hurt, but you can't make an omelet without breaking eggs, right? It was never reasonable to think that everyone was going to get to keep the doctors and the plans that they wanted. Something had to change and this is a foundation for something better. But this foundation has so many cracks you cannot build a healthy structure on top of it. Just look at everything the administration has had to do in the last few months just to keep the law running. They had to delay the employer mandate and the enforcement, apparently because they couldn&#8217;t even figure out how to make this regulation work. It may never go into effect, which means we'll lose millions of people who were supposed to get coverage expanded through [unintelligible] and the cost will go up to the government. They delayed the Spanish language website, and now apparently part of it is written in Spanglish. Despite the fact that Hispanics are a major constituency for insurance expansion. They delayed the small business exchanges.</p><p end="2005" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="1948">They've allowed people to keep plans that were supposed to be illegal because they weren't real insurance Kathleen Sebelius told us. They've delayed deadlines over and over again. They've done all these things by asserting emergency powers by doing administrative fixes through executive fiat, and yeah fair enough, Obamacare is certainly an emergency, but all of these changes have had the effect of undermining and destabilizing the law that they think is so important. They&#8217;ve had to do these things even though they know it makes the insurance pools less actuarily sound, because they can't face the political backlash. And what happens when Republicans get into office and I assume they, too, think Obamacare is an emergency and could be fixed with some executive orders. Essentially they've made it so that Republicans can undo two-thirds of this law with a stroke of the presidential pen. Obamacare is Now Beyond Rescue. The administration has destroyed their own law in order to save it. Thank you.</p><p end="2071" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="2005">Has anybody here ever renovated a house? I've done it twice. It was hell. Every day I went through brought fresh misery and fresh reason to think why am I doing this, but in the end it worked, and the reason it worked is because we know how to renovate houses, right? So when you hear about the problems that our opponents are describing in the law, they had to delay this, they had to fix this, the Spanish language website didn't work as well as they wanted the first day. You have to ask, are these things that are going to fundamentally destroy the law or are they the kind of problems you have in a renovation? They said, oh, we didn't quite get the counters we want. Oh, this went a little bit over cost. Well, then you have to ask -- to answer that question you have to ask what kind of endeavor is Obamacare?</p><p end="2127" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="2071">Is the Obama administration trying to build a moon base? Is the Obama administration trying to build a thriving liberal democracy in a hostile Muslim country? No. What they're trying to do is build a national health insurance plan. Can you build a national health insurance plan? Well, every advanced economy in the world, except the United States, has built a national health insurance plan. All of those countries insure all their citizens and all of them pay considerably less than we pay here in the United States. So you&#8217;re a priori assumption has to be yeah, this is something you can basically do that the problems you have are not signs that everything is about to collapse onto itself, but the problems you have any time you go through any major project. So, what our opponents have been trying to do for months, and months, and months, actually is paint this picture where every time the contractor comes to you and says, "Oh, it turns out they don't have this color, oh, it turns out the plumber is unavailable on this day," it means the whole thing is going to collapse on its own.</p><p end="2187" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="2127">But actually, nothing like that is happening at all. And there is no evidence that anything like this is happening. The main argument that the opponents have been making the entire time is that there is going to be a death spiral. That's the only plausible mechanism that they have, that the law will fail. A death spiral is a term that I expected them to talk about, because that's what they've been talking about for months. It's something they've barely invoked at all. And I think the reason is it's become clear, in recent days, that there's no chance of a death spiral in the Obamacare law. A death spiral is when you have too many old, sick people who drive up the cost, making the premiums more expensive, leading the healthy people to flee, driving up costs more.That is theoretically possible, but is not something that can possibly happen in this law.</p><p end="2187" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="2127">In fact, if you want to say, "Is the law succeeding?" you don't have to ask the administration. You could ask the insurers, right? Because the insurers have recently been saying they're very happy with the mix of people -- the mix of people you have in the exchanges is sound. It's sustainable. They don't need -- they don't need it to change.</p><p end="2250" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="2187">They've got a mix of people that's healthy enough to keep the exchanges going forward.</p><p end="2250" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="2187">What's more, even if you had more old people going into the exchanges than they expect, you had -- the Kaiser Health Foundation ran the numbers and said, "What's the worst-case scenario?" We don't get any increase in young people at all. And they said it would be about a 2.4 percent increase in premiums 2.4 percent increase in health insurance premiums. If any of you have ever had health insurance and you get a 2.4 percent increase over your bill last year, you'd say, "Thank God it's only a 2.4 percent increase," right? That's a rounding error. No one notices 2.4 percent. That couldn't possibly set off a death spiral. So there's really no plausible mechanism that the law could fail. So I think what they're giving you -- instead of what used to be the plausible mechanism for which the -- this can fail, they're giving you a mix of wishes and hopes and completely debunked facts. They said, "Cost growth leveled after 2010.&#8221; No. Cost growth in 2012 was lower than at any year in 50 years. And in fact -- this is important because when the law was passed, cost growth was the main thing they talked about.</p><p end="2305" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="2250">Obamacare was supposed to control costs. And they said, "No, no, it's going to make costs explode with all this bureaucracy regulation. They're going to go out of control.&#8221;</p><p end="2305" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="2250">What happened is that cost growth came in way lower than the most optimistic estimates believed it would be before the law was signed. And so now, they're reduced -- instead of saying, "This disaster of cost growth is going to happen," they're going to say, "This incredible miracle of low cost growth is simply a coincidence.&#8221; So, all they're saying is essentially that this wonderful thing that's happened has nothing to do with the gigantic change in healthcare or that happened just before costs started going to the lowest level in 50 years. And you can't prove that it's not a coincidence. But you have to -- see, this is indicative of the mentality we're dealing with, where it simply moves from one possible disastrous scenario to another possible disastrous scenario.</p><p end="2305" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="2250">So you have to wonder, "Why are they simple moving from one disaster scenario to another disaster scenario?"</p><p end="2370" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="2305">Actually, I wanted to debunk a couple points they made, because a lot of this is just --</p><p end="2370" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="2305">we've heard from the other side -- are not true. I can't give you links and charts to debunk them, but let me say that it's not the case that 5 million policies have been canceled. That's a number that was floating about that you can't verify. It's almost certainly not true. Many journalists have tried to figure out exactly how many policies have been canceled. And they don't have good enough records to know, but they know it's not 5 million. And they suspect -- the administration suspects it's closer to one-tenth of that figure. They can't actually prove that either, but for various reasons, you don't have a good enough count. This -- that's almost certainly nowhere close to 5 million.</p><p end="2370" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="2305">And that's a big number that's -- they're citing because they're saying, that -- those are the losers. But it's really nowhere close to that. Yet they say -- Megan said we can't --</p><p end="2370" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="2305">we can't say for sure how many -- how -- that there are more insured now than there were before. We can't say for sure, because again, this number can't exactly be counted. We don't know that 400,000 -- it was 500,000. But we know it's not anywhere close to 5 million. And it's a mortal certainty that far more people have health insurance now than would have had in absence of the law.</p><p end="2427" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="2370">So why are we having this kind of lurch, from one argument, abandoning these arguments when they disappear, and simply coming up with new ones? The truth is,</p><p end="2427" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="2370">they disagree with the goals of the law. And I think you could hear that in their remarks.</p><p end="2427" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="2370">They say, "There's less choice.&#8221; And it's true. The government says insurers have to provide certain benefits right. They have to provide pregnancy coverage. That's -- and maternity care. Those are the most controversial things that are mostly cited, because they want people who are male or old to not have to pay for those things. And they want people who are young and female and might have to bear children to pay those costs themselves, because that's an ideological difference between the two sides. And that's fine for them to have an ideological difference between the two sides. But we're not here to debate whether this law is a good idea. We're here to debate whether the law is actually working, and the truth is the only reason they're desperately trying to claim the law is not working is because they oppose national health insurance.</p><p end="2731" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="2672">Oh, well, I would say that I certainly agree with Jonathan Chait, that this is going much,</p><p end="2731" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="2672">much, much worse than I thought, and there are all sorts of problems that I didn't anticipate. So to that extent, it's true.</p><p end="2784" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="2731">I'm picking on stuff that I did not predict because my worries at the time of passage were about things like the federal budget deficit and would the cost controls hold. Will this tamp down innovation, which is, if you think about the millions of unborn or still living but not yet sick people who can be cured by innovations that haven't happened yet, I was worried about that. But we haven't gotten to the point where I can worry about those sorts of things. We've gotten to the point where I'm now worried that this is going to implode and destroy the market for insurance.</p><p end="2784" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="2731">I think that Jonathan is way more optimistic than I, that a death spiral isn&#8217;t possible. For one thing, you know, a lot of the -- the thing that everyone has been leaning very hard on -- I haven't heard the insurers saying that they are real pleased with the mix.</p><p end="2784" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="2731">Humana and other people have said it's more adverse than they expected.</p><p end="2853" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="2784">No, at the JPMorgan Conference a series of insurers were interviewed, and they all said that they were generally expecting getting what they expected.</p><p end="2853" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="2784">But that -- neither -- leaving that point aside --</p><p end="2853" is_meta="true" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="2784">laughter</p><p end="2853" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="2784">There were a series of insurers quoted at the JPMorgan Conference on January 15.</p><p end="2853" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="2784">There were also a series of insurers quoted, saying that they've had adverse --</p><p end="2853" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="2784">That they're announcing earnings adjustments because of their adverse selection. But that's not really even -- the issue is that, you know, a lot of the mechanisms they're depending on are these things called these risk corridors, which are temporary kind of reinsurance facilities to help insurers transition, and also the fact that these subsidies basically grow with the cost of the policy so that if we do start seeing adverse selection,</p><p end="2853" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="2784">if we do see young people not in the pools, healthy people not in the pools and so costs go up, well, then the subsidies will rise and these risk corridors will kick in. But those things end in 2018. Subsidy --</p><p end="2909" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="2853">Right, but what we're seeing right now is that they're not even going to need that kind of adjustment in the first place because they're saying the pool of people is young enough that it's meeting their expectations, that they don't need to raise premiums,</p><p end="2909" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="2853">Right, we don't know.</p><p end="2909" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="2853">The government will not --</p><p end="2909" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="2853">You're right, you said -- that's correct.</p><p end="2909" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="2853">-- the administration will not say --</p><p end="2909" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="2853">Right, we don't know exactly --</p><p end="2909" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="2853">-- that we have more people covered.</p><p end="2909" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="2853">-- right -- we don't know the number of people who had their plans cancelled. It's way less than five million. We don't know, so we can't say exactly how many [inaudible].</p><p end="2909" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="2853">But why is January 1, the first date the law started, the best mark? The law's supposed to --</p><p end="2969" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="2909">Well --</p><p end="3085" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="3029">The reason I wrote that you're against national health care is because in 2009 you wrote a column called "Why I Oppose National Health Care."</p><p end="3085" is_meta="true" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="3029">laughter</p><p end="3085" is_meta="true" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="3029">applause</p><p end="3085" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="3029">You've also predicted -- a few months ago you predicted the exchanges might not even open on January 1, that the administration would have to stop its whole law. So if you're talking about moving the goal post your definition of failure just keeps getting smaller and smaller.</p><p end="3085" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="3029">Well, I'm just saying that in 2010, 2011, and 2012, and 2013, I have written that I support the sort of catastrophic reinsurance program. I've been proposing it for a fairly long time.</p><p end="3145" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="3085">You're using the word death spiral in a way that no one in health care and economics ever uses it.</p><p end="3330" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="3269">That's all you keep saying -- obligate people to Medicaid, but I don't think the word means what you think it means. No one is obligated to go on Medicaid. People are offered to go on Medicaid and they very rationally choose to go on Medicaid.</p><p end="3330" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="3269">Right. Now, our opponents have made two different claims about Medicaid. Scott&#8217;s made a terrible argument about the quality of Medicaid and Megan made one that is merely bad.[laughter]</p><p end="3330" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="3269">Scott's argument, he's obliquely citing studies that have taken two populations, one of which is on Medicaid and one which is not on Medicaid and compared their health.</p><p end="3330" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="3269">Now, if you're on Medicaid you're in a terrible place. Something has gone bad in your life. You're very poor. You're very sick. Bad things are happening to you. So, a lot of studies are comparing two completely different kinds of populations and finding the people on Medicaid are worse off.</p><p end="3330" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="3269">Those are the studies people don't take seriously.</p><p end="3330" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="3269">Then the study that Megan cited is still not a very good use of data. It's not a good use of data for two reasons -- if I may --</p><p end="3386" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="3330">Number one --</p><p end="3386" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="3330">So, there are a series of studies on the effectiveness of Medicaid. Many of these studies -- most of them show what you would intuitively think. Going on Medicaid and being able to see doctors, even if you don't get a lot of choice, even if a lot of doctors don't want to take the low prices, is better than not having health insurance and going togood -- going to the doctor at all. Because as my partner explained in fairly strong detail, not having health insurance is dangerous. It's terrible. Nobody wants to have it.</p><p end="3386" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="3330">And people are right not to want it --</p><p end="3386" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="3330">Well, it shows actually --</p><p end="3386" is_meta="true" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="3330">applause</p><p end="3386" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="3330">Here's something interesting -- is a lot of these studies have looked at Medicaid versus the uninsured. And the uninsured do better. Having no insurance is better in these studies than having Medicaid, even when you control for [unintelligible] --</p><p end="3386" is_meta="true" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="3330">laughter</p><p end="3386" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="3330">Now, that said, do I think that having Medicaid is actually worse than being uninsured?</p><p end="3386" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="3330">No, I don't.</p><p end="3446" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="3386">It's very hard to actually measure lots of things. But the -- you would want to know about the impulse control, or social support and so forth. But I think that most people agree that Medicaid is bad coverage. It's not good coverage. You wouldn't want to go on it. And there are people who had cheap policies canceled -- got cancellation notices and found that when they went to the exchanges, they were were into Medicaid.</p><p end="3446" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="3386">That's [inaudible] --</p><p end="3446" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="3386">So I'm not --</p><p end="3506" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="3446">Well, no, I --</p><p end="3567" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="3506">I think that what they hoped to achieve was a program that even if it wasn't perfect,</p><p end="3567" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="3506">would be politically self-sustaining in that it would be impossible to repeal, because some, they think, would love it. And I think that's what a key issue is with Medicaid --</p><p end="3567" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="3506">-- and with these narrow networks, is people aren't going to love these and aren't going to fight to keep them.</p><p end="3630" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="3567">You've got to remember, the proposition here is "beyond repair.&#8221; So they're not --</p><p end="3630" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="3567">that's not a claim about beyond repair. That's a claim about something that might happen in the future that they can plausibly say will be --</p><p end="3630" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="3567">Right.</p><p end="3630" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="3567">So --</p><p end="3630" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="3567">Right.</p><p end="3630" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="3567">So the initial projections were -- CBO said they guess about 7 million people would be in the exchanges by the end of the open enrollment period in March. Now, the website was broken for the first few months. That wasn't just people could enroll. That means the whole outreach campaign that the administration, its outside allies, and in the insurers had planned to direct people to this website -- which was broken -- had to beput off. So basically, we&#8217;ve lost two-thirds of the time to enroll people in the exchanges.</p><p end="3630" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="3567">It was trying to enroll people in the exchanges that we've had, October, November,</p><p end="3630" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="3567">December. Only December wasn't working. Yet -- so in one third of the time they've had available, they did a whole two thirds of the target they were supposed to have in the exchanges. They thought by the end of December they would have three million.</p><p end="3630" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="3567">Instead, they have two million. So that seems to be --</p><p end="3929" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="3866">Do I have the intentions of protecting families from financial damage for medical bills?</p><p end="3929" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="3866">Absolutely. Do I think that the execution was good? I think that's a hard argument to make. But, you know, I also think that there are better structures and attempts to like preserve everything that any person in the United States had, which we already know wasn't possible manage to do it, while simultaneously layering a bunch of new stuff on top of that, was just an inherently flawed design, I don't think that I understood that it would be executed so badly, but I --</p><p end="3988" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="3929">Yes.</p><p end="3988" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="3929">I think of it as sort of like the autobahn, which is great, but I wouldn't necessarily say that you could just build that in the United States now. We already have a highway system.</p><p end="4051" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="3988">And so looking at what another country has done with a really long history is helpful in the sense that you can see elements that work, but that doesn't mean that we can have Germany's health care system. We have a different set of doctors and nurses and patients and all sorts of things, and that's why I like the idea of a kind of very American -</p><p end="4051" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="3988">- we're going to have the government insure your financial losses after a certain point,</p><p end="4051" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="3988">but we're going to leave you out there as a market driven consumer, making choices of whatever health care you want when you get sick.</p><p end="4111" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="4051">I -- here's one way to tie this together. For years and years, when you asked conservatives about national health reform, they would say some horror story, right?</p><p end="4111" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="4051">They would say some man in Canada walked 100 miles in snow and lost his feet because of the Socialist horrors of Canada to come to the freedom of America, and everyone in Britain has lost their teeth because of the NIH --</p><p end="4174" is_meta="true" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="4111">laughter</p><p end="4174" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="4111">-- and all these, you know, weird kind of mix of anecdotes and half-truths. Those [unintelligible] --</p><p end="4174" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="4111">But that's actually true, Jonathan.</p><p end="4174" is_meta="true" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="4111">laughter</p><p end="4174" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="4111">-- that was what was like floating around out there. And I think what's happened here is that all these horror stories simply migrated to the United States and now describe Obamacare. They've kind of forgotten all about the horrors of socialized medicine, and the way that they understood national health insurance in the other countries is now the way they understand national health insurance in the United States. It's a very partial anecdotal kind of slightly hysterical way.</p><p end="4174" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="4111">John Donvan:I'm so tempted to ask who in the audience is British and would like to smile at us right now.</p><p end="4174" is_meta="true" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="4111">laughter</p><p end="4174" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="4111">Our motion is, "Obamacare is now beyond rescue," and I'm saying that because I've repeatedly said it's beyond repair. The motion language is beyond rescue. Here comes a question right now. And if you rise, they'll find you a mic. Thanks.</p><p end="4234" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="4174">Well --</p><p end="4234" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="4174">-- you know, I think it's kind of self evident that this target date-- that we've heard from the other side of -- are things better by January 1 is oddly irrelevant, the first day that the law is actually in operation. The point is to make a change over a series of years.</p><p end="4234" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="4174">Now, the outreach campaign to the public is something that by definition just takes months and months and months and years and years and years to build up. And no one envisioned that the law would reach its coverage target even under the best circumstances the first year. And again, the website responded. So, in 2013 they lost two-thirds of the available time. So naturally you're just going to move back the target for the ramp up year, you're going to hit it more slowly, but nothing about that process changes the law's ability to fundamentally reach its goals in the coarse of time.</p><p end="4408" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="4351">No, the law set out to do things to reform the cost structure of benefits to control costs and by all evidence it's succeeding beyond the best expectations and --</p><p end="4408" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="4351">Even the government's actuaries say, you know, CMS economists are saying that it was the recession, not Obamacare. But look, you know, is everything in Obamacare going to go away? No. Obamacare involves, for example, changes to the student loan program.</p><p end="4408" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="4351">Are those going to be rolled back if the insurance markets don't work out? No. The question is, are the major super structures going to stay in place, and especially the things that you needed to do of a piece. You know, our -- we're going to go back to --</p><p end="4408" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="4351">we're going to take kids under 26 off their parents insurance? I doubt it. But that doesn't, you know --</p><p end="4408" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="4351">That's entirely fringe.</p><p end="4475" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="4408">No. I mean, the law intended to do a lot of things. It intended to cover people in a lot of ways. Covering people under 26. That was the way they covered people under 26.</p><p end="4475" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="4408">But controlling costs -- what they decided to do was not have one big blunt force wave to hold down medical inflation they let thousand flowers bloom and change the infrastructure in a lot of ways and there's a lot of good evidence --</p><p end="4475" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="4408">It's a big law with a lot -- with two major goals accomplished in a bunch of different ways.</p><p end="4526" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="4475">So we're -- I think where we lack the metrics is how many people had their plans with their private insurance plans cancelled? That's what we don't know. And that's the kind of negative sum in their ledger, that they're trying to say the law failed. We don't really know that no one has the -- but we do know who's signing up. We've got very good metrics on that.</p><p end="4588" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="4526">So, do we know how many people are going in the exchanges, how many people are</p><p end="4588" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="4526">going into Medicaid, what type of healthcare costs? All those things can be measured and are being measured. And they're all very positive.</p><p end="4588" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="4526">Well, it's --</p><p end="4708" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="4646">I would like to, actually. There's a huge amount of data. It contradicts what the others are trying to say. Let me cite one. Two Urban Institute researchers published a study finding that the number of adults reporting that they skipped care because of high costs in Massachusetts fell 17 percent to 11 percent for the first two years of the law. So Ithink of all the things it's trying to do, is -- quit -- stop people who can't get healthcare because they can't afford it. That was the main goal of the law and it succeeded</p><p end="4770" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="4708">All right. There were a lot of cost reforms in the way that hospitals were compensated,</p><p end="4770" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="4708">that happened before 2012, right? So, instead of paying people based on more care --</p><p end="4770" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="4708">the more medicine you perform, the more money you get -- it changed the model where people get paid based on providing quality of care and actually in measurable ways of improving patients health. So, one way is it penalized hospitals that have high rates of infections. Because previously, hospitals -- if your patients get an infection,</p><p end="4770" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="4708">that's a bonus for you. They have to go back in the hospital and get treated again. And you make more money. So, instead the law changed and said, "No, we're going to penalize you if you have a high rate of infections.&#8221; And the rate of infection has actually fallen. There's a wide series of reforms like this changed the cost structure of American medicine. And I think a lot of researchers have looked at this and concluded they're actually working on changing the cost model and making people try to provide quality instead of just more and more care for more and more money.</p><p end="4829" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="4770">-- there's a lot of changes in the law that were supposed to control costsThere are some that take effect immediately, like hospital remission. But that was only in Medicare.</p><p end="4829" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="4770">And the cost reductions have been occurring across the board, not just in Medicare, a recent paper at Brookings suggests it's probably due to a combination of the recession and technological slowdown, we haven't had a lot of innovation for whatever reason in the last few years. Going forward, there are things like accountable care organizations that think they're not looking as great as they thought that they were. Other issues with electronic medical records, also not looking as great as we had hoped. And some Medicare pilot programs. And eventually, the comparative effectiveness for [unintelligible] -- slow Medicare costs and it doesn't come down on its own. But all --</p><p end="4829" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="4770">most of that stuff hasn't really -- either hasn't finished being implemented or isn't expected to return dividends or is going to be started being implemented this year.</p><p end="4948" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="4890">You know, I think that, that is a political issue. We already on net transfer a lot to older</p><p end="4948" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="4890">people and a lot of the set up here is transferring more and more to older people and to sicker people, which is a kind of a separate issue.</p><p end="5005" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="4948">It's actually kind of interesting how few people -- how little the transfers are until you get to be about 50. And I know we're all hoping to make it there, but is that politically sustainable when that's the minority of the voting base and when they're already getting most of the transfers and growing every day? And when the budget is under strain, when we have to find ways to cut, I do question that. I question whether in 20 years we're still going to be gung ho about giving money to people over the age of 50 instead of people over the age of 65.</p><p end="5365" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="5304">Let me let you in on a secret. When we set up this debate back in the fall, it was a while ago, it looked like Obamacare might really collapse. The website was broken. We didn't know when it would be fixed. We didn't know if it would be fixed. Some people thought it would never be fixed. It looks like it's possible the law would actually not come into effect. But now it has come into effect. Now we're actually living the experience of this law. So the position that was an outlandish and somewhat exaggerated fear three months ago, is now kind of silly.</p><p end="5432" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="5365">And I think if you look back into the history of libertarian anti-statism in America,</p><p end="5432" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="5365">there's a long tradition of these kinds of fear mongering predictions, senators who were opposed to child labor laws a few years ago saying that children would refuse to do chores in their household, Ronald Reagan saying, "If we pass Medicare the government will tell doctors they can't live here, they can't live there, and one day we'll look back at a day when we had freedom in America and wonder what happened to it." So this is a constant recurring pattern, Social Security, all kinds of civil rights laws, labor laws. The American far right lives in terror of government, and it's ideologically understandable that they would oppose these laws, but they translate this ideological terror into a series of verifiable predictions about what will happen if these laws come into effect. And one day we're going to look back at the kinds of predictions they've been making about Obamacare, and those will go in the time capsule, and they'll look just as silly as the predictions that were made by all these other reforms, which is not to say that it works perfectly. It's not to say those other things that work perfectly. Believe me, child laborwas a big part of the economy a hundred years ago and when we banned it it actually imposed a lot of disruption and pain on people.</p><p end="5488" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="5432">Right now it seems obvious and back then it was really hard. Families lost an income.</p><p end="5488" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="5432">But these changes did fundamentally work. The market responded. People responded</p><p end="5488" is_meta="false" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="5432">and I think when we look back time we'll see that the people who were saying the law must fail were really just people who didn't agree with its goals in the first place.</p><p end="5488" is_meta="true" speaker="Jonathan Chait" start="5432">applause</p><p end="5488" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="5432">So, I don't want to go into an anecdote; we can talk about people who just got coverage and there are people who have and couldn&#8217;t get it before and I&#8217;m happy for them, or I could talk about the people who have written me and said now I can't afford coverage and I had it before what do I do, and I don't have anything to tell them. That's not really the assessment of the law. They're just individual stories. It doesn&#8217;t tell us how it&#8217;s going.</p><p end="5546" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="5488">And the question isn't whether the status quo was bad, or anyone on this stage is a bad person. I think we all didn&#8217;t want the status quo. We're all good people. We all want to help the other Americans to be as healthy as possible. The question is whether the law is undermining its own goals. And to think about going forward, we, you know, Mr.</p><p end="5546" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="5488">Chait says it&#8217;s now here. In fact, we still have a long way to go with a bunch of unpopular stuff that is going to happen. Small businesses are starting to get a wave of cancellations that are going to come through the year, and they're being asked for a lot more money. A lot of that is due to Obamacare. The Cadillac tax, 40 percent surcharge on generous health insurance is especially hard on companies with old sick people, but a lot of benefits managers are saying basically everyone is going to have to go to light plans and scale down rather than get hit by that tax. We&#8217;ve got comparative effectiveness research which is going to start determining what sorts of things Medicare will reimburse at what rates.</p><p end="5607" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="5546">We've got the individual mandate. People aren't going to pay it this year. They pay it in 2015. As each of those things comes due, there will be an outcry from people who are affected. And the administration has so far shown no willingness to stand up. Yes, you may have to break an omelet to make eggs, but the administration is not going to tell the eggs that, and the Republicans certainly aren't going to make the eggs crack itself.</p><p end="5607" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="5546">So, if we are not willing to impose the pain, and so far we haven't, this law cannot survive. It is set up as a giant piece of interlocking machinery. You can't just rip the carburetor out and hope that it&#8217;s still working. That is why Obamacare is beyond rescue,</p><p end="5607" is_meta="false" speaker="Megan McArdle" start="5546">because we are not willing to face the hard choices the law made necessary.</p></transcript></debate>