<debate duration="6219" url="https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/obesity-governments-business"><speakers><speaker name="Dr. Pamela Peeke" position="for"><description>WebMD Chief Lifestyle Expert</description><bio>Dr. Pamela Peeke is a nationally renowned physician, scientist and expert in the fields of nutrition, metabolism, stress and fitness. Named one of... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Dr. David Satcher" position="for"><description>Former Surgeon General of the United States</description><bio>Dr. David Satcher served as the 16th Surgeon General of the United States and published America&#146;s first &#147;Call To Action To Prevent and Decrease... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="John Stossel" position="against"><description>FOX Business News Anchor &amp; Commentator</description><bio>The host of "Stossel", a weekly program airing Thursdays at 10 PM EST and midnight on Fox Business Network, John Stossel has received 19 Emmy Awards... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Paul Campos" position="against"><description>Author, The Obesity Myth &amp; Law Professor, University of Colorado</description><bio>Paul Campos is a law professor, author and journalist currently on the faculty of the University of Colorado in Boulder. He is the author of The Obesity... Read More</bio></speaker></speakers><results><result against="19" for="55" submitters="live" undecided="26" when="before" /><result against="35" for="55" submitters="live" undecided="10" when="after" /><result against="14" for="56" submitters="online" undecided="28" when="before" /><result against="14" for="84" submitters="online" when="after" /></results><transcript><p end="360" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="299">Well, it was sort of a surprise when we saw what had happened over a 20-year period and the direction that we were going in terms of increasing obesity. So we didn't know how long it would take to begin to turn what we call the epidemic around.</p><p end="360" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="299">I became a Pew Foundation scholar in nutrition and metabolism because in medical school, I learned nothing. I didn't have a minute of nutrition taught to me. Yet here I was in the critical care unit where people -- where people's lives were at stake. I had to keep them alive with food. And I was the most clueless person of all. I went back to school.</p><p end="420" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="360">Yeah, I was a -- sounds improbable, but I was a -- I was doing a conference on the Clinton impeachment when it was taking place, and a speaker dropped out on me, and I had to fill in the gap in the program. And so I was looking at the media coverage of the Clinton impeachment to see if there was something interesting to say about it.</p><p end="487" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="420">And I did a lexis search, and I found that there were more than 100 news stories that used the phrase "Monica Lewinsky" and the word "zaftig." And I was very struck by that, because, of course, as I have discovered in talking about this over the years, the vast majority of Americans don't know what zaftig means. This audience probably has a relatively high percentage of people who know what that word means.</p><p end="487" is_meta="true" speaker="Paul Campos" start="420">laughter</p><p end="487" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="420">But most Americans don't. And yet Monica Lewinsky was being identified as both fat and Jewish, which I thought was kind of interesting by the use of that word. And so I started looking at the weight that -- the role that weight obsessionalism played in the Clinton impeachment. And here we are today.</p><p end="487" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="420">A what? Yes, yes.</p><p end="487" is_meta="true" speaker="John Stossel" start="420">laughter</p><p end="487" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="420">Omna.</p><p end="487" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="420">John Donvan:That might have been too personal. Relevant to this debate, John, you have likened those who would want to regulate the diet of Americans to the prohibitionists of the early 20th century, the moral being what?</p><p end="543" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="487">That they mean well, but that they do more harm than good.</p><p end="543" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="487">And it reminds me of what Mencken said, that they have the haunting fear that someone somewhere may be happy.</p><p end="543" is_meta="true" speaker="John Stossel" start="487">laughter</p><p end="661" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="599">Thank you. Well, we contend that obesity is definitely the government's business. My favorite story I think about policymakers is a story about a man who was traveling across the country in a hot air balloon, and at a certain point he realized that he was lost, he had no idea where he was, so he decided that he would lower the balloons and see if he could see some recognizable landmarks. So he lowered the balloon, couldn't see anything that he recognized, no Golden Gate bridge, no Washington Monument, so he had no idea where he was. So he kept lowering the balloon, and when he got to about 30 feet above ground he saw a man working in the field. So he yelled out, "Where am I?" and the man stopped digging in the field, and he said, "Well, you're in a hot air balloon about 30 feet above ground."</p><p end="661" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="599">laughter</p><p end="727" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="661">Well, the man in the balloon said, "You sound like a scientist. Do you work in science?"</p><p end="727" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="661">And the man on the ground said, "My goodness, I am a scientist. But how in the world did you know that?" Said, "Well, I knew that because what you told me is technically correct but it is of absolutely no use to me right now."</p><p end="727" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="661">laughter</p><p end="727" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="661">Well, not to be outdone, the man on the ground said, "Well, you sound like one of those policymakers from Washington or somewhere." And the man in the balloon said, "I am.</p><p end="727" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="661">I'm an outstanding policymaker. I'm a leader. But how did you know that?" And the man on the ground said, "I knew that because you're in the same position you were when we met, you don't know where you are, you don't know where you're going, and now you're blaming me."</p><p end="727" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="661">laughter</p><p end="727" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="661">Well, let me say that I spent nine years in government, five as director of the CDC, and as you've heard, four as surgeon general and assistant secretary for health, and I have to tell you, I would trade nothing for those nine years.</p><p end="780" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="727">They were rich years. The people with whom I worked were special. So I am very excited about the role of government in dealing with a problem like obesity. Let me just say a few of the things I was involved in. In 1996, while director of CDC, we released a very interesting report on physical activity. It was actually released as a surgeon general's report, and basically what we showed in that report on physical activity was that there was a dramatic decline in physical activity among the American people,</p><p end="780" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="727">including schools no longer requiring physical education, K through 12. And so we expressed a lot of concerns about the sedentary lifestyles of American people and the implications of that.</p><p end="847" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="780">In 1999, I represented the United States at a world conference on health promotion and disease prevention. And at that conference for the first time I released the surgeon general's Prescription [to the American People], which I'm sure many of you are familiar with, but among the things on that prescription was the recommendation for regular physical activity, at least 30 minutes a day, at least five days a week, but also a recommendation that the American people consume at least five servings of fruits and vegetables per day. There were other things on the prescription, even one having to do with mental health and the need to have some planned strategy for dealing with stress.</p><p end="847" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="780">We didn't really understand at that time the relationship between things like physical activity and depression, the fact that physical activity is a major intervention for reducing depression. Then in 2001, as surgeon general and assistant secretary for health, I released the surgeon general's Call to Action to Prevent and Reduce Overweight and Obesity.</p><p end="909" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="847">That report, among other things, pointed out that between 1980 and the year 2000 there had been a tripling of overweight and obesity among children in this country and a doubling among adults. So we did sound the alarm, and even though I was former director of the CDC and we are very selective at what we call "epidemics," usually reserved for infectious diseases, we declared that overweight and obesity was an epidemic in this country. We didn't realize at that time that the same thing was beginning to happen all over the world. In that report of the surgeon general on overweight and obesity, we especially expressed concern about the changes in the maps throughout the country, where you could actually map the increase in overweight and obesity in various states, whereas in 1990, 15 percent was almost the high.</p><p end="961" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="909">By the year 2001, it was 25 to 30 percent of the American people who were obese.</p><p end="961" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="909">What we know about overweight and obesity from a population perspective is very important, I think, to this debate because what we know is that it has increaseddramatically, but also that it is clearly associated with an increase in chronic diseases,</p><p end="961" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="909">especially what we call Type II diabetes, or increases in what we call BMI, the way we measure body fat, directly related to an increase in Type II diabetes. And, as you know,</p><p end="961" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="909">Type II diabetes increases the risk for cardiovascular disease and even renal disease.</p><p end="1020" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="961">So we were concerned about what was happening in this country. We were concerned about the implication of these rising rates of overweight and obesity. We were also concerned about disparities. We have declared the goal of eliminating disparities in health in this country, especially among different racial and ethnic groups. And what we observed, of course, was that this epidemic was disproportionately impacting African Americans and American Indians. So, American Indians also have the highest rate of Type II diabetes. And African Americans have the highest mortality rates from Type II diabetes. So we were very concerned about the impact that this was having on eliminating disparities in health. We were also concerned about what was happening in children. I think this was really critical. What we found was that children, by increasing overweight and obesity, were now getting what we previously had called adult-onset diabetes.</p><p end="1079" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="1020">We were seeing it in children. We were seeing hypertension in children. Pediatricians were expressing great concerns.</p><p end="1079" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="1020">Thank you.</p><p end="1079" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="1020">applause</p><p end="1571" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1507">Obesity is the government's business. You hear from the opposing side that we're looking at a nanny state or food policing. Au contraire, that's not what we're looking for at all. Voluntary? We give you voluntary. That's what we're looking for. I wear many hats. I'm a physician first, and I hail from the front trenches, face to face with my patients and as chief lifestyle expert for WebMD's 90 million members, click to click with my cyber folks. This is where I practice high-tech touch. I set up a discussion group asking, is obesity the government's business? It lit up like Kyoto at nighttime. It was fabulous. The bottom line was, yes, obesity is the government's business for leadership,</p><p end="1571" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1507">education, protection, options, opportunities, infrastructure.</p><p end="1627" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1571">No sidewalk, no walk. No park, no play. No bike path, lots of accidents. Bottom line,</p><p end="1627" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1571">what they said was, "No blame, no shame. No tax, no bans." They drew a line in the sand. And Dr. Satcher and I agree with that. Obesity is the government's business.</p><p end="1627" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1571">I'm going to flip now to my public health hat. Government cannot solve the obesity problem alone. A problem as large as obesity, pun fully intended, requires all sectors of society to bring our thinking to the table. So I argue for government private sector partnerships. Shouldn't be just the government at all. When we initiate a voluntary campaign or an effort, we want to be able to offer people options and opportunities because if there is no choice, there can be no moderation.</p><p end="1681" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1627">We're in New York City. I love this place. And although you just heard that some of what you're doing isn't working so well, I say, forget all that. You have programs here,</p><p end="1681" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1627">for instance, Mayor Bloomberg has joined with 500 other mayors with the "let's move cities and town" campaign to be able to work, drill down into the neighborhoods. What we can do to be able to improve physical activity as well as nutrition. In addition, the "fresh" program, food retailed expansion to support health programs. Say that three times. The food retail expansion to support health program has set up 14 supermarkets in food deserts. This was a private-public collaboration, a partnership that worked. We now have fresh produce out there. And that's really important.</p><p end="1739" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1681">Of course, we have so many other measures that have taken place. Good grief, we have play streets. We've taken quiet streets and turned them into play yards because we have nothing else out there. We're using what we can. We're doing what we can. At the national level, obviously we're looking at prevention now. The national prevention and health promotion strategy to stop disease before it starts. Million hearts campaign.</p><p end="1739" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1681">Let's Move actually celebrates its second anniversary this month alone. And it's been reaching out to everyone from REI for outdoor, you know, to a beverage industry for clear on calories so you can begin to understand what's going on in those labels. Is it perfect? Absolutely not. Is it voluntary, and does it touch people's lives? Hell yeah. I'm on the board of America on the Move, and we're moving. We have corporate sponsors.</p><p end="1739" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1681">We do private, public sponsorships all year long. We do this in neighborhoods, in states all across this country. We touch people.</p><p end="1802" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1739">Exercise is Medicine, I am their national spokesperson, a collaboration of the American Medical Association as well as the American College of Sports Medicine.And here we see again trying to show people that there are simple, small steps, literally,</p><p end="1802" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1739">that you can take to be able to help yourself, voluntary, nothing stuffed up your nose.</p><p end="1802" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1739">We're not going to the tax and ban place. We're not food policing. We're reaching out asking people to hold our hand and say, come on. We can do this together. Is it sloppy?</p><p end="1802" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1739">Yeah. Are we perfect? No. We're about as perfect as the people who create them and implement them. We're human. We're getting there.</p><p end="1802" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1739">I'm going to switch over to my last hat for my seven minutes as a researcher. Guess what? The National Institutes of Health is public funding. $32 billion to save your lives,</p><p end="1802" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1739">to do the work we do.</p><p end="1859" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1802">It's interesting, when I began my work there as a senior scientist, I went to the clinical director's office, and above the office there was a sign that said, "In God we trust," and there was a little sign below it that said, "Everyone else must show data."</p><p end="1859" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1802">laughter</p><p end="1859" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1802">Fairly straightforward. We wanted to see some good data here. And so in our laboratory we showed the connection between chronic stress for instance and the buildup of that toxic fat deep inside your belly which increases your risk for heart disease and diabetes. We showed for instance that it's not about ELMM, "Eat less,</p><p end="1859" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1802">move more." That's so important, however, so much bigger. We forgot the mind.</p><p end="1859" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1802">What about stress? New research has just been published showing that children who are stressed, and you know what that's about, in their childhood, at home, at school, eat more, and that's that stress-fat connection that we talk about so often. What are we doing about that?</p><p end="1920" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1859">We have a new science called, "epigenetics," we're trying to look at how we can literally change gene expression, how we turn on and off genes, by simply doing easy things like if I eat an apple every day on a regular basis I get that gene expression and therefore I'm able to what? Have an increased or decreased vulnerability toward obesity. Or I could just do what so many people do, that nocturnal m&#233;nage &#224; trois every night, you know what I'm talking about, you, Ben, and Jerry.</p><p end="1920" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1859">laughter</p><p end="1920" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1859">All together in bed watching the tube, hanging out, doing it. Doesn't work, all right?</p><p end="1920" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1859">What's that gene expression looking like? All right. So here we're looking at something that's a brand new phenomenon, something we love to call "secondhand obesity."</p><p end="1920" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1859">What we're looking at is virally, families, what's going on with them? How are wetouching kids? It's so much bigger than demonizing sugar. It's so much bigger, so much bigger than saying the government's just too fat.</p><p end="1989" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1920">What we're saying is, putting our hand out, we're trying to say, "Educate, bigger brain,</p><p end="1989" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1920">better choices, obesity is the government's business."</p><p end="1989" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="1920">applause</p><p end="1989" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="1920">Thank you. I think that the fundamental difficulty here is that, despite the great courtesy of the organizers of this debate to invite me, I'd like to start by pointing out that this debate is framed in completely the wrong way. To have a motion that says,</p><p end="1989" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="1920">"Obesity is the government's business," essentially begs the question because using the term "obesity" frames the debate as one which is about the supposedly pathological state of people who have a body mass index of about 30 if they're obese or above 25 if they're overweight.</p><p end="2041" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="1989">And that in itself essentially tells us that we ought to think about those states as being per se bad and in fact a diseased or a quasi-diseased state. Imagine if this debate were framed as, "Eliminating body diversity is the government's business." I think that would sound a lot different, but in point of fact there is really -- there is no practical distinction between those two motions. The assumptions at work here are that a narrow range of body weight is normal for human beings and that outside that range a variation is the product of poor lifestyle. Furthermore, it's assumed in the framing of this issue that by reforming poor lifestyle either voluntarily or quasi coercively, you can eliminate abnormal body weight. This is all wrong.</p><p end="2102" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="2041">There's nothing normal about normal body weight. It's not normal statistically. It's not normal epidemiologically. The overweight category of BMI 25 to 29.9 does not, in fact,</p><p end="2102" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="2041">feature increased overall health risk, so there isn't even a correlation there between increased health risk and the pathologizing of that body state. The vast majority of people, and I'm going to say this about 27 times tonight, cannot intentionally modifytheir body mass in a long term fashion successfully. There is no better established proposition empirically in all of medicine than that. In other words, people, as you all know -- well, I shouldn't say "all of you," but many of you know from personal experience -- find it extraordinarily difficult to change their body weight in a significant long term way voluntarily. Government intervention in this area, and my partner, John Stossel is quite correct in saying that.</p><p end="2152" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="2102">In comparison to him, I am almost a Stalinist in my enthusiasm for government intervention, although I think he did overstate a couple of my positions. I won&#8217;t get into those because that&#8217;s beside the point. But in fact, even though I am generally enthusiastic about various forms of government regulation that fill him with dread, I am in fact utterly opposed to government regulation in this area because I think government -- the same as -- obesity as government&#8217;s business is almost a kind of dream scenario for a Libertarian. Because a Libertarian could not come up with a better example of government dysfunction than of the notion that we&#8217;re supposed to make people thinner, mainly because -- well, for a bunch of reasons, which I want to go through quickly right now and then come back to later.</p><p end="2222" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="2152">Here I want to emphasize first of all that we do not know an enormous number of things that we would have to know if we were going to have a rational policy that was based on the notion that we were going to make everybody have a BMI between 18.5 and 24.9, the so-called normal range, which for an average height woman would be between 108 and 144 pounds, outside of that supposedly pathological. Here&#8217;s what we don&#8217;t know. We don&#8217;t know how to produce significant long-term weight loss. We just don&#8217;t. We don&#8217;t know if such weight loss would be beneficial. This hypothesis has not been tested for the very good reason that since we don&#8217;t know how to produce it, we can&#8217;t test the hypothesis. We don&#8217;t know to what extent, if at all, the generally weak associations between obesity and increased health risk are products of a causal relationship as opposed to markers for other things like, for example, dieting, weight cycling, diet drug use, eating disorders, stress, stigma, and lower socioeconomic status.</p><p end="2222" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="2152">We don&#8217;t know why weight went up among Americans in the 1980s and &#8216;90s. We don&#8217;t know why it was stable in the 1960s and &#8216;70s. We don&#8217;t know why it has plateaued over the course of the last 10 years.</p><p end="2279" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="2222">We don&#8217;t in fact know whether people are more sedentary today than they were 40 years ago. We just don&#8217;t have the data on that. We just have a few very indirect markers for that, such as the amount of mandatory gym periods in school, but we don&#8217;t have any direct measurement of how active people were 40 years ago. We don&#8217;t knowwhether people consume more calories today than they did 40 years ago. Again, the data is not available. People often -- you know, when that&#8217;s pointed out to them rather rudely by someone like me, the reaction of public health officials tends to be something like, &#8220;Well, it&#8217;s just common sense,&#8221; right. But see, common sense is what you invoke when you don&#8217;t have data, right.</p><p end="2279" is_meta="true" speaker="Paul Campos" start="2222">laughter</p><p end="2279" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="2222">That&#8217;s why we have these academic institutions, right, so that we don&#8217;t just rely on common sense. We actually try to have some evidence for our propositions. Here&#8217;s what we do know. We do know that public health interventions designed to produce weight loss do not produce weight loss. This hypothesis has been tested.</p><p end="2342" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="2279">It&#8217;s been tested in situations where we have had intense public health intermediations that are much more intense than those that we could produce on a population-wide scale. And those interventions do not produce weight loss, either in adults or children.</p><p end="2342" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="2279">We do know that labeling bodies as diseased is stigmatizing, and we know that stigma is very bad for health, as are stress, weight cycling, and eating disorders, which are other things that are produced by this kind of labeling. We do know that risk factors that are associated with obesity, like, for instance, hypertension, can be addressed cheaply and successfully through inexpensive drugs that work quite well and increased physical activity, which is beneficial for people of all shapes and sizes whether in fact it produces any weight loss, which it usually doesn&#8217;t. Finally, what I really would want to emphasize here above all is that healthy lifestyles don&#8217;t eliminate body diversity, which is found among people with a wide variety of body types, many of whom fall outside the phony,</p><p end="2342" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="2279">so-called normal range.</p><p end="2410" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="2342">And so, what I would advocate more than anything else is that we ought to focus on a harm reduction, not weight reduction. We&#8217;ve already had some indications tonight of the notion that we don&#8217;t want to stress people. Here&#8217;s a suggestion. Stop telling them that their bodies are pathological because that&#8217;s very stressful.</p><p end="2410" is_meta="true" speaker="Paul Campos" start="2342">applause</p><p end="2410" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="2342">That&#8217;s not good for people. And if you say that you don&#8217;t want to stigmatize obese people but you just want to stigmatize obesity, I would suggest that that is a protocol that&#8217;s not going to be successful. Thank you.</p><p end="2513" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="2463">Well, I think the evidence is related to several things. First, we had a very interesting study funded by NIH in the late '90s, early part of this 2000.</p><p end="2584" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="2513">And basically showed that if we could get people to be physically active and to change their diet, even if they lost only five to 15 percent of their weight, we could dramatically decrease the risk for diabetes, in fact almost 60 percent reduction among African-</p><p end="2584" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="2513">Americans and American Indians in the onset of Type II diabetes, by getting people tochange their lifestyles and to be more physically active and to consume diets with less saturated fats and sugars. So I think we do know, from that study, that it's possible to help people change lifestyles. And I did say help because Pamela is correct, there are a lot of people in this country who do not have access to healthy lifestyles. And it is in fact a responsibility of government to make sure that everybody has the opportunity,</p><p end="2584" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="2513">everybody has access to the opportunity for healthy lifestyles.</p><p end="2584" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="2513">The track record that I mentioned was the one dealing with African-Americans and American Indians in terms of reducing --</p><p end="2584" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="2513">-- the risk for diabetes mellitus.</p><p end="2647" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="2584">Yes. In fact in that study --</p><p end="2647" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="2584">Yes, right. And it's a study that Dr. Satcher was citing there, there was an average of 2.3 kilograms of weight loss, which is about four pounds. The difficulty with citations to the notion that a small amount of weight loss is going to greatly reduce the risk of Type II diabetes is that a couple things, one, you can't -- you cannot disentangle the amount of weight loss that is produced, which is generally quite small, from the beneficial effect of the lifestyle intervention. The way that you would want to test that, to say, well, let's look at the people who've lost weight and compare them to the people who didn't lose weight if they all engage in the same lifestyle intervention. Is there a dose response that is related to the weight loss? And the answer is no, there isn't. In those studies, the people who engaged in the same lifestyle changes but didn't lose weight had the samereduction, on average, in Type II diabetes risk as people who engaged in the lifestyle changes and did in fact lose some weight.</p><p end="2699" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="2647">So to me, that's really compelling evidence for the notion that focusing on weight in that context doesn't make any sense. I'm all for focusing on, you know, lifestyle changes. I think it's good to encourage people to be physically active. But there's a lot of evidence that physical activity in and of itself is beneficial. But what there's not evidence of is that either physical activity changes are going to produce significant long-term weight loss. Again, they don't in the vast majority of people, or secondly, that the weight loss is necessary for the purposes of getting the benefits of the increase in the --</p><p end="2699" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="2647">-- in the activity levels.</p><p end="2699" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="2647">Mm-hmm.</p><p end="2760" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="2699">I will be more than happy to take that on. Apparently Paul is not aware of the national weight control registry. This is an ongoing study, almost 20 years old, which has been sponsored by the University of Colorado as well as Brown University, my colleagues, Dr.</p><p end="2760" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="2699">James Hill and Rena Wing. The cohort right now is over 10,000 people, including people who have bariatric surgery as well. And these people are known as the successful losers. And actually, Paul, you actually are too, because of your own weight loss as you noted in your book. You qualify because you had to have dropped at least 30 poundsand kept it off for at least a year. And the grand majority of these people have kept off approximately 60 pounds for almost six years or longer. And this is on the average in a very large cohort. So are these mutants?</p><p end="2822" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="2760">Freaks? What are they? These people have determined that they will keep this weight off by utilizing very simple things. And this has been published in extensive literature.</p><p end="2822" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="2760">One of the most interesting things we found was that the number one predictor for being able to keep weight off and do this well is to have a healthy breakfast every morning. They are physically active. Are they part of the Olympic camp? No. They basically get out. And the number one favorite thing to do is walk. And in most of the government interventions, all we're asking people to do is not drop weight so much.</p><p end="2822" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="2760">That's not where we're going. Losing weight, I'm a physician. People lose weight and do really stupid things to lose weight. That's not where we're going.</p><p end="2822" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="2760">We're going to health.</p><p end="2822" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="2760">We're going to health, and we're going to fitness.</p><p end="2822" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="2760">And that's what we saw in this study.</p><p end="2822" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="2760">Absolutely.</p><p end="2877" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="2822">Because Pamela said that's all voluntary and talked about public-private partnerships being voluntary. But government isn't voluntary. It said we have a voluntary tax system. But try not paying your taxes and see if it's voluntary. Men with guns will come and make you pay for the dumb programs that they keep creating that don't work and that Paul says make people miserable.</p><p end="2877" is_meta="true" speaker="John Stossel" start="2822">laughter</p><p end="2877" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="2822">And keep growing.</p><p end="2877" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="2822">Because the schools can barely teach reading, writing and arithmetic.</p><p end="2877" is_meta="true" speaker="John Stossel" start="2822">applause</p><p end="2877" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="2822">Well, I think a couple of things. The goal of these programs is to help children develop lifetime habits of physical activity and good nutrition.</p><p end="2939" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="2877">We also know, by the way, that children who develop good eating habits and regular physical activity do better academically. They perform better on standardized exams in math and reading. They are more disciplined in school. So the benefits of healthy lifestyles go far beyond losing weight. Now, Paul quoted the statistics about weight loss versus decrease in diabetes. The goal is to decrease fat. And sometimes you can decrease fat and increase muscle and not lose weight. But you still reduce the risk of diabetes. I think you know that as a runner.</p><p end="2939" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="2877">So let them learn that from Pamela's TV show and from Richard Simmons. We don't need government.</p><p end="2939" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="2877">Dr. David Satcher:Excuse --</p><p end="2939" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="2877">Here's the problem.</p><p end="2939" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="2877">Yeah, that's nice for people who do have cable TV. Unfortunately, many people don't have Discovery Channel.</p><p end="2939" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="2877">applause</p><p end="2939" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="2877">So for those poor people out there who have no access, what are you going to do? You just assume they're going to catch it on the tube. Oh, no. You're not supposed to be watching TV because if you watch TV too long, you get this big.</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="2939">So, I mean, you're going round and round. Why not just sit there? Why not do what Alice Waters did in Berkeley, the Martin Luther King middle school? She built a garden.</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="2939">She had the kids grow stuff.</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="2939">Kids who grow and eat it.</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="2939">Well, let's be clear, though.</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="2939">It's not the information. It's the opportunity to act on it.</p><p end="3058" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3001">I think what Pamela described in terms of in the inner cities of the country&#8212;you don't have sidewalks, you don't have safe places to be physically active, you don't have access to grocery stores, so what you're talking about is the opportunity --</p><p end="3058" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="3001">That's absolutely right.</p><p end="3058" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3001">-- to leave --</p><p end="3058" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3001">Yeah, in some --</p><p end="3058" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3001">Look at what Louisville did. It changed the zoning laws so that within so much area you had to have grocery stores and you had to have parks and playgrounds, so the government can, in fact, produce the opportunities for people to have access.</p><p end="3058" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3001">Oh, really?</p><p end="3058" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3001">The fixation here is on healthy lifestyles.</p><p end="3058" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3001">What was your report called, Dr. Satcher, your 2001 report? Was it a report on healthy lifestyles?</p><p end="3122" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3058">No, the first ever surgeon general's report was on smoking and health and it was on cancer, but that wasn't the focus. The focus was on getting people to stop smoking.</p><p end="3122" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="3058">Absolutely.</p><p end="3122" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3058">So are you in favor of getting people to stop eating?</p><p end="3122" is_meta="true" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3058">laughter</p><p end="3122" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3058">Getting people to stop -- getting people to eat -- to engage in healthy lifestyles.</p><p end="3122" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3058">Well, I'm all for engaging in healthy lifestyles, but I'd like to point out that --</p><p end="3122" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3058">That's the role of government.</p><p end="3122" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3058">-- one of the most interesting things about this debate is that if you had a time capsule,</p><p end="3122" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3058">everything that's being said by the advocates of the government's position here was said almost literally word for word in the 1950s. Remember -- some of you may remember -- President John Kennedy -- I don't remember it actually, but I've read about it -- initiative for the president's council on physical fitness, right?</p><p end="3122" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3058">John Stossel:I remember that.</p><p end="3122" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3058">John remembers it, right?</p><p end="3122" is_meta="true" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3058">laughter</p><p end="3122" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3058">That's right, all that kind of thing, [unintelligible], you know, that we're all for[unintelligible], and, you know, for being healthy in that way. John Kennedy was actually a wreck physically but they hid that quite successfully at the time because -- but anyways, that's another story.</p><p end="3181" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3122">The thing is, it's really striking, if you looked at the literature, the government officials were saying in the 1950s the same thing they're saying today, they're saying,</p><p end="3181" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3122">"Americans are getting horribly fat, and it's going to cause this huge health crisis, and if we don't do something about it, the Russians are going to just come in and push us over and takeover --"</p><p end="3181" is_meta="true" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3122">laughter</p><p end="3181" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3122">"-- and it's, you know, the terrorists within," and all that stuff, and nothing that was ever predicted took place. But this is one area I have found in terms of government policy and social hysteria and moral panic where data simply doesn't move anything because people have such a fixation with the desirability of weight loss that you can talk all you want about how we ought to have healthier lifestyles, but what people really want to do is make people thin.</p><p end="3181" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="3122">No, we don't want to make people thin.</p><p end="3241" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="3181">It has everything to do with the government --</p><p end="3241" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="3181">-- because they don't have resources. Where are the play yards? Where are the parks?</p><p end="3241" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="3181">Where are the bike paths?</p><p end="3300" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3241">I just want to say, though --</p><p end="3300" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3241">It would be very interesting to find these studies that Paul is quoting saying that obesity was a major problem in the '50s. There's no such study. We looked at every --</p><p end="3300" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3241">Forty percent of the American population was, quote, unquote, "overweight," in 1958,</p><p end="3300" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3241">40 percent, so apparently if there's been an epidemic, we've had an epidemic for a long time.</p><p end="3300" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3241">But overweight -- I want to be clear about "overweight," because I know you've written,</p><p end="3300" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3241">saying that people who are overweight are healthier. Many people who are overweight are athletes who are muscular or people who work out, so we admit it in our books, we acknowledge that the BMI is not reliable in people who are muscular, who are athletes,</p><p end="3300" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3241">and who work out. So I think that's a distortion.</p><p end="3364" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="3300">My understanding is that there are just as many or more parks, playgrounds and sidewalks as there have ever been. People can exercise if they wanted to. And John,</p><p end="3364" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="3300">you talked about they&#8217;re responding to this national emergency. That&#8217;s the justification for government, and I think you&#8217;re right. And that always is. The crisis is the friend of the state. But there -- the specialists always have emergencies. It&#8217;s terrorism or global warming or Y2K. Remember, the planes were all going to crash, and the killer bees were coming up from Mexico, were going to sting us all to death, and Bird Flu and plastic bottles. It&#8217;s endless. It all requires government to intervene, to raise your taxes and to limit your freedom.</p><p end="3364" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="3300">Right here in New York City.</p><p end="3364" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="3300">Honey, listen, get out of New York -- get out of New York and live, right. Go out to the hinterland. Go out to places where people don&#8217;t have these --</p><p end="3364" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="3300">The hinterland is one big park.</p><p end="3364" is_meta="true" speaker="John Stossel" start="3300">laughter</p><p end="3425" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="3364">Very seriously, John. I mean, really, what we&#8217;re looking at is the ability to be able to give people options. We keep telling people to go out and do whatever. Eat less, move more. You give them food deserts. You don&#8217;t give them anywhere to move that&#8217;s safe.</p><p end="3425" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="3364">And then what do you have? Where is that obesity? Do I see a lot of obesity out here?</p><p end="3425" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="3364">I don&#8217;t think so. Again, go to the hinterland. John, keep looking. It&#8217;s up there somewhere.</p><p end="3425" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="3364">laughter</p><p end="3425" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3364">You don&#8217;t have to go to the hinterland. There are many areas in this city and surrounding cities where it&#8217;s not safe to get out and walk in the street. It&#8217;s not safe.</p><p end="3425" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3364">There&#8217;s no safe place.</p><p end="3425" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3364">applause</p><p end="3425" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="3364">It&#8217;s safer than it used to be. Crime is down.</p><p end="3425" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3364">I&#8217;m sorry.</p><p end="3425" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="3364">It&#8217;s safer than it used to be. Crime is down. And obesity is up.</p><p end="3425" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3364">And it&#8217;s down in great part because of the same leadership that&#8217;s now saying that we&#8217;ve got to change the way we direct food to people.</p><p end="3477" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3425">We&#8217;ve got to intervene to make sure that people know what they&#8217;re eating.</p><p end="3477" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3425">No, the association exists, but the relationship is complex, right. I mean, the notion --</p><p end="3477" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3425">do we know that diabetes causes obesity? How do we know that obesity doesn&#8217;t cause diabetes?</p><p end="3477" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3425">Right, we -- in other words --</p><p end="3477" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3425">We don&#8217;t know -- we don&#8217;t know the cause of breast cancer. That doesn&#8217;t mean we don&#8217;t screen for it. We do know the association.</p><p end="3477" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3425">applause</p><p end="3477" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3425">Well, yeah, but David, I don&#8217;t think --</p><p end="3477" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3425">In public health, we deal with associations.</p><p end="3477" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3425">Do you want to just perform mastectomies on women who don&#8217;t have breast cancer so they can avoid getting breast cancer?</p><p end="3545" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3477">I don&#8217;t get the connection.</p><p end="3545" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3477">The connection is --</p><p end="3545" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="3477">Okay, Paul, Paul.</p><p end="3545" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="3477">Whoah, whoah, whoah, whoah, whoah. In our laboratory, in the laboratories of many of our esteemed colleagues around the country, we&#8217;ve made it very clear that excessive visceral adiposity, a lot of fat deep inside your belly, is highly associated with a pro-</p><p end="3545" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="3477">inflammatory state, which increases the risk of diabetes, coronary vascular disease and cancer, period. I have that much literature to back up.</p><p end="3545" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3477">Yes, that&#8217;s right.</p><p end="3545" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="3477">And you know what? You can get rid of visceral body fat --</p><p end="3545" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="3477">talking simultaneously</p><p end="3545" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="3477">In addition, Paul, the information that you presented showing that overweight is okay by me is actually wrong. And that has been refuted by at least two pooled meta-</p><p end="3545" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="3477">analyses publishes in Lancet and the New England Journal of Medicine by my colleague,</p><p end="3545" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="3477">Dr. Walter Willett from Harvard and by leading epidemiologists around this country basically refuting your --</p><p end="3545" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3477">Yeah, well, first of all, visceral body fat can be very effectively dealt with through changes in activity levels. It&#8217;s not going to --</p><p end="3599" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3545">There is a correlation between visceral body fat and increased health risks. That&#8217;s quite true, but the notion -- look, again, I want to emphasize the willingness to talk out of both sides of the mouth on this issue is just astonishing to me. You have people coming here and say obesity, obesity, obesity, right. We have this huge crisis. And then I point out this is a bunch of nonsense. And then it gets flipped around into, &#8220;Well, we&#8217;re not really talking about obesity. We&#8217;re talking about lifestyle.&#8221; This isn&#8217;t called, you know,</p><p end="3599" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3545">&#8220;Is lifestyle the government&#8217;s business?&#8221; This doesn&#8217;t have a picture of a lifestyle on the front of it, right.</p><p end="3599" is_meta="true" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3545">laughter</p><p end="3599" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3545">It has a picture of a --</p><p end="3599" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3545">Now, let&#8217;s be fair. Obesity is an outcome, in many cases, of unhealthy lifestyles. It&#8217;s not that simple. We differ in terms of metabolism. There&#8217;re some people who can eat a lot of calories and not gain a lot of weight. There are other people who gain weight easily.</p><p end="3599" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3545">So everybody&#8217;s not equal.</p><p end="3657" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3599">We&#8217;re not stigmatizing people who are obese. Read the surgeon general's report,</p><p end="3657" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3599">clearly says this is not about appearances. It's about health. And the way to improve health is to change lifestyles. That's what the report says.</p><p end="3657" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3599">applause</p><p end="3717" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="3657">Well, they mention the NIH and basic research. And there is a better argument to be made that that does promote the general welfare.</p><p end="3783" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="3717">But if the general welfare means the obesity police or the lifestyle police, then there is no limit to what government can do. Then they can reach into every crevice of your life.</p><p end="3783" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="3717">They can ban the dinner you're about to have. They can ban fat --</p><p end="3783" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="3717">-- and ice cream.</p><p end="3783" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="3717">You used to work at ABC. You can't be a neutral journalist.</p><p end="3783" is_meta="true" speaker="John Stossel" start="3717">laughter</p><p end="3783" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="3717">Sorry.</p><p end="3783" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="3717">Well, that's part of it. I mean, Thomas Jefferson said it's the natural progress of things for government to grow and liberty to yield.</p><p end="3841" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="3783">Government always grows. It starts with information. It moves to taxes. Then it moves to limits on what you can consume. And now that we have Obama care and the government says we're going to pay for your health care, then that's an argument to say, we have the right to have exercise police come into your home and make you improve your lifestyle.</p><p end="3841" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3783">You start off by quoting --</p><p end="3841" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3783">-- Lincoln, so I'll quote Lincoln who said that it is the role of government to do for people what they cannot do for themselves. And that's what we're talking about here.</p><p end="3841" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="3783">People can't lose weight for themselves?</p><p end="3841" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3783">Not if they don't have safe places to be physically active, not if they don't have access to fresh fruits and vegetables.</p><p end="3841" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="3783">And they can't be biggest loser because they don't own a TV.</p><p end="3841" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3783">Well, that's going to be helpful.</p><p end="3902" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3841">Well, couple things. First of all, if you're concerned about rising medical costs, which you would be in favor of if you believe that obesity kills people, then much obesity is possible because what drives medical care costs through the roof is an aging population,</p><p end="3902" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3841">all right?</p><p end="3960" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3902">That's where the health care costs get spent, right? In an elderly population, supposedly obese people are all going to die before they get to be old, right, which is, of course,</p><p end="3960" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3902">nonsense. But if you really did believe that, that's what would drive down health care costs. Secondly, and I think more fundamentally -- and I just want to repeat this again.</p><p end="3960" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3902">We cannot make fat people thin, okay? So even if it was desirable from a social perspective to produce a society that did not have a lot of fat people in it, you cannot do that in a developed economy, right? We have a situation in this country where we somehow got it into our heads that everybody can be within a certain narrow range of body mass if they have a healthy lifestyle. That's -- there's absolutely no reason for believing that that's true or that it's in any way necessary. So I mean, I'll tell you what,</p><p end="3960" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3902">you know what really would reduce health care costs more than anything else? I can do a back of the envelope calculation right now. We can reduce healthcare costs by $1.7 trillion a year out of the 1.9 trillion that we spend by just having everybody be between the ages of 20 and 29.</p><p end="3960" is_meta="true" speaker="Paul Campos" start="3902">laughter</p><p end="4023" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3960">That's a great question --</p><p end="4023" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="3960">-- that you raise. Let me just say that 80 percent of Medicare costs -- and Medicare is the most expensive program that government supports in terms of health. 80 percent of their costs are due to preventable diseases. And certainly, half of that is related to obesity and Type II diabetes. There's no question about it. So it is true that the government has a self-interest to try to help people to develop healthy lifestyles. And we're not even talking about obesity. We're talking about the benefits of healthy lifestyles generally. Less diabetes mellitus, which is a major driver of costs of Medicare and other health programs.</p><p end="4023" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="3960">Can we quit saying that we're trying to aim for turning fat people into thin people? This is -- just end it now, please.</p><p end="4085" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="4023">This is ridiculous.</p><p end="4085" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="4023">We're going for healthy, and we're going for fit. We don't want life spans. We want health spans. We want the highest quality of life we can have. And if you started out at 250 pounds, and you're a 5'4" woman, and right now you're 180 and a happy camper,</p><p end="4085" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="4023">-- and fitness.</p><p end="4198" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="4144">Well, I think we ought to be clear. You know, we are the government, and it is the role of government to create the conditions in which people can be healthy. That's how we define public health. That's how the Institute of Medicine defines public health. It is the role of public health to create the condition.</p><p end="4261" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="4198">It's a collective effort to create the conditions in which people can be healthy. And that's what we're talking about.</p><p end="4261" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="4198">But aren't there more opportunities to be healthy now than ever before? Per capita income, a bicycle is cheaper than it used to be. There are more soccer leagues than there ever used to be. There's more awareness of physical activity.</p><p end="4261" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="4198">Oh, I'm so sorry, did you forget about the fact that in the grand majority of schools across this country physical education is all but eliminated, it's gone?</p><p end="4261" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="4198">applause</p><p end="4261" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="4198">Well, let's get rid of government schools --</p><p end="4261" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="4198">And so we have --</p><p end="4261" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="4198">-- and we'll have better school.</p><p end="4261" is_meta="true" speaker="John Stossel" start="4198">laughter</p><p end="4261" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="4198">-- and then in addition, John, in addition, John, for soccer, I'm sorry, that costs money.</p><p end="4261" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="4198">You have to have money to buy those soccer clothes. You have to have money to join the league. And those kids don't have it. So let's just see now. We eliminated recess.</p><p end="4261" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="4198">I just have to disagree --</p><p end="4261" is_meta="true" speaker="John Stossel" start="4198">talking simultaneously</p><p end="4261" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="4198">-- New York City any kid can join a soccer league and if he doesn't have money the equipment will be given free. There's plenty of charities around to pay for that.</p><p end="4329" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="4261">Let me remind you that schools are supposed to be the great equalizers in this country.</p><p end="4329" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="4261">In other words, kids come to school, some of them come from communities where they have adequate places to play, access to fresh fruits and vegetables. Other children come from homes where there's no place to play safely, no access to fresh fruits and vegetables. At school at least they should be helped in developing lifetime habits of physical activity and good nutrition.</p><p end="4379" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="4329">Yeah, I think it's an excellent question. The government's role can be put into three categories. One is this assessment where you really monitor the health of the population, and you give us this kind of information that we can act on.</p><p end="4437" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="4379">The second one is assurance that everybody has access to the opportunity to lead healthy lifestyles. The third one is policy. And you're right, it is the responsibility of government to develop guidelines for healthy eating. The Nutrition Act that's just passed is an effort to say, "If we're going to have free breakfast, free lunch in the schools for 40 to 50 percent of the children, we must make sure that those lunches are healthy, that they have adequate fruits and vegetables," I agree with you. The third role of government is policy development, and that policy is made in such a way as to make sure, number one, we have the information that we need, we&#8217;ve got to have labels on the foods so we know what we're getting, and also you've got to make sure the children who are receiving these lunches are getting healthy foods.</p><p end="4437" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="4379">That is the role of government.</p><p end="4498" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="4437">Dr. Satcher, I think you're confusing intention with results. It's nice that we have this good intention, but government doesn't get the results. Some schools now have banned vending machines. A University of Pennsylvania study -- banned vending machines that sell unhealthy food. They studied it.</p><p end="4556" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="4498">They found the kids eat just as much junk food, no difference in weight loss. You earlier said that, you know, the schools are supposed to be the great equalizer. They are supposed to be, but government schools are more segregated than private schools. It doesn&#8217;t work. Government fails.</p><p end="4556" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="4498">Well, well, I don&#8217;t agree that governments fail. Now, the study that you&#8217;re talking about, I don&#8217;t think anyone, even the ones who carried it out would see that as a conclusive study. What they said was to date, we don&#8217;t see the evidence that changing the vending machines --</p><p end="4556" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="4498">We are going to keep working to help children develop lifetime habits of good nutrition and physical activity. I think that&#8217;s our responsibility. And that&#8217;s what the schools have to do.</p><p end="4556" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="4498">There -- I mean, I think there&#8217;s a major misunderstanding here about the way that society works in regard to the things that people eat and how many calories they have.</p><p end="4617" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="4556">I mean, I&#8217;ve just spent the last three days on the upper west side of New York, and I&#8217;m surrounded by nothing but the most incredibly high caloric food that you can imagine,</p><p end="4617" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="4556">which, thanks to the neuroses of your mayor, are now made evident to me every time that I walk into a store because it says right there how many calories there are. And so I go into this place where it&#8217;s filled 100 percent by upper class white people looking at these little cupcakes that have 545 calories in them, so it&#8217;s like a nuclear bomb of calories, right. But is that going to cause obesity in that group? No. Guess why?</p><p end="4617" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="4556">Because they&#8217;re going to, you know, buy it and then slice it into eight little pieces and then eat it in a super neurotic way and then go to the yoga studio for two hours, right.</p><p end="4617" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="4556">Now, the notion that that kind of a social structure can be altered through these kinds of informational government interventions is just -- again, there&#8217;s no data to back it up.</p><p end="4617" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="4556">Now, I understand the theory that if something hasn&#8217;t worked, you can keep doing it until it does work, right.</p><p end="4679" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="4617">That -- [unintelligible] one of the classic, you know, definitions of insanity, but that seems to be the government program here. Again, do you think --</p><p end="4679" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="4617">It&#8217;s amazing that the same thing was said about tobacco, the effort to get people to stop smoking, you know. Go back to the &#8217;60s and the &#8216;70s. It&#8217;s not working. There&#8217;s no evidence. To date, we can point to millions and millions of peoples whose lives have been saved because of the efforts to get people to quit smoking.</p><p end="4679" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="4617">Smoking is a behavior. Obesity is not a behavior.</p><p end="4679" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="4617">You&#8217;re wrong, wrong, absolutely wrong.</p><p end="4679" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="4617">Paul Campos:Oh, absolutely wrong? Is that why -- tell me, Pam. Tell me, Pam, why are people fat?</p><p end="4679" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="4617">Why are people fat?</p><p end="4679" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="4617">Was it magic? It was behavior.</p><p end="4679" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="4617">Because I&#8217;m a upper-class white person who has the privilege of modifying my weight to an extent that most people don&#8217;t.</p><p end="4679" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="4617">And you cut your cupcake into 13 pieces.</p><p end="4679" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="4617">Except, you know, right now, Pam, I weight about 185 pounds, which is supposed to be rather high in the overweight range. So, apparently, I might drop dead right on the stage right now because according to Dr. Walter Willett, that -- to be overweight is very,</p><p end="4679" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="4617">very dangerous.</p><p end="4751" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="4679">If that doesn&#8217;t happen, I suggest that people think about the possibilities that are actually available to people in this culture. And I would especially want to emphasize that if you think that the biggest problem that poor kids have in this country right now is that they don&#8217;t get enough information about how much calories is in the junk food they eat or they don&#8217;t have enough play spaces to play outside, you&#8217;ve got a really bad conceptualization of what actually --</p><p end="4751" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="4679">You&#8217;re off-topic, Paul.</p><p end="4801" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="4751">It&#8217;s a great point and a great question. And I think that&#8217;s exactly what&#8217;s happening. I think government is beginning to change the way we spend our money relative to foods,</p><p end="4801" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="4751">with children especially. Look at the new nutrition act and the difference that it represents from what we&#8217;ve seen in the past in terms of the way children eat in school.</p><p end="4801" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="4751">So I think we are -- the government is responding to the studies that we&#8217;ve been talking about, showing how these foods are affecting lifestyles and therefore resulting in ill health, especially Type II diabetes, even in children. So, you&#8217;re right, we, the government, have been at fault in many ways in terms of what&#8217;s going on in this country, in terms of subsidies as you pointed out. And hopefully we are making the changes that we need to make.</p><p end="4866" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="4801">It is the role of government to continue to learn and to grow and to change. And that's what we're seeing now.</p><p end="4913" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="4866">As surgeon general, what I said was that I'm not a politician. I speak to the American people based on the best available public health science. But believe me, there were a lot of political pressures on me every time I did a report. But the fact of the matter is,</p><p end="4913" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="4866">the surgeon general's report is based on the best available public health science. It has to be approved by the NIH. It has to be approved by the CDC. It has to be approved by HHS. So government is imperfect. And it's up to us to continue to make it more perfect,</p><p end="4913" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="4866">a more perfect union. But it's up to us to continue to push the government --</p><p end="4978" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="4913">I think it's really important to keep in mind that scientists are people just like everybody else and that science is a deeply politicized activity because it can't avoid being politicized given that it's about power and social policy and all the things that are political all the way down. I think when we look at the food industry, one thing that people ought to keep in mind is that the food industry loves the obsession that Americans have with weight. The food industry makes enormous profits from selling people food that is supposed to make them thinner, right? The diet foods have a significantly higher profit margin than regular foods because diet foods can be sold as a kind of magical elixir that's going to cause this weight loss if you buy something, which it doesn't have something in it that it's supposed to have in it, but which is supposedly then -- which has a substitute of something else. So for instance, a fat-free Fig Newton has more calories in it than a regular Fig Newton.</p><p end="5043" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="4978">Because the sugar that's substituting for the fat in the fat-free Fig Newton is more caloric. But the fat-free Fig Newton will cost more. So the food industry loves all this stuff, loves the fact that we're obsessing on these issues and trying to supposedly find a magic cure for our supposed obesity epidemic because that's one of the main sources of its profit margins. And so it encourages this kind of social hysteria.</p><p end="5043" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="4978">Well, the way to get the price down is to make more of it, right? Isn't that what happens with -- happened with computers and everything? So in time, we ought to be able to get the price of Fig Newtons down.</p><p end="5043" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="4978">laughter</p><p end="5157" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="5097">I think she's suggesting it's not working, that they have a free lunch, but they spend $4 on the vending machine junk. You can't manipulate people as well as we think you can.</p><p end="5157" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="5097">Actually, there's a -- there is a fantastic study that just came out in the journal of sociology. And it basically showed that when you have all of this at school, and you have another option, many of these kids are going to what they're used to at home. And so what they're not going to do is, you know, come from a home where they're eating trash and drinking trash and back and forth, and then suddenly magically come to school and go, wow, asparagus, bring it on. They're just not going to do this.</p><p end="5218" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="5157">What you're talking about is a reward system in the brain that's been hijacked. And you're looking at consistent behaviors on the part of these children. This is one of the reasons why --</p><p end="5218" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="5157">Well, the government's role in this, you know, is a bit more complex. You're looking at a child and controlling that child and offering options there. But you haven't talked to the parents. What we need to do now is bring in the family. If you don't have the family as a unit in this, then this is going nowhere fast.</p><p end="5218" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="5157">And the government --</p><p end="5218" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="5157">Yeah, but what you're talking about is -- they may have the money. They haven't made the connection.</p><p end="5218" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="5157">Look --</p><p end="5218" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="5157">Again, this has been studied.</p><p end="5278" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="5218">There have been intense government intervention such as, for instance, the pathway study was based on the notion we're going to educate the kids, we're going to educate the parents about healthy eating habits and better physical activity. We're going to do all these wonderful things that the government is advocating that we do. And what those things did was that they produced some improvement in terms of lifestyle modification, but they did not produce weight loss. There is no evidence that telling parents of children, of fatter children, that this kind of food is -- has more calories in it,</p><p end="5278" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="5218">and this has less and this is more nutrient rich, and that is less or whatever, is going to produce thinner children. And I want to get back to Sandy Schaefer's point because I think it is an absolutely crucial one. Right now, what we are creating is a machine essentially for stigmatization and bullying, right, because the government is justbroadcasting this message 24/7, that if you're a fat kid, you have something wrong with you, and you have something wrong with you that happens to be your fault because you could modify it.</p><p end="5278" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="5218">Paul, that's not just the government.</p><p end="5278" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="5218">[unintelligible].</p><p end="5339" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="5278">No, no, no, no. We're talking about the media. Bring it on through the media. You look at those magazines. You look as those shows. You look at the fantasy world everyone lives in. That was going on a hell of a lot longer before any government intervention showed up.</p><p end="5339" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="5278">Right. But now you're exacerbating it.</p><p end="5339" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="5278">I think the government is the only actor. Remember who the government is. Public health is the collective efforts of a society to create the conditions in which people can be healthy.</p><p end="5400" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="5339">Government calls upon all of us to work together to solve the problem. It does it through public-private partnerships. So it's not either/or. We're not saying the government does this, and nobody else. We need all hands in. But if the government does not do its job, it will not get done because government has the resources, and nobody else does, to monitor the health of the population. Government has the resources to make policies so that we can have an idea what people are eating and what they are exposed to in terms of information.</p><p end="5400" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="5339">So I think the government has a role that only the government can play. But it doesn't mean nobody else does.</p><p end="5400" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="5339">Yeah, I'd like to point out something. The health of the American population is better now than it's ever been before. I mean, all this talk of like a huge health crisis overlooks the fact that in fact not only is the life expectancy the highest it's ever been and continuing to increase at a steady rate, but all -- the rates of almost all the major diseases are significantly lower than they've been before.</p><p end="5400" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="5339">Life expectancy may be up. Health span is down. The quality of life is decreasing significantly.</p><p end="5466" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="5400">Yeah, because people who are 90 are not very healthy.</p><p end="5466" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="5400">We're keeping people alive who are grossly disabled by these diseases.</p><p end="5466" is_meta="true" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="5400">laughter</p><p end="5466" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="5400">So you talked about Medicare, and it's true, it's eaten us alive. That's what's going to make us go broke fastest. So you're saying that because we have socialized medicine,</p><p end="5466" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="5400">which everybody loves, we have to give up our freedom and invite government to come in and control more of our lives?</p><p end="5521" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="5466">I don't think it's any coincidence that this biggest push for more food regulation comes at a time when Congress is obsessing about paying for everybody's health care. When government pays, it's drawn into your personal life, and this is not a good thing. It's not true that only government can do these things. Free people can control their own lives.</p><p end="5521" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="5466">Government will propose to control you because you eat too much. Will they next try to ban skydiving and extramarital sex? How about another try at prohibition? That might save money. You&#8217;re going to have the government teach poor people to serve asparagus when we have a $3.8 trillion spending already? [unintelligible] and transportation alternatives? I'll give you money. But you want government to build more bike paths? My local councilwoman is giving out free bike helmets to encourage bicycle use. You know, my neighborhood is where Jerry Seinfeld and Sting live.</p><p end="5584" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="5521">I say to her, "Why would you spend public money?" "This isn't public money. It's free.</p><p end="5584" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="5521">It's a government grant."</p><p end="5584" is_meta="true" speaker="John Stossel" start="5521">laughter</p><p end="5584" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="5521">It's not free. Some people say, "Well, it's just information." And information's good, but it's not free. These calorie counts which haven't worked, they raise the price of food a little because it costs restaurants money to post that. And they also -- all this information distracts you from other information that might be more important. This happens all the time when government intervenes. You ever look at a birth control pill label? I happen to have one here.[laughter]</p><p end="5584" is_meta="false" speaker="John Stossel" start="5521">Look at this thing. Tiny fine print, both sides, the result is nobody reads it. It doesn't make us safer. This is what government gives us.</p><p end="5640" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="5584">Well, let me say that I have seen government at its worst and I've seen government at its best. I know government is not perfect. I grew up in Alabama at a time of segregation and discrimination. I was a teenager when George Wallace, running for governor, came to town and said that he would deputize every white man in Alabama before he would see one black child go to the University of Alabama. I've seen government at its worst. But I've also seen government at its best. I've seen government protect children from lead. As a medical student I saw babies coming into emergency room with toxicity from lead. Many of them died. That was in the '60s. In 1978, the government regulated the lead content of house paint, and we've seen a dramatic decline in lead poisoning in children. I've seen government at its best.</p><p end="5702" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="5640">I've been involved in the eradication of polio, and all over the world, and recently learned that last year for the first time not one child in India suffered from polio. And only three countries in the world have polio, a total of less than 700 cases in the world.</p><p end="5702" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. David Satcher" start="5640">Government at its best is "We, the people." Government is the collective efforts of a society to create the conditions in which people can be healthy. So that's what we see as government. We believe that there is no substitute for individual responsibility. Let's make that clear. It's why I wrote the prescription. But individual responsibility can only take place in an environment where there is equal opportunity, there is equal access to the opportunity for a healthy lifestyle. It's our contention that obesity is the business of the government because it is the business of the government to create those conditions. Thank you.</p><p end="5762" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="5702">Thank you. I was watching the Super Bowl with my father who&#8217;s a retired physician and oncologist actually. And we were getting bombarded, of course, with erectile dysfunction ad drug advertisements. And they -- all of them have this tag line that&#8217;s legally required, right. &#8220;Ask your doctor if Cialis is right for you,&#8221; right. So after about,</p><p end="5762" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="5702">you know, six of these, my father turns to me and says, &#8220;How the hell do I know if Cialis is right for you?&#8221; Okay, and the point was, you know, significant in two ways. One, first of all, he&#8217;s an oncologist. He doesn&#8217;t know anything about the pharmacology of erectile dysfunction drugs, right, just because he&#8217;s a doctor, right. But the more profound point is that you would think that the question of whether Cialis is right for me is a little bit more socially complex and it could be answered by a doctor, right.</p><p end="5822" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="5762">You&#8217;d think there would be at least one other person who would have an opinion on that question besides a doctor, right. The point of that story really is that what is now called erectile dysfunction used to be called being 50 years old, right. In other words,</p><p end="5822" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="5762">we take a completely natural process and we pathologize it. We turn it into a disease so that it could be treated through pharmacological intervention. And what&#8217;s really going on here, and I know that our opponents are not in any way intending this, but intention,</p><p end="5822" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="5762">you know, we know the road to hell is paved with, right. What&#8217;s happening is that all this talk about lifestyle intervention is something that the pharmaceutical industry loves because they know that that stuff doesn&#8217;t work. And the point of all this discourse is to soften up the regulatory pipeline for the next generation of diet drugs. That&#8217;s where the real money is, and that&#8217;s why we&#8217;re hearing about obesity, obesity, obesity all the time.</p><p end="5883" is_meta="false" speaker="Paul Campos" start="5822">Oh, we&#8217;ll get kids to eat fruits and vegetables. Alice Waters will make asparagus for everybody, and we&#8217;ll make lots of bicycle paths, and then kids won&#8217;t be fat. But they will be anyways. Until then, what will we need? Drugs. And that&#8217;s what I would suggest this is really at the bottom line all about.</p><p end="5883" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="5822">As the Discovery health correspondent, I was filming my show in South Central L.A. at the National Body Challenge where we take families and we try to teach them everything we can as physicians about being healthier. It&#8217;s not just about dropping weight but being healthier. This was a small little house. It was 97 degrees in the middle of summer. There were no sidewalks. Or what was there was scary-looking.</p><p end="5938" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="5883">And we were asked to go out and take a little walk. And I looked near the front door,</p><p end="5938" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="5883">and there was a golf club sitting there. Now, the closest golf course was probably about 100 miles away. So I asked what was that sitting there for. And the mother looked at me and she said, &#8220;That&#8217;s to beat away the dogs, the feral dogs that are running all over the place from the drug lords who are either jailed, dead or MIA and just so we can get to our car.&#8221; And I said, &#8220;You have a dog yourself. Where do you walk it?&#8221; &#8220;We have to drive three-four miles away to a small park, and that&#8217;s what we do.&#8221; So I went out, and I took a walk with them because my producers told me to. And we went outside, and I took the fastest walk of my life. And as we were coming around and we were being filmed, of course, the producers were in a car and I was on the sidewalk or whatever was out there, I noticed the dogs coming. They were about three blocks away, totally freaked me out.</p><p end="5999" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="5938">And I realized, wow, let&#8217;s break into a run. You&#8217;re walking so well. Let&#8217;s run. And so we did, and I ran for my life. I suddenly realized as we sat in there, as they ran into the house, and the kids were crying by this time because they were scared, they said,</p><p end="5999" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="5938">&#8220;Where&#8217;s the cookies?&#8221; It feels good. And the grandmother looking at me, saying, &#8220;No,</p><p end="5999" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="5938">we just learned something different. Let&#8217;s just pray.&#8221; And I looked around and I said,</p><p end="5999" is_meta="false" speaker="Dr. Pamela Peeke" start="5938">wow, obesity is the government&#8217;s business because it&#8217;s not really obesity, really, at the end of the day. Wow, health, the fitness to be able to live and survive -- that&#8217;s really what it&#8217;s about.</p></transcript></debate>