<debate duration="6498" url="https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/policing-racially-biased"><speakers><speaker name="Gloria Browne-Marshall" position="for"><description>Associate Professor of Constitutional Law, John Jay College of Criminal Justice &amp; Former Civil Rights Attorney</description><bio>Gloria J. Browne-Marshall is an associate professor of constitutional law at John Jay College (CUNY), a legal correspondent and a civil-rights... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Marq Claxton" position="for"><description>Black Law Enforcement Alliance &amp; Retired NYPD Detective</description><bio>Marquez (Marq) Claxton is currently the director of public relations and political affairs for the Black Law Enforcement Alliance. Marq is a retired... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Heather Mac Donald" position="against"><description>Thomas W. Smith Fellow, Manhattan Institute &amp; Author, The War on Cops</description><bio>Heather Mac Donald is the Thomas W. Smith Fellow at the Manhattan Institute and a contributing editor of City Journal. Mac Donald&#8217;s work at... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Harry Stern" position="against"><description>Attorney, Rains Lucia Stern &amp; Former Police Officer</description><bio>Harry S. Stern is the managing principal for Rains Lucia Stern, a law firm focused on civil litigation and criminal defense. Stern has successfully... Read More</bio></speaker></speakers><results><result against="16" for="57" submitters="live" undecided="27" when="before" /><result against="28" for="60" submitters="live" undecided="12" when="after" /><result against="37" for="39" submitters="online" undecided="20" when="before" /><result against="61" for="32" submitters="online" undecided="3" when="after" /></results><transcript><p end="557" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="499">I'd like to say that there are branches on the same tree of justice, so I don't choose one, they're all branches on the same tree.</p><p end="557" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="499">My partner is Marq "tear 'em up" Claxton.</p><p end="557" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="499">Thank you. Thank you.</p><p end="619" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="557">Yeah, I think it's unavoidable, when you're exposed to so much negativity throughout the course of a career. It's unavoidable, you're going to some scar tissue. But I like to think that as a result of my experience in the police force, that I have the, you know, increased sense of compassion, and understanding, and sensitivity to some of the issues that people face.</p><p end="619" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Mac Donald" start="557">Hi, John.</p><p end="619" is_meta="true" speaker="Heather Mac Donald" start="557">Applause</p><p end="679" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Mac Donald" start="619">Oh --</p><p end="679" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Mac Donald" start="619">I do -- I like to be called that than some of the other names --</p><p end="679" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Mac Donald" start="619">-- I'm called, but --</p><p end="679" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Mac Donald" start="619">Well, I lived through the transformation of New York from a symbol of urban dysfunction to a hipster mecca and family-friendly tourist destination. It was impossible not to become interested in policing, since it drove that change.</p><p end="679" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Mac Donald" start="619">The courtroom whiz kid, Harry Stern.</p><p end="801" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="738">Thank you. I really want to start out really quickly by offering my condolences and recognizing the severe loss that we had in the law enforcement community, the death of the legend, the hero, NYPD detective Steven Mac Donald.</p><p end="865" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="801">And I wanted to start off by doing that and acknowledge his loss -- tremendous loss to this city.</p><p end="865" is_meta="true" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="801">Applause</p><p end="865" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="801">All right. No clapping. Don't take away my time now.</p><p end="865" is_meta="true" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="801">Laughter</p><p end="865" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="801">I want to start off because we were talking about bias here. It's clear -- I think we have to get a better understanding about what it is specifically. What is bias? And I know we're talking about policing and racially biased, so, I took it upon myself to bring out some definitions for us to go over. So, if you don't mind, I'd like to start off by reading Merriam-Webster's definition of bias. Included in that definition is a bent, tendency, an inclination, or temperament, or outlook -- especially a personal and sometimes unreasoned judgment. That's bias. I also refer to the Black Law Dictionary. The Black's Law Dictionary has "bias" listed as "inclination, a bent, a prepossession, a preconceived notion or predisposition to decide a cause or an issue in a certain way.&#8221;</p><p end="928" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="865">Most importantly, I want this last line in Black's definition is, "This term is not synonymous with prejudice." I want us to remember that as we vote on this motion. And you should be voting yes on the motion. But remember, this term is not synonymous with prejudice. I suspect that through the course of this evening what you're going to hear is a boatload of statistics, a truckload of data that will attempt to explain what many of us already know. What many of us are already acknowledged and what many of us are working hard to prevent or at least address. And I think we just have to be honest about certain things. When you're talking about police bias, let's just be honest about it because these numbers, this data that I suspect that you'll be hearing this evening, actual bias is not easily quantified.</p><p end="978" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="928">It's hard to really put numbers to specific and detailed bias. Without a historical context, without legal context, it becomes confusing. And that's why I'm honored tonight that Gloria, my debate partner, will be dealing and addressing with some of those historical and legal, contextual issues, because you can't just go nakedly into this conversation and expect to fully grasp and understand it. And if you deny bias and you reject not only your common sense but the experiences of many people like myself, a rejection of bias in policing is intellectually dishonest. And that's why you must vote yes to the question.</p><p end="1038" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="978">You -- if you don't vote yes to the question, what you do is reject the story that I have, the experience that I have - 20 years in the police department in every unit in the police department; plain clothes, narcotics division, uniform patrol, observing what I observed. Or, perhaps, my personal experiences, being -- just shortly before going into the police academy, being stopped on Springfield Boulevard into a checkpoint along with five other vehicles. There's five other black men, and we were all tossed out of our cars, many of us physically. I was thrown across the trunk of my car onto the street. It was later explained to me that I was stopped because they were looking for a black man in a dark car. That was one week before the academy. Or, maybe perhaps, the experience that my own son had 23 years later, less than a mile from the same location than it occurred with me. Or, maybe, less innocuous is this, if you remember. This is going to give you an example of bias.</p><p end="1098" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="1038">In 2003, there was, in the Prospect Park, the Philharmonic was playing. 2003, let me remind you, was a time when there was a severe and heavy crackdown -- zero tolerance in the communities of color across this -- across the city. No tolerance for drinking in public, no tolerance for loitering, no tolerance for this. Absolutely zero tolerance, yet, still Mayor Bloomberg -- then Mayor Bloomberg sat in Prospect Park drinking his wine, laying out on a blanket, being offered all types of alcohol. He said, "Well, these people are different. There's not a problem with this. So, the police enforcement isn't necessary." The police did nothing to those large crowds of wine and cheese drinkers in Prospect Park, so much to the point where I went the next week to Bryant Park with my little blanket and my wine and my cheese, and I drank very well.</p><p end="1098" is_meta="true" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="1038">Laughter</p><p end="1098" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="1038">Bias, no enforcement. Finally, I want to say -- and I wanted to go into a "stop and frisk" data and information. I don't think I'll have an opportunity to.</p><p end="1159" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="1098">But I wanted to tell you that the other victims of bias policing are those hard-working, diligent, dedicated law enforcement professionals who because of biased policing are put in positions and given quotas and false productivity standards which place them in harm's way because they have increased contact and increased liability. It is not the everyday police officer who sets the tone and determines the level of bias in policing right now. It is the system, which I'm sure Professor Marshall will be going into historical context again -- it is the system that places not only a certain population of citizens, but our police officers, in increased harm's way. Vote yes for the truth. Vote yes on the motion.</p><p end="1651" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="1578">Policing is racially biased. We're not saying that every police officer operates with racial animus. We're saying, generally, policing is racially biased and we support the motion with law, history, and practice. With law. Well, this city -- New York City, was sued by Mr. Floyd, and in 2013 the federal court said policing in New York City is racially biased, as well as the Justice Department of the United States said there were small, as well as large, police departments across the country and are finding that policing is racially biased. The United Nations said in 2013 in its report by the Human Rights Commission, policing is racially biased. By that point alone, we have won. However, we also need to know this, that the police department made up of people who've joined the police to help others are part of an extension of an American society that has race as that original sin.</p><p end="1699" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="1651">I'm going to go through 400 years of history in a minute and a half.</p><p end="1699" is_meta="true" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="1651">Laughter</p><p end="1699" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="1651">Four hundred years of history, a minute and a half. 1607, Jamestown colony is founded in Virginia. 1619, 20 Africans arrive in that colony. 1620, the Mayflower lands. We were here before the Mayflower. In the 1600s, you had hard-working people of African descent following the law, but then the laws changed, didn't they? And subjected them to chain slavery. Subjected to chain slavery and freedom becomes a crime, but then slavery is the law. Who enforces slavery? Militias, small groups, slave catchers.</p><p end="1822" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="1699">In our society, it's not the bobbies of London that start the police force. It is the slave patrols from which our police force then is founded. Those slave patrols, the bounty hunters whose job it is to go find those runaway slaves and bring them back. 1865, the 13th Amendment abolishes slavery, but read your Constitution. Slavery is abolished except as punishment for a crime. The words are there. Slavery is abolished except as punishment for a crime. So, what happens between 1865 and World War II? The convict lease system. Criminal laws are put in place to criminalize black behavior so that they can then be used as laborers, remember the movie "The Shawshank Redemption?" The wardens then lease out the prison laborers. But then how do you get that labor? You create criminal laws that criminalize black behavior.</p><p end="1822" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="1699">You round them up. You do these things, and then you work them -- some of them worked to death. Remember, from 1865 to World War II. Then we have Jim Crow segregation. Who then enforces segregation? The criminal justice system, police officers. Over 4,000 people were lynched in this country, burned alive, castrated, throats cut, tortured. This happened right here in the United States. Was anybody arrested? No. Where were the police officers for African Americans? No people were arrested. And yet, we fight on, believing in our criminal justice system, even though the police officers are protecting those people. There are pictures of those crowds standing there with bodies hanging from trees. Where are the police? Then we get the Civil Rights movement, and there's movement forward. But then, in 1968, the U.S. Supreme Court rules, in Terry v. Ohio, that the police have unprecedented authority to stop and frisk based on reasonable suspicion of imminent danger.</p><p end="1939" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="1822">But now, as we go through time, we find the imminent danger part has dropped away. Police officers are stopping people, but they're stopping mostly brown and black people, until by 2011, we have 600,000 people stopped by police -- nearly 700,000 people -- the majority of whom are black and brown. That's why the Floyd case in 2013 ruled that there was racial profiling practiced in this city. History, practice, law. You will hear that the police officers have no choice but to go to into certain communities based on data. But can't it be both data as well as racial bias? We say that there is both. You can have some data, but there's also racial bias. He said that black people commit more crimes. What kind of crimes?</p><p end="1939" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="1822">How many of you were smoking marijuana, or your friends? That's a crime. How many of you were committing criminal acts, and you know the police wouldn't stop you for it? What kind of crimes? When they talk about African Americans, they want to talk about violent crimes. And then they want to vilify those people who protest against our public servants we pay taxes for, who are abusing our rights. This country was born in protest. The Declaration of Independence was protest. We should not be vilifying those people, those citizens who say, "We want the police to help us, not hurt us." Will someone Christian decide when the anti-Semitism is over? Will a man when decide when there's no more sexism? I don't think so. There is racial bias --</p><p end="1939" is_meta="true" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="1822">Applause</p><p end="1939" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="1822">-- in policing. Vote yes for the motion. Thank you.</p><p end="1939" is_meta="true" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="1822">Applause</p><p end="1958" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Mac Donald" start="1939">Thank you very much. Let me state some core principles. The police have an absolute obligation to treat everyone they encounter with courtesy and respect. Too often, cops develop hardened, obnoxious attitudes towards the public. Second, every police shooting of an innocent civilian is a stomach-churning tragedy. Tactical training has to work incessantly to prevent such calamities. Third, given this country's appalling history of racism, and the use of police brutality to uphold slavery and segregation, police shootings of black men are particularly and understandably fraught. But however tragic the history of policing and race, patterns of policing today do not demonstrate police bias.</p><p end="1958" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Mac Donald" start="1939">Contemporary policing is data driven. In order to save lives, cops go where people are most being victimized, and that is in minority neighborhoods. To understand policing, you first have to look at the facts of crime, however uncomfortable it may be to do so. I'm going to focus on fatal police shootings, because that has been the focus as well of the Black Lives Matter movement. In 2015, cops killed 991 people -- the vast majority, armed and dangerous. 50 percent of the victims of police shootings were white, though you would never know it from the press coverage. Among the white victims of fatal police shootings was a 50-year-old in Tuscaloosa, Alabama in a domestic violence incident, who ran at the officer with a spoon, and a 28-year-old driver in Des Moines, Iowa, who led the police on a car chase and then walked quickly towards the shooting officer.</p><p end="2060" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Mac Donald" start="1958">The team arguing against the motion, Heather MacDonald and Harry Stern, indeed do come up with the argument that data matters a lot. They say that policing is not racially biased, but that it may seem so due to confusion and misconception based on stories and anecdotes that can be powerful but not absolutely comprehensive. They say the reality is that black people commit more crime per capita than other groups; that that's where the crime is, that's where the police go, that's where the incidents happen. They are basically making argument that if you step back and look at the numbers and look at the patterns, it's also true that while some cops may be racist, the system as a whole is not racist. So, we're going to peel back some of these arguments and mix it up and go a little bit deeper on all of these topics. But I want to start by asking the team arguing against the motion to respond to your opponents' laying out the fact that there -- that racial profiling had been established and documented by the Department of Justice.</p><p end="2060" is_meta="false" speaker="Heather Mac Donald" start="1958">The report done on Ferguson, Missouri, a few years ago, was damning in its portrayal of racism in an entire community. They talk about the UN, et cetera. What about those cases as evidence? Where do you -- how do you place those? I'll take it to Heather MacDonald first.</p><p end="2544" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="2478">I am quite sure the police department is not going to go into a meeting and talk about race. They're not saying, we're going to go after the black people. However, in the Floyd case, I was in the federal courtroom --</p><p end="2544" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="2478">The Floyd case was a case that was brought by an individual African-American male who was going into his home and he was arrested by police, racially profiled by police, and he brought a suit. I want you to think about what stop and frisk is. Think about the government touching you, holding you up to ridicule in public, rubbing your legs, your arms, your head, your body, your back, your chest, and then making you stand there, making you lie down on the ground with your face in the -- on the sidewalk or in the dirt.</p><p end="2620" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="2544">That's what racial profiling can lead to in stop and frisk. And that's the power police officers have. I want police officers to be safe. I have friends who are police officers. But there has been abuse. And the Floyd case that was decided in federal court indicated that there was not just based on disproportionality, but based on the facts of the case and the evidence given and a recording of police officers telling other police officers to go to certain communities and, I quote, "Make them understand that community does not belong to them, it belongs to us."</p><p end="2665" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="2620">No.</p><p end="2665" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="2620">Harry Stern</p><p end="2665" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="2620">Racial -- I like him. I'd like you too, but not for the moment.</p><p end="2665" is_meta="true" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="2620">Laughter</p><p end="2665" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="2620">Thank you.</p><p end="2665" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="2620">Harry Stern</p><p end="2665" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="2620">Here's my point: Racial profiling is crappy police work. And here's what I mean by that. I worked -- I had the privilege of working in predominantly black neighborhoods.</p><p end="2730" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="2665">And if I was going to stop every black person that I encountered, not only was it going to be a long and arduous day, I wouldn't get anything accomplished. So, the idea that racially profiling, stopping people just because of their race constitutes good police work is hogwash.</p><p end="2730" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="2665">He's arguing with himself.</p><p end="2730" is_meta="true" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="2665">Laughter</p><p end="2730" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="2665">Look. I agree with my partner. He's arguing with himself.</p><p end="2730" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="2665">I don't think -- one thing that I think we have to do and I attempted to do it in my definitions is really stay as close to the motion as possible, because I fear that if we go deeper into, is policing racist we go in a different area and dimension. We can have that argument. We're prepared to do that, but I think I want to make sure that the audience knows -- the voting audience knows, that, you know, the motion is Policing is racially biased.</p><p end="2844" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="2730">Let's be clear about something. Stop and frisk and I think, you know, was mentioned, referred to the data on stop and frisk specifically here in New York City, the numbers speak unbelievably for themselves and they speak poorly about policing, and I agree with you. You know, racial profiling and policing is crappy police work and that's why it's important for us to understand that in addition to, you know, citizen victims it's the police officer who now has increased liability, more negative contact with people, a lack of confidence. We've lost the faith in cops as have so many people. Why? Because quotas and the quest for data forces police officers to engage in conduct that they normally would not engage in. It's a matter of survival, job survival on many levels, and it's important for us to realize that we expose our brave men and women to increase liability by engaging in racial profiling or biased policing.</p><p end="2844" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="2730">But it was not found that she had any impartiality in that case.</p><p end="2906" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="2844">I'm going to say something that goes back to what Harry mentioned.</p><p end="2906" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="2844">Harry Stern</p><p end="2906" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="2844">You're back on my team?</p><p end="2906" is_meta="true" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="2844">Laughter</p><p end="2906" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="2844">No.</p><p end="2906" is_meta="true" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="2844">Laughter</p><p end="2906" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="2844">You said blacks commit more crimes. How are you defining crime? You've only focused on violent crimes and that's a very small percentage of all crimes.</p><p end="3024" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="2906">When you start talking about burglaries, when you start talking about assaults, when you start thinking about the fact that there are over 300 million people in this country, the majority of whom are white. So, in order for you to be a part of this database, that means that a police officer has to not only encounter you, but decide to arrest you, and what happens is, whites commit more crimes, but they are not arrested in the proportion in which they should be arrested. There are interactions with police officers that take place on a myriad of occasions, but what we have at the same time is that police officer making a judgment call, because policing is very subjective. You're going to decide, &#8220;Do I -- am I going to ruin the future of this teenager whose caught, you know, destroying public property or smoking marijuana in the car?&#8221; And those of you in this room know how many times you should have been arrested as a teen.</p><p end="3024" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="2906">Okay.</p><p end="3024" is_meta="true" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="2906">Laughter</p><p end="3266" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="3149">-- with the opposition.</p><p end="3325" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="3266">All right.</p><p end="3325" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="3266">Okay. John Jay College is located on 59th and 10th Avenue.</p><p end="3446" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="3325">Think about the fact that this used to be Hell's Kitchen and now it's the Lincoln Center area. There is a difference in services provided based on that. When I see young people leaving school, they are rambunctious. They are talking loud, they're having fun, they have all this energy. But then once you put a shade of color on them, it's a difference in policing. When those students are leaving this area in the Upper East Side, rambunctious, loud, using new curse words, yes, they're not seen as a threat. But then you move it to Brooklyn, they are. That's what we're talking about when we're saying racial bias in policing, the difference in what you see, your perception. My other concern is this, when we talk about crime, no one's talking about that white serial killer. No one's talking about that white mass murderer. The person who committed the most murders in this country as one human being, the Green River Killer, who killed over 48 women.</p><p end="3446" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="3325">And he can't remember the other 50.</p><p end="3446" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="3325">Well, one of the things that, you know, Harry and I talk about a little bit beforehand was the data collection. In order to collect the data, whenever there's an encounter with police, then it has to be -- it has to be collected. It has to be written down in some way. So, that means when you have that data with that interaction with the white teenager. My concern is, and it's a concern that Harry raised before. The fear that officers are being used to put people in the system.</p><p end="3505" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="3446">That's a concern both of us share. When you have people of color being put in the system, being labeled in a way, being part of the overall data collection. But if you're encountering the -- making that determination when you encounter a white teenager that you decide to counsel instead of arrest --</p><p end="3505" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="3446">I think they&#8217;re going to have to.</p><p end="3505" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="3446">In order for us to find out who the police is actually interacting with. We -- but I think we're going to have to write it -- and it disturbs me as much as it disturbs other people. But we can't have it only be written down by people -- about people of color because that's then who Heather studies, who is ever in the database. And then she then teases a number from that --</p><p end="3505" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="3446">-- and we leave out all those other white middle class and upper class kids and other individuals who are not part of the study.</p><p end="3564" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="3505">That's not true.</p><p end="3629" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="3564">Well, first, if I can tell you that Heather has really bought the NYPD line hook and sinker, boy. I'll tell you, we're responding to community complaints, et cetera. I think that -- I mean, that sounds great.</p><p end="3629" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="3564">Well, I did it for 20-something years.</p><p end="3629" is_meta="true" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="3564">Laughter</p><p end="3629" is_meta="true" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="3564">Applause</p><p end="3629" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="3564">And I can tell you -- and it sounds good, and I understand why because it just would seem logical that police action would be based on these actual complaints from the ministers and the community, et cetera.</p><p end="3685" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="3629">First off, if you've ever gone in these communities, that ain't a whole lot of people there so you're not getting a lot of information, but --</p><p end="3685" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="3629">Let me just say this, you will find crime where you look for it. If you look for it there, you will find it. And if you collect databased on the decision that you made, the subjective decision that you made to look for it there, not based on community concerns or some old lady said this, or some, you know, person said that. It's not about that at all. But where you decided to consciously look for it and execute this new enforcement action, you're going to find crime there.</p><p end="3685" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="3629">And it point where the shot came from.</p><p end="3745" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="3685">But, Heather, hear me.</p><p end="3745" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="3685">Just to that point specifically --</p><p end="3745" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="3685">Here's a classic example of what I just said. You only get shot -- shot -- what's the name of this silly system?</p><p end="3745" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="3685">-- Shot Spotter information from locations you put the Shot Spotter equipment in.</p><p end="3745" is_meta="true" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="3685">Laughter</p><p end="3745" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="3685">And all of those locations --</p><p end="3745" is_meta="true" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="3685">Applause</p><p end="3745" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="3685">-- all of them are in black communities, all of them. Am I right, Heather?</p><p end="3806" is_meta="false" speaker="Harry Stern" start="3745">Well, let me -- let me explain.</p><p end="3806" is_meta="false" speaker="Harry Stern" start="3745">Because violent crime is what matters, and violent crime -- there are no reasonable policy debates of whether or not we should respond to armed robberies or whether there's a difference between homicide reporting and investigation in the suburbs or in the city, okay? So, those are the things that aren't subjective. They're a hundred percent objective. On the fringes are drug crimes and quality of life crimes. But here's where those two things come together, okay.</p><p end="3867" is_meta="false" speaker="Harry Stern" start="3806">The broken window theory, the stop and risk -- the stop and frisk -- Marq would call it "stop and risk" -- theory of fighting crime goes something like this, in order to combat the violence that no reasonable person is going to argue is a good thing. Nobody's out there saying we&#8217;d like more homicides in our neighborhood. We want more holdups. In order to combat those things, you go after quality of life crimes. So, without one, there's the -- there's not the other. And that's a perfectly rational police response to an outcry from a community. And frankly, it works.</p><p end="3924" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="3867">White men and white-on-white crime is something that has not been studied and should be studied, because white men and other people within their ethnic group kill or hurt within their ethnic group. Whites hurt whites. Blacks hurt blacks, et cetera. Latinos, Asians, et cetera. You hurt what's in your ethnic group. Rape within your ethnic group. We have not talked at all about the number of people harmed by white men who commit mass murders. When a white male walks into a school and kills children it's not a white male who's done it, it's a disturbed young male. When a white man --</p><p end="3924" is_meta="true" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="3867">Applause</p><p end="3924" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="3867">So, when we start talking about how can we save lives, this nation has now been known as a nation of mass murderers.</p><p end="3985" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="3924">And those mass murderers --</p><p end="3985" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="3924">-- are 99 percent white men.</p><p end="3985" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="3924">Okay.</p><p end="3985" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="3924">Well, I would say that there are black victims who want police to come and they want justice. So, we concede that point when it comes to the fact that there's harm within the black communities. Unfortunately, what about the little old lady who lived down the street whose grandson is stopped five times because he fits the description of young and black in Brownsville? And Heather refers to this as the crime tax. Well, that's the tax you pay for living in a high-crime neighborhood that you don't have the same rights, you don't get the same protections.</p><p end="4044" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="3985">You don't get the same courtesy as people who live in other communities because you happen to live in a neighborhood where there are murders that take place like Brownsville. So, when we talk about, you know, racial bias, which is the topic here on the table and Marq has gone back to this many times, policing is racially biased, does that mean that, based on where people can live if crime has taken place in that neighborhood, and I say this one more time, when we look at the upper east side or the upper west side and the types of crimes that take place in this neighborhood that are not reported, since police are not focused on those areas, you're not going to have the same people subjected to the same type of harassment that takes place in these other communities.</p><p end="4044" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="3985">That's not true.</p><p end="4044" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="3985">That is not true.</p><p end="4104" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="4044">Yes.</p><p end="4166" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="4104">The New York State attorney general's report on stop and frisk found that of all those stopped, black and brown people, 70 percent African American, a very high percentage of Latinos, it was on white people stopped. A very small percentage of white people stopped that they found the guns.</p><p end="4230" is_meta="false" speaker="Harry Stern" start="4166">Howdy.</p><p end="4292" is_meta="false" speaker="Harry Stern" start="4230">Yes.</p><p end="4349" is_meta="false" speaker="Harry Stern" start="4292">Sure. Let me try and answer that. Thank you for the question. So, now am I going to hearken back to my vast knowledge of police work. And I was a warrior on the crack wars. I started police work in the late '80s, and here was the driving force, though. It was violence. So, nobody cares if some chubby guy with long hair is smoking weed, and watching cartoons, and eating Twinkies in his apartment. That's not a public safety issue. His parents aren't happy, but he's not causing violence in the community.</p><p end="4408" is_meta="false" speaker="Harry Stern" start="4349">When I worked in narcotics -- primarily focused on crack, because that's what we were dealing with -- it wasn't the idea that people were smoking crack and ruining their lives, it was the violence that was attendant. And we were responding directly to the outcry from the community, "Get the dope dealers off the streets. Stop the drive-by shootings. Make our neighborhood safe again."</p><p end="4408" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="4349">May I --</p><p end="4408" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="4349">And I --</p><p end="4408" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="4349">And that fits into the issue of the system and how you have the racial system and the racial -- the bias in the racial -- in the system, in that you have different policies for different people. So, when it's crack cocaine, you have a policy of arrest. When it's powder cocaine, you have a policy of counseling. And at this point, we're dealing with a heroin epidemic.</p><p end="4469" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="4408">And it's now getting so bad -- it's gotten so bad that it's made the news -- New York Times articles, et cetera. Let me just point to one thing. Here's where the violence comes in. You have to feed that $100, $200, $300 a day habit, so you have breaking and entering. You have burglaries. And that's why I say, when we talk about crime, why is it that you only look at certain crimes? You're not looking at these types of crimes. You're not looking at the fact that crystal meth is an epidemic in rural communities, mostly white people -- but you don't hear that much about it. Suburban communities, wealthy communities are dealing with this, and they're saying counseling. Now they're saying, "Don't even arrest these people." As far as I know, possession of heroin is a crime. And yet, counseling, not criminality is the point when those people are being arrested.</p><p end="4598" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="4532">I [unintelligible] you're making that up.</p><p end="4598" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="4532">I think that's a very good question. There was an article last year that there has been a slight increase in the number of whites arrested. When we started looking -- and I know Heather doesn't like disproportionality, but when we start thinking about crimes and certain crimes committed by certain people at certain times, when we start looking at the reasonableness of crime and whether or not a person is arrested for what it is they're doing, the United States has 5 percent of the world's population and over 20 percent of those incarcerated.</p><p end="4649" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="4598">The whole incarceration rate needs to come down, but at the same time we need to look at, are people who are committing the crimes actually getting arrested. When we start seeing in line not just these murder crimes, but all crimes across the board. Whites use drugs more than blacks yet the arrest rate for blacks is higher. That's what we're talking about. When you start talking about people getting arrested for doing the same thing other people are doing, if that starts going down, then I think that we're looking at a less racial bias in criminal justice and policing.</p><p end="4649" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="4598">You're not just a citizen.</p><p end="4649" is_meta="true" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="4598">Laughter</p><p end="4709" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="4649">But you did say that we said that blacks commit more crimes?</p><p end="4778" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="4709">Yes.</p><p end="4778" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="4709">Harry Stern</p><p end="4778" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="4709">We seem so negative.</p><p end="4891" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="4778">Yeah. Just briefly. I think we're going to need a fact checker year.</p><p end="4891" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="4778">Yeah, a fact checker!</p><p end="4891" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="4778">But the fact of the matter -- I think -- I mean, I -- I disagree. I disagree with what you've asserted here. I've just -- I've never seen any of that data that you mentioned.</p><p end="4891" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="4778">I know Center for Police Equity.</p><p end="4891" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="4778">You want to get an idea about bias? Just think to yourself how many times have you been walking down a street and then a young black man that walked up -- walking behind you, and you feel less safe, or you cross the street? How many times do you decide to be at the ATM and a young black guy comes, or an old black guy for that matter, and you just feel a little funny. How many times has that happened to you? So less than a -- these studies that you mention, I've never heard of. I find them to be counterintuitive. I'm not doubting you now, Heather, because I respect you. But for me, this is difficult to understand that type of data. So I --</p><p end="4891" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="4778">The --</p><p end="4891" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="4778">I would like to see the studies because I saw an interview Heather did, and none of these studies were mentioned.</p><p end="4957" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="4891">So, maybe this is something you just recently learned about --</p><p end="4957" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="4891">Harry Stern</p><p end="4957" is_meta="true" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="4891">unintelligible</p><p end="4957" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="4891">-- but you know, I want to stay with policing is racially biased, and this is not, let's cut up Heather, because that's not what I want it to be about. But it's -- you know, this pulling things out of the air. But that's -- but here is the -- but --</p><p end="4957" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="4891">And I -- but no, I'm just -- that's why I said I don't want this to be about &#8211;</p><p end="4957" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="4891">No, this is not the Heather -- this is not the Heather show, and I'm not trying to make this about undermining Heather. That's not -- I want to go back to policing is racially biased and what Marq just said. This has happened not just for the young black person walking to the ATM. This happens to me walking to the ATM. This happens to me being stopped. No one sees when I'm walking or driving around that I'm a professor at a college, you know, and I write books.</p><p end="5070" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="4957">What they see is the color of the skin. And decisions are made based on that. So, it goes back to that point of policing is racially biased when we are talking about how people make their decisions. We have to consider, based on our history, based on what we've learned over time, we think some people are more criminal than other people. And, you know, and what Heather is saying, it's not about where the color is, it's where the crime is.</p><p end="5070" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="4957">Nonviolent is the question.</p><p end="5196" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="5132">The school to prison pipeline, as pointed out, means that in the third-grade certain tests are given and if students do poorly on these tests because they haven't been taught well how to read and write, et cetera, then there's a decision made by certain corporations for private prisons and most state prisons have private prison parts to them, that they are going to be in adult prisons by the time they reach 18.</p><p end="5311" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="5196">And that's why they call it the school to prison pipeline. That they're going to lose interest in school because they can't read properly and that they're going to get in trouble and end up in juvenile detention and then into adult prisons. They actually base the number of beds in adult prisons on how many children are failing their tests in the third and fourth grades. We have inadequate schooling, but that's not on the table today. That's also leading to some of the criminal behavior. We have inadequate summer programs so that students can get in trouble when they're young and they have lots of energy. And all of these things are leading to it. We also had passed -- have recently passed in Missouri a law that allows primary school children to be handcuffed, where in most of the country we have public schools that are going to be majority minority schools. So, you're seeing a policy in which people believe that African Americans can take it. Young people can take more criminal punishment because they're just built that way.</p><p end="5311" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="5196">And so, that sense of the school to prison pipeline is also part of the system of criminalizing black and brown people so that we end up with not a sense of fairness, but a sense that they were built with latent criminality and therefore it's not racial bias, it&#8217;s data.</p><p end="5311" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="5196">The bias policing and the prison industrial complex.</p><p end="5311" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="5196">The prison industrial complex --</p><p end="5311" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="5196">Well, I'm smart.</p><p end="5375" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="5311">Well, biased policing contributes to this prison industrial complex, you see, and it kind of correlates to what Gloria mentioned earlier about the school to prison pipeline. You see, if you prime people and you prepare them they go through stages. If you can get them accustomed to being, you know, increased police contact, et cetera, then they become primed for criminal -- criminality later on, or at least they're in somebody's database. So, biased policing, basically, is the methodology to get people into this prison pipeline to criminalize perhaps large segments of our society, black and brown people. It goes hand in hand. It is one.</p><p end="5375" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="5311">Well, it also --</p><p end="5375" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="5311">-- prison industrial complex --</p><p end="5494" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="5375">As someone who's lost a family member to gun violence, I don't take gun violence lightly. So, when we're having this conversation, this is very real to me. But I also understand something as a civil rights attorney. I understand that there is a difference in the way people are treated. What we have on the table today: Policing is racially biased. It doesn't mean that there are not black victims. There are. I know them. But what it does mean is that we have a system that's in place, historically, that has looked at black people based on a criminality that does not exist to the extent of which the other side is presenting it.</p><p end="5560" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="5494">And it's allowing police officers to extend their power well beyond what is needed. I think that it's unfair to the black community. We want to have police protection. Please understand that. But if you come to help us and end up hurting us, then we fear the police.</p><p end="5560" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="5494">Thank you. And thank you for the opportunity to participate in this debate. Once again, I have to remind people that we're not debating "Is policing racist, is policing" -- anything other than racially biased.</p><p end="5672" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="5560">And I read the definitions earlier. It's important, as you vote -- and as you vote yes -- that you keep in mind that we're voting on police being racially biased. And I think we have to be honest about certain things, and we have to acknowledge and accept our own biases, in whatever form they are. Each and every one of us has -- in this audience right now -- has a bias, some sort of bias. So, it would be really just counterintuitive to assume that there is no bias in this large legal structure called policing. But I warn you -- and I encourage you to avoid being swooned by a lot of -- as I said, a truckload of data, a lot of 1 percent, and 3 percent, and 5 percent -- makes your eyes roll up in your head. I warn you not to use data as the rationale for accepting that policing is not racially biased.</p><p end="5672" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="5560">I believe that we should use statistics and data -- and Mark Twain, I believe, said this -- we should use statistics and data as a drunk uses a light pole -- for support and not illumination.</p><p end="5672" is_meta="true" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="5560">Laughter</p><p end="5672" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="5560">If you are looking for these answers based on statistics, and all of these conflicting data and sheets and -- you're going to be really lost in the sauce. It's important for us. Data also is important -- can be racially biased. It is us. We input the data into those machines. Heather spoke about comp-stat being a vitally important legal tool, a crime fighting tool. Well, guess who inputs the data into the comp-stat machines? Individuals who carry with them a certain bias, along with the systemic bias of the structure of policing.</p><p end="5732" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="5672">Policing --</p><p end="5732" is_meta="false" speaker="Marq Claxton" start="5672">Vote yes.</p><p end="5854" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="5732">Thank you, Harry, for voting for our side.</p><p end="5854" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="5732">Harry Stern</p><p end="5854" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="5732">I do vote, actually, for my side.</p><p end="5854" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="5732">Policing is racially biased. White people overall commit more crimes. The other side has pointed to certain very specific areas in which there is a spike in black crime.</p><p end="5975" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="5854">But overall, whites in America commit more crimes because there are more white people in this country. So, if you still don't believe it, I want to tell you this. And this is from a quote from John Ehrlichman who was the adviser to Richard Nixon in 1968. He said, and I quote, "You understand what I'm saying. We couldn't make it illegal to be either against the war or black. But by getting the public to associate the hippies with marijuana and blacks with heroin and then criminalizing both heavily, we could disrupt those communities," Ehrlichman said. "We could arrest their leaders, raid their homes, break up their meetings and vilify them night after night on the evening news. Did we know we were lying about the drugs? Of course, we did," end quote. So, don't be so alarmed. Not only has history, law, and practice shown that race is a part of our policing and that policing is racially biased.</p><p end="5975" is_meta="false" speaker="Gloria Browne-Marshall" start="5854">The media has fed to us since 1968, at the end of the civil rights movement, the vilification of blacks to make it appear as though we were the only criminals out there, so that when people say, "Blacks commit more crimes," so many folks want to believe it. And police policy is then driven by that. Funding is then given for it, and then we end up in 2017, as was pointed out, trying to figure out how we deescalate this situation. Policing is racially biased. We could all, based on being here today, do our part about it. Thank you.</p></transcript></debate>