<debate duration="6576" url="https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/ration-end-life-care"><speakers><speaker name="Dr. Art Kellermann" position="for"><description>Chair in Policy Analysis, RAND Health</description><bio>Art Kellermann holds the Paul O'Neill Alcoa Chair in Policy Analysis at the RAND Corporation. Before joining RAND, he was a Professor of emergency... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Peter Singer" position="for"><description>Philosopher &amp; Professor of Bioethics, Princeton University</description><bio>Peter Singer is the Ira W. DeCamp Professor of Bioethics in the University Center for Human Values at Princeton University. He specializes in applied... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Sally C. Pipes" position="against"><description>President and Chief Executive Officer of the Pacific Research Institute</description><bio>Sally C. Pipes is President and Chief Executive Officer of the Pacific Research Institute (PRI), a San Francisco-based think tank founded in 1979... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Ken Connor" position="against"><description>Chairman, Center for a Just Society</description><bio>In 2005, Ken Connor founded the Center for a Just Society, where he serves as the organization&#146;s Chairman. Connor is affiliated with the law firm... Read More</bio></speaker></speakers><results><result against="20" for="43" submitters="live" undecided="37" when="before" /><result against="12" for="82" submitters="live" undecided="6" when="after" /><result submitters="online" when="before" /><result submitters="online" when="after" /></results><transcript><p end="767" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="712">Well, I think that's not the business of physicians. I think they can judge. There are ways of judging quality of life and life expectancy, but moral character is something different. It's too subjective, I think. I wouldn't like to see it used as a criteria in there.</p><p end="833" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="767">John Donvan All right, Peter Singer. Our motion is this, "Ration end-of-life care," and here to argue against the motion, first, Ken Connor.</p><p end="833" is_meta="true" speaker="Peter Singer" start="767">applause</p><p end="833" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="767">Ken, you are chairman of the Center for a Just Society, and you played a major role in perhaps the most well known case that centered on end-of-life issues, the Terri Schiavo case, in which the nation and the family was divided over the question of whether to remove the feeding tube from a young woman. The governor of Florida was empowered by the law called "Terri's Law" to become involved in that. What was your involvement in that story?</p><p end="833" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="767">I represented the governor in defending Terri's Law.</p><p end="833" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="767">John Donvan</p><p end="833" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="767">And the fact that in the end your side lost?</p><p end="833" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="767">Terri's Law, was struck down by the Florida Supreme Court, and Terry was ordered to die by starvation and dehydration. She did so over a 13-day period. If the court had ordered that of Ted Bundy, it would have been deemed to be cruel and unusual punishment, but that's precisely what it was.</p><p end="1918" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="1849">Thank you very much. It's the position of our side that we are already rationing health care, so in a sense we can't really debate whether we should do so. The question that we can discuss is whether we should be open and explicit about what we're doing, and,</p><p end="1918" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="1849">therefore, try to do it in the best, most thought-out way possible, which essentially means, "Do it in the way that gets the best value for the health dollars that we're spending now," or whether we should continue to do it in a way that we don't bring out in the open so we cover up, that we don't really dare to discuss.</p><p end="1981" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="1918">And we can see that politically it's not really a topic that people dare to discuss openly,</p><p end="1981" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="1918">and as a result, more people will die who could be saved than will die if we use the money we're spending effectively.</p><p end="1981" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="1918">Now, it's clear that we are not spending our health dollars effectively in this country at present. We spend about between 17 to 18 percent of everything we have, of our gross national product, on health care. That's about 50 percent more than other comparable countries, the other industrialized countries that we compare ourselves with. There is no evidence, no evidence that we get any better outcomes for the extra 50 percent that we're spending, the extra 7 or 8 percent of GDP that we're spending, than those other countries.</p><p end="2027" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="1981">And Dr. Kellermann will give you a more detailed rebuttal to what Sally Pipes just said when she specifically focused on cancer in those remarks. When we looked at not just what the health system does &#8211; but at health outcomes in America, we're actually terrible. It's the combination of what the health system does and our general health.</p><p end="2027" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="1981">We rank in terms of health outcomes somewhere around the level of countries like Slovenia and Costa Rica. They are countries that are much poorer than we are, and yet their health outcomes are comparable to ours. And the other industrialized nations have better health outcomes, including, incidentally, Canada.</p><p end="2097" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="2027">It's also true -- it's also true that when you ask Canadians, as Gallop did a couple of years ago, and Americans, and Britons, people in the U.K., do they have confidence in their health care system, the Britons and the Canadians, 73 percent of them, just coincidentally the same number, say, "Yes," they do. When you asked Americans, only 56 percent of them say they do. I think that there's a general feeling that this health care system is not delivering what we want. But as I said it is rationing. It rations in many ways. For example, we about 44 million people, Americans, now, who are not insured at all. That number will drop significantly when Obama Care comes into effect,</p><p end="2097" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="2027">but it will not unfortunately drop to zero. Now, not being insured means that you are more likely to die if you have a serious illness or accident. In fact, Joseph Doyle, a MIT scientist, looked at people who were brought into emergency care as a result of road accidents, seriously injured.</p><p end="2154" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="2097">And found that those who were uninsured died at a higher rate even when adjusting for other variables than those who had insurance. And when he calculated how much it would have cost to save these people's lives, it would have been about $280,000.</p><p end="2154" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="2097">Reasonable amount of money. But that was how much more was spent on saving the lives of the others. But given that these were mostly fairly young people, in terms of how much it would have cost to extend their lives for one year, it would be about $5,500. These people's lives were lost because we were not prepared $5,500 for each year of life that we could have saved. Compare that with the amount that those much criticized bodies Sally Pipes mentioned NICE, the National Institute for Clinical Excellence in the United Kingdom.</p><p end="2212" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="2154">What they say is too much to spend. Apparently, NICE&#8217;s figure is around $49,000. In other words, almost 10 times, nine times as much as would have saved the lives of these young accident victims. And of course, we ration in a lot of other ways as well, because some people can't afford copayments. We have long waiting times. We don't pay doctors enough for Medicare, and so they don't take Medicare patients, or they don't take so many Medicare patients. So we are losing lives, and we're losing lives that we could save quite cheaply.</p><p end="2212" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="2154">So I think we ought to be more explicit about this. We ought to be prepared to say,</p><p end="2212" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="2154">"Let's use the dollars --" maybe we should spend more dollars. I'm not necessarily opposed to spending more dollars. But let's use the dollars we spend in the most effective way in order to save the greatest number of lives.</p><p end="2267" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="2212">Something has to be done, because health care costs are rising here much faster than the economy is growing. They're rising at 9.8 percent per annum. We all know the economy is not growing at anything like that amount. So as that keeps happening,</p><p end="2267" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="2212">what's going to happen? It will eventually soak up all available spending. But we know the government has to spend on other things. On the [Intelligence Squared] website, in the articles that were posted. There's a very moving piece by Ken Connor about the plight of elderly citizens in our country, how they are neglected, and how because of the demographic changes, there's going to be more of them. Effectively, we need to spend a lot more to give our senior citizens a comfortable and dignified life when they can no longer look after themselves. That costs money, and it's going to cost more money.</p><p end="2334" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="2267">We cannot increase health care spending indefinitely and also spend more on the elderly and spend more on the environment, on education, on all of the other important things that we need. So, like it nor not, we are rationing health care. We are arguing that, indeed, we should. That's obvious. But whether we should be more explicit about it, because we want to get the best results we can. We want to save the most number of lives that we can. And the way to do that is to be explicit and vote yes for this motion. We should be rationing health care. Thank you.</p><p end="2334" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="2267">John Donvan Thank you, Pete Singer.</p><p end="2334" is_meta="true" speaker="Peter Singer" start="2267">applause</p><p end="2334" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="2267">And our final debater will be speaking against this motion. It's Ken Connor. Ken is chairman and founder of the Center for a Just Society. He is a successful trial lawyer.</p><p end="2334" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="2267">He represented Governor Jeb Bush in the long-running Terri Shiavo case, and for several years served as president of the Family Research Council. Ladies and gentlemen,</p><p end="2334" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="2267">Ken Connor.</p><p end="2334" is_meta="true" speaker="Peter Singer" start="2267">applause</p><p end="2395" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="2334">Good evening, ladies and gentlemen. Sally Pipes' mother's situation is exhibit "A" for why Americans don't want the government to wind up rationing health care in this country. By contrast, my mom suffered from advanced colon cancer late in life at an older age than Sally's mom. She received aggressive treatment, both surgery and chemotherapy, made a full recovery, and went on to live more than a decade of a good and healthy life, until she finally died at 90 at home in good health in her own bed.Which system would you prefer? Ladies and gentlemen, I'd like to make three points, if I may, about why government should not be in the business of rationing health care.</p><p end="2395" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="2334">First of all, health care decisions should be made at the end of life, just as at any other point in life, at the bedside, by the people involved and who are affected, not by bureaucrats at a remote location.</p><p end="2460" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="2395">Secondly, that rationing is unethical, because it ultimately devalues human life and inevitably winds up punishing the sick and the dying.</p><p end="2460" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="2395">Thirdly rationing is the lazy man's way -- lazy man's attempt to balance the budget. It's easier to balance the budget on the backs of the sick and dying than it is to reform your ways of wasteful spending in government and try to wrench money back from the hands of the special interests at home and abroad. So back to the premises, first of all, that healthcare decisions should be made at the bedside. Americans don't want bureaucratic bean counters in Washington making decisions about what kind of care they're going to wind up receiving at the end of life. Decisions about healthcare and how it ought to be administered and when it ought to be administered ought to be decisions that are made by the patient informed by their doctors and by their families.</p><p end="2511" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="2460">Decisions about what kind of care will be administered at any given time to any given patient should take into account the needs of the patient. In other words, healthcare should be both individualized and particularized to the needs of the given patient. A bureaucrat remote from the bedside, hundreds, perhaps thousands of miles away practicing assembly line medicine simply is not in a position to make those kinds of individualized decisions that are required. These are decisions that have to be based real time, sometimes at 2:00 or 3:00 a.m. in the morning as Dr. Kellermann has pointed out. And it's the people who have their feet on their floor -- on the floor in the hospital and their hands on the patient who ought to be making these decisions.</p><p end="2572" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="2511">There's simply no way that a government functionary practicing assembly line medicine in Washington can make those kinds of decisions. Healthcare requires the fine edge of a scalpel, not the blunt end of an ax. And patients don't want their doctors straight-</p><p end="2572" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="2511">jacketed by some bureaucratic straightjacket fashioned in the federal city. They want decisions made by doctors who are taking their interests into account. They don't some interest that was decided in a smoke-filled room in Washington, in a room that was predominated by lobbyists to be the ones who are making the decisions.And, folks, do we really want the men who are wearing the green eye shades in Washington to be making these kinds of decisions? Should cost be the primary driver of such decision, especially in the zero sum environment that prevails in Washington?</p><p end="2631" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="2572">I would submit to you, ladies and gentlemen, that when the tradeoffs are made, we don't want decisions about healthcare to go by the board in preference to a new start in green energy or some other pie in the sky kind of effort. Now, no one is suggesting for a moment that we should not be good stewards of scarce healthcare resources. We absolutely should be. But rationing is not what we need. It's rational care. We ought to be asking ourselves, is the procedure under consideration necessary for the patient? Is it clinically appropriate? Is the cost reasonable compared to similar services? These are questions that ought to be answered by people with their feet on the ground in the hospital in real time by hospitalization -- hospital utilization committees and not by people who are removed from the bedside.</p><p end="2690" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="2631">Now, folks, make no mistake about it, government rationing represents the first step down the road to the utilitarian philosophy of former Colorado governor Richard Lamb who said, "The elderly have a duty to die and get out of the way." This philosophy sees the elderly and the handicapped as resource hogs whose useful life is over and who now costs more to maintain than they produce. They reject the sanctity of life ethics that has long prevailed in this country, and that maintains that every human life is precious and out to be respected and protected under the law. That view affirms equal protection for all, the old, and the handicapped to the very young and to the very old.</p><p end="2690" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="2631">Instead the quality of life advocates maintain that we should use quality of life calculus and functional capacity studies in deciding who lives and who dies.</p><p end="2749" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="2690">Of course, the elderly and the handicapped who suffer from dementia and disability don't score well using those formulas. And isn't that the point? Ladies and gentlemen,</p><p end="2749" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="2690">what criteria will the all-wise bureaucrats use to pick winners and losers at the end of life?</p><p end="2749" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="2690">Will they be any more successful than they were in picking Solindra and Bright Source and Abound Solar on whom the government squandered billions of dollars? But then again, what does it matter? At the end of life, we're all going to die, right?</p><p end="2749" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="2690">Folks, I would suggest to you that there are many places that we can look to find the savings that we need to provide appropriate care for the sick and for the dying. For heaven's sakes, we spent $4 trillion on the Wall Street bailout to rescue businesses that engaged in profligate spending practices.</p><p end="2812" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="2749">Surely, we can spend the money required to render appropriate healthcare to the sick and the dying. Ladies and gentlemen, I urge you to vote against the proposition because by the time you reach the end of your life, you'll be glad you did. Thank you.</p><p end="2812" is_meta="true" speaker="Ken Connor" start="2749">applause</p><p end="2812" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="2749">John Donvan Thank you, Ken Connor. That concludes round one of this Intelligence Squared U.S.</p><p end="2812" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="2749">debate.</p><p end="2812" is_meta="true" speaker="Ken Connor" start="2749">applause</p><p end="2812" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="2749">John Donvan Now we'll have the debaters address each other directly and also answer questions from me and from you in the audience, we have two teams of two. Arthur Kellermann and Peter Singer are arguing for the motion: "Ration end-of-life care." And we have heard them say basically that we already are rationing, that healthcare is rationed right now by the ability to pay for it by the individual and that it is time to be explicit, to ration in a different way, to step up and admit that's what we're doing and figure out a system for doing it.</p><p end="2881" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="2812">They say that you need to figure out how much saving a life produces in terms of results. You have to compare that to how the resources could be used elsewhere. The team arguing against the motion, Sally Pipes and Ken Connor, argue that rationing end-</p><p end="2881" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="2812">of-life care is the wrong way to balance the budget. They say that it would be falling to government bureaucrats to make intensely personal decisions, that cost should not be the driver of a decision regarding the end of life, and that they depict a future where basically the elderly will be thrown overboard. Now, I notice that the two sides do agree that cost cutting needs to happen, that costs are out of control. They do agree that ideally these decisions will be made at the bedside by doctors and their families. The question is, who ends up controlling where the money comes from. And I want to put to the side arguing in support of rationing end-of-life care, particularly to Peter Singer,</p><p end="2881" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="2812">this basic question: Is there a way actually to arrive at a dollar value for what a few more months of life would be worth to an elderly person versus what it would be worth to a younger person?</p><p end="2928" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="2881">And does that explain whether -- does that price carry over to whether a procedure is worth pursuing or not? Can you put a dollar number on these things?</p><p end="2928" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="2881">It's very difficult to agree on dollar numbers. I mean, healthcare economists try to do it because really what they're doing is they're comparing what you get for your money if you spend it on one thing, let's say saving young people's lives and what you get for your dollar if you spend it on something else, perhaps let's say for cancer where it can only extend life by two or three months at significant expense. And I think what they can clearly say is we get better value in some cases rather than others. We extend lives for longer for the same amount, or we extend lives for an equal amount for less money.</p><p end="2995" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="2928">John Donvan You said in your opening remarks that younger lives are less expensive generally speaking to save than older lives with the outcome of a longer life lived because the person's younger rather than older. Am I reading you correctly?</p><p end="2995" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="2928">Well, I think most of us would agree that it's a greater tragedy if a 20-year-old dies because they're in an accident and didn't have health insurance than if an 85-year-old dies. I think, you know, we would feel that people have lived most of their life, achieved most of what they're going to achieve when they die in their 80s, let's say. It's still sad,</p><p end="2995" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="2928">of course. I know it's sad. But it's a greater tragedy. It's worth spending more to prevent if we can save the life of somebody who still has most of their life in front of them and still has a lot of things that they can achieve.</p><p end="2995" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="2928">John Donvan All right. Sally Pipes I'd like your response to that in light of your saying in your opening remarks that each of us has the right to live as long as we can. Does age come into it?</p><p end="2995" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="2928">Do the young -- do the younger have more of a right to live as long as they can than the older?</p><p end="3112" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="3056">John, I'd like to weigh in against that kind of a calculating.</p><p end="3198" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="3112">Well, let me ask you this point, if I may, you've been an apologist in your book -- in your books for infanticide, making the point that disabled infants who lack rationality or the capacity to grasp that they existed over time or that they lack some form of self consciousness were somehow not persons and could be disposed of, indeed you've gone so far as to make that argument about all newborn infants, maintaining that within a period of, say, 28 days after birth, parents should be able to decide to get rid of them or not.</p><p end="3302" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="3198">Point of order.</p><p end="3302" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="3198">Point of order.</p><p end="3302" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="3198">This is not the topic we're debating tonight, but I'm happy to debate it some other time.</p><p end="3302" is_meta="true" speaker="Peter Singer" start="3198">talking simultaneously</p><p end="3302" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="3198">Well, it is the topic.</p><p end="3302" is_meta="true" speaker="Ken Connor" start="3198">applause</p><p end="3302" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="3198">And here's the point I would make, old people who suffer from dementia often lack self awareness. They often lack the capacity for rationality. They often lack the capacity to grasp the notion that they exist over time. Would you declare them non-persons and say that they are not worthy of protection and preservation, as you have in the case of --</p><p end="3302" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="3198">John Donvan Okay, Art Kellermann, because I'm not hearing them make the argument in thatextreme way, but I want to --</p><p end="3353" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="3302">Exactly my point. And the point is, we're going to use some kind of criteria to decide who lives and who dies. And for instance, if the eminent Dr. Singer were to become the rationer in chief in the next administration, what criteria would he use? Would we look at the elderly, the demented, the disabled and say that their quality of life years don't merit preserving their lives? Would we say that, as in the case of the infants that he's identified, that they are not persons whose lives are worthy of protection and preservation? Ideas have consequences. What we believe determines how we behave,</p><p end="3353" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="3302">and this logic applies at the end of life no less so than at the beginning.</p><p end="3417" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="3353">I would try to look at the number of years that we can expect to extend people's lives for a given number of dollars. I would also try to look at the quality of life as well. Now,</p><p end="3417" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="3353">that certainly may be affected by dementia, but, in addition, especially with older people, I would hope that they would be encouraged to state their own wishes as to what should happen to them if they become demented, or if other things happen to them.</p><p end="3417" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="3353">John Donvan But, Peter, assuming that you're correct, that you're not going to get the job, what body do you see making the decisions?</p><p end="3417" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="3353">So I think, actually, although it's much criticized, I think that the U.K. model of setting up -- they have a National Institute for Clinical Excellence.</p><p end="3468" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="3417">Sally referred to it by its acronym, NICE. Not everybody thinks it's nice. But what they do is, they try to cost the various treatments that are out there, and they try to get expert data on how long those treatments extend life in a variety of different conditions, and they make recommendations. They're not binding, but they make recommendations to the local area health authorities throughout the United Kingdom to suggest that this treatment does give value for the money; you should be providing it.</p><p end="3468" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="3417">But perhaps this treatment for this specific condition is above the bar that we think reasonable, and you may consider not providing that. And the health authorities then reach those decisions.</p><p end="3468" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="3417">John Donvan And how often -- if you happen to know -- how often is there a recommendation not to use a particular intervention or treatment? Is it uncommon, or is it pretty common?</p><p end="3533" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="3468">It's relatively common that there are some treatments for some specific conditions that are considered too expensive to provide. And I think that that's going to be inevitable,because medical technology really has no limits to how much it can cost, and the drug companies can charge more. In fact, drugs are much cheaper in the United Kingdom because the manufacturers know that if they price them very high, they're not going to be recommended by NICE, whereas here they can basically charge whatever they like,</p><p end="3533" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="3468">and they're still going to get users.</p><p end="3533" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="3468">John Donvan Let's hear from your opponent Sally Pipes.</p><p end="3718" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="3657">Well, I think it's important to understand, as a practical matter, the truth of the notion that he who pays the piper gets to call the tune. And so it's a practical matter.</p><p end="3718" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="3657">Whoever's making those payments, in large measure, is going to call the shots.</p><p end="3775" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="3718">What we advocate, though, in contrast to a central bureaucratized, central planning,</p><p end="3775" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="3718">decision making process is that we have consumer-driven decision making, informed by medical advice, mediated by markets. We believe that that system is a better system than the government system. We believe that that system is a better system and that those -- that's a better way to make decisions than relegating it to the people who brought us the bridge to nowhere, Solyndra, the Wall Street bailout. Now, look -- look,</p><p end="3775" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="3718">folks, plain and simple. There's an economic concept that our physician friend may not be aware of. It's called opportunity cost. And -- and your proposition assumes the fallacy of only two alternatives: Either we recoup the money from the sick and dying, or we don't.</p><p end="3828" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="3775">But my point is there are other ways to recoup the money from other areas where we are wasting money. And it's much easier to balance budgets on the back of the sick and dying than to wrench it out of the hands of the special interests in Washington.</p><p end="3828" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="3775">John Donvan Arthur Kellermann.</p><p end="4013" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="3953">Yeah, but we don't support that system. I mean, that's not --</p><p end="4070" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="4013">Well, let me just say, I mean, I've spent most of my life in Australia as you can probably tell from the funny way I speak. And we have universal health coverage, but we also have private insurance. It's not like Canada. You're not out of the Medicare, as we call it. You're not out of that scheme by taking out private insurance. It just gives you, if you want to do that, extra coverage for various things that you can do. So it's an option and--</p><p end="4070" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="4013">John Donvan All right. I don't feel I'm doing a very good job as moderator tonight.</p><p end="4070" is_meta="true" speaker="Peter Singer" start="4013">laughter</p><p end="4070" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="4013">John Donvan I'm sorry. Because I want to shape this back to what we're talking about as a tradeoff of what you get for what you pay, and are you willing to pay it, and is it wrong to deny that payment? And I -- you know, Ken Connor, you actually did put your finger on it when you said that, he who is paying the cost gets to call the tunes on this. And right now we are in a world where Medicare is taking care of an awful lot of people. And it's very expensive. We know a crisis is coming.</p><p end="4136" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="4070">Given where we are on that, their argument that at some point you have to say no, and let's figure out a way to say no, and let's make it fair for everybody, which is the principle of rationing, that if there's not enough of something to go around, you set up a system so that everybody gets an equal shot at it. But everybody doesn't get all of what they want. Just -- just that concept, what do you think of -- what is wrong with that?</p><p end="4136" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="4070">Because I know you think that it's wrong.</p><p end="4136" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="4070">Well, I think you're talking about fundamental fairness here. Let's think of it in these terms: How fair is it when you pay into something all your life, you get to the end of your life, when you really need it, you've been told that you're paying in to receive healthcare, and you get down to the point when you really need it and say -- and the government says, "Sorry, you're going to cost us too much." Isn't there a fundamental fairness issue in that regard? No. We're going to take the money that you paid in over time, over all these years, and we're going to give it to younger people because they don't need as much of it as you do. Isn't that why we paid into it all of our lives? Isn't that -- isn't that part of fundamental fairness, is getting what you pay for?</p><p end="4255" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="4190">No --</p><p end="4255" is_meta="true" speaker="Peter Singer" start="4190">applause</p><p end="4255" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="4190">[talking simultaneously]John Donvan But Peter used the United Kingdom system as an example so I think it&#8217;s on the table --</p><p end="4421" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="4370">Let me ask you this question.</p><p end="4421" is_meta="true" speaker="Ken Connor" start="4370">laughter</p><p end="4421" is_meta="true" speaker="Ken Connor" start="4370">applause</p><p end="4421" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="4370">If I may, you've made the point, and you've written about it, it's a good point, that some 15,000 people die estimated every year because of the lack of insurance coverage.</p><p end="4421" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="4370">Easy. Then probably due to medicine estimates that 100,000 people die a year from medical malpractice. Are you willing to be as aggressive about reforming medical malpractice and ensuring that physicians meet the standard of care for those 100,000 as you are to argue for the 1,000s who don't survive because of a lack of insurance?</p><p end="4793" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="4730">I'm not sure I understood your question fully, and I apologize for that.</p><p end="4793" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="4730">John Donvan Can I restate? You're talking about, are we going to go to a world where -- well, the second scenario you were talking about, are we bound to a world where there are so many sick and elderly people, and we are so unable to pay for it, that people are going to be encouraged to off themselves? That's what you were asking?</p><p end="4855" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="4793">I'll be happy to address that. Historically, in America, we have maintained that humans -</p><p end="4855" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="4793">- you know, it's a self-evident truth that human beings are endowed by their creators with certain inalienable rights, the first of which is the right to life. That right to life has been deemed to be the foundation of all other rights because if you don't preserve it,</p><p end="4855" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="4793">you don't get to enjoy any of the others. Now, I fear that rationing opens the door to euthanasia because decisions are made on a utilitarian basis about who lives and who dies. And that's the reason I injected the issue on the front end of this debate about personhood.</p><p end="4915" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="4855">Because Dr. Singer has maintained that if you lack certain qualities, rationality, the capacity to reflect on your own existence, self-awareness, you're not a person. And he makes the point that if you're not a person, then it is not as morally culpable to destroy that entity than it otherwise would be for --</p><p end="4915" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="4855">John Donvan But Ken, he's not -- he's not making that argument.</p><p end="4915" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="4855">Well, my point ultimately goes to this: Is that when we use these utilitarian criterion to decide who lives and who dies effectively, we wind up redefining who a person is and --</p><p end="4915" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="4855">and that gives rise to a potential license to kill which invites euthanasia.</p><p end="4915" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="4855">John Donvan Peter Singer.</p><p end="4915" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="4855">Well, if I can comment on that, I think what we are increasingly finding, and we will in the future, if you're looking to the future, is that more people want to have the right to make their own decisions about when they die, about when they've had enough.</p><p end="4978" is_meta="true" speaker="Peter Singer" start="4915">applause</p><p end="4978" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="4915">At the moment, people generally can say, "I don't want any more treatment." But if there isn't treatment that's keeping them alive, they don't have that choice. Now the citizens of Oregon, the citizens of Washington state, have voted in favor of having that right, at least to get a physician to prescribe the medicine that they know will be lethal that can end their life. The courts in Montana have said that citizens there have that right as well. There are several nations in Europe that allow that and also allow -- some of them allow a doctor to give a lethal injection as well on the request of the patient,</p><p end="4978" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="4915">satisfying certain conditions like a second opinion. Those countries are satisfied with that. In the Netherlands, for example, that's been the case for at least 20 years now.</p><p end="4978" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="4915">And through different governments, through liberal governments, through conservative governments, through a Catholic prime minister who never tried to repeal that law because he knew it was too popular and would be political suicide if he did.</p><p end="5031" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="4978">So I think that that is actually something that probably is increasingly going to happen as people start to see that this is something that they want for themselves. But that's a matter of choice. That's not a matter of rationing.</p><p end="5031" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="4978">John Donvan I want to remind you that we are in the question-and-answer section of this Intelligence Squared U.S. debate. I'm John Donvan. We have four debaters, two teams of two, who are debating this motion: Ration end-of-life care. Peter Singer, I had the sense that Ken Connor's point wasn't about voluntary euthanasia, and I think the question was also about a culture in which euthanasia becomes a suggestion overhanging the elderly as they become more and more in number and as they become more difficult to take care of, that this sort of -- I think the question is, will we get to a world once we open the world to explicit rationing where an old person will know that it's time to get on the ice flow and get the pushout.</p><p end="5093" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="5031">No, I don't believe so. I think there's still going to be the possibility of choosing,</p><p end="5093" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="5031">providing, of course, as you're saying, that you're not imposing a huge burden on other people by opting for something very expensive and of doubtful benefits. So there are going to be limits there. But I think otherwise people are going to be able to make their choices in accordance with their own values, and there will be some people who'll want to hang on to life as long as possible and other people who will say, life has lost whatever quality is had that I think makes it worth living, and I think it's time to go.</p><p end="5157" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="5093">Yeah, I entirely agree. The decisions about living and about voluntary euthanasia should be matters between doctors and patients. And that's why I think they're separate from decisions about costs and about when treatment is imposing so much of a burden onothers and on the general health budget that it's not something that the public should be paying for.</p><p end="5157" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="5093">John Donvan So are we, or I, confusing euthanasia, which is a deliberate act to end life, with the withdrawal of an extraordinary measure which the patient hopes will save his or her life? Are those two different things?</p><p end="5157" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="5093">They are somewhat different things, certainly. Again, I think patients should have those choices, and patients might choose that they don't want life support even though that is considered sufficiently cost effective to be worth providing. But that should be a choice.</p><p end="5212" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="5157">John Donvan Okay.</p><p end="5212" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="5157">But they are different.</p><p end="5212" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="5157">John Donvan Ma'am, sorry. I didn't see you.</p><p end="5280" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="5212">Well, I affirm, doctor, that the premises of your question, which is if we can eliminate the waste broadly abused, doesn't that obviate the need for rationing? And that was the point I tried to make in my opening statement, is that the alternative is not simply ration or not.</p><p end="5332" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="5280">The question is whether or not we're going to continue to waste money and then promote the need for rationing because of it. Now, the institute of medicine reports,</p><p end="5332" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="5280">for instance, that we spend $75 billion a year because of healthcare fraud. 190 billion in excess administrative costs. Inefficiently delivered services, $130 billion a year. Now,</p><p end="5332" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="5280">my point is this: It's easier to argue for balancing the budget on the backs of the old people who aren't voting and who don't have lobbyists and who don't have packs [spelled phonetically] than it is to try to rest the money away from the people who are --</p><p end="5332" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="5280">who are perpetuating the fraud or rendering these services inefficiently.</p><p end="5392" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="5332">When healthcare providers perpetrate fraud, government has a legitimate interest in stopping that fraud. That's a perfectly appropriate role for government.</p><p end="5392" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="5332">But it isn't just fraud. I mean, the problem is that the financial incentives in the market system, that the opposition are defending all the way, provide incentives to do more.</p><p end="5392" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="5332">Here is an example. The national rate of cesarean sections is 34 percent of births.</p><p end="5452" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="5392">There's an outfit called Intermountain in Utah healthcare that has a cesarean rate of 20 percent. It saved $50 million by doing fewer cesarean sections. But it cost it money. It lost money by doing fewer cesarean sections, by saving the system $50 million it suffered a financial hit itself because the financial incentives are to do more and you get paid more, and you can pay -- you can build up your financial base, expand, stop, et cetera. So this is the problem with allowing this to be done through the free market.</p><p end="5452" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="5392">We need something that puts a lid on not just fraud but also the incentives to do more medical treatments.</p><p end="5452" is_meta="true" speaker="Peter Singer" start="5392">talking simultaneously</p><p end="5452" is_meta="true" speaker="Peter Singer" start="5392">applause</p><p end="5695" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="5637">-- may I weigh in on that? I come back to the premise that I outlined earlier. And that is that we should be able to make consumer driven decisions, informed by the medical community, mediated by markets. Now, the difference between markets and the government is that within markets you have a choice. And so if you don't like the way the insurance company is rationing your care or the circumstances that it requires for you to participate in, then you have alternatives. When you're in a one size fits all government program, you have no alternatives. You have lost your liberty in that regard.</p><p end="5695" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="5637">John Donvan All right. I don't feel like there is a need from a response from this side because the question was posed to this side, so I'm going to go on to another question. Sir.</p><p end="5812" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="5758">Well, in America, we've historically said that we're entitled to equal protection underthe law. And so the government, arguably, has an obligation to treat everyone the same. Now, in the marketplace, it doesn't always work that way.</p><p end="5869" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="5812">We talk about equal opportunity, not equal outcomes. And so that's what I like about the marketplace, is that decisions can be made in the marketplace. Look, the notion that government is more qualified to make decision and to allocate resources than markets, I think, is a foolish notion. The history of the world suggests otherwise. The Soviet Union imploded on itself because its central managers were not efficient, but in the final analysis, I think we need to understand that the Constitution is a hedge against government. It's not a hedge against individuals. It's not a hedge against the markets.</p><p end="5869" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="5812">Bu the Constitution limits the powers of government. So if government is going to assume certain responsibilities, it's bound by the chains of the Constitution, and I think we want it that way.</p><p end="6000" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="5940">Well, look, I think we're all in agreement that rationing is a de facto matter. Rationing occurs. The question is, who should ration? And is government in a better position than others to ration?</p><p end="6000" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="5940">John Donvan But you've made that before, but, so, to his specific question, the answer is yes, there are situations --</p><p end="6000" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="5940">The answer is yes, and I favor rationing through markets and individuals rather than through government.</p><p end="6053" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="6000">John Donvan Okay. Does the other side want to respond to that . Okay. Ma'am? I'm sorry. I'm going to take two more questions, then, if it's a serious question. Just let the gentleman go first because that -- because that's who has the microphone. And then we'll --</p><p end="6232" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="6182">I would, yes. I mean, I --</p><p end="6232" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="6182">John Donvan Ken Connor.</p><p end="6232" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="6182">You've made a very good point that I think is a very important point, and that is that when we don't have skin in the game, we're less likely to be good stewards of theresources available to us. And so for instance I think one way that we can promote having skin in the game in the responsible consumption of medical resources is to allow young people, for instance, to have health savings accounts with high deductible insurance policies. And they've got skin in the game. Let the government subsidize or provide tax breaks to individuals who purchase health insurance, not just to businesses.</p><p end="6295" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="6232">The way the current system is set up is that we tend to over consume the resources because we don't have any skin in the game. The employer is paying the bill. The government subsidizes the employer, and there's no skin off our nose. And so if we want to promote good stewardship, good stewardship, then I think we ought to -- ought to cause people to have skin in the game. And that would mean that they have a stake in their own healthcare decisions. If they do, they're less likely to over consume resources than they otherwise would be.</p><p end="6533" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="6478">We've actually reached a surprising amount of agreement in this debate because both sides agree that rationing occurs. Sally said there's always going to be rationing. Ken said we are all in agreement that rationing occurs. The question is he went on to say, is who should ration? He says he favors rationing through markets rather than government. But you should read that article that he wrote that I mentioned before on the website about the problems of the elderly because his approach from that article,</p><p end="6533" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="6478">all-profits nursing homes have on average 32 percent fewer nurses and 47 percent higher deficiencies than their nonprofit counterparts.</p><p end="6591" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="6533">This increased emphasis on profits has led to a distressing rise in neglected end of use seniors. So I have to ask, why does Ken have such confidence in the market, solving the problem of the allocation of medical resources, when he is broadly, I believe, critical of what all-profits nursing homes do to abuse seniors. We think that there has to be a better way than allowing profit maximization to determine how we are cared for.</p><p end="6591" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="6533">Let me just conclude by referring to the case that Sally began with, the sad case of her mother, and say that although that is a tragic case, obviously we cannot generalize from a sample of one. I spent most of my life living under single-payer systems, either in Australia or in the United Kingdom.</p><p end="6656" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="6591">I or rather my wife, had two of our children in the United Kingdom and one of them in Australia. I think that the quality of care that we have received in Australia has been outstanding. I've obviously had medical care in this country. I don't think that it's better than it is in Australia. And I don't think that it's even more a respectful of individual choice because Australians can insure themselves in addition to Medicare.</p><p end="6656" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="6591">John Donvan Peter Singer your time is up.</p><p end="6656" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="6591">Thank you very much.[applause]</p><p end="6656" is_meta="false" speaker="Peter Singer" start="6591">John Donvan And here to summarize his position against the motion, Ken Connor. He is founder and chairman of the Center for a Just Society.</p><p end="6656" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="6591">One of our founding fathers said, "If men were angels then we wouldn&#8217;t need government." Men are not angels and we do. Markets are not perfect. And they do need regulation. The question is "Where do we wind up striking the balance?" And I can tell you to Peter&#8217;s point that care in our nursing homes in America is America's dirty secret.</p><p end="6713" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="6656">And it's in part because a -- real estate investors pose as health care providers. And the government doesn't adequately regulate them, plain and simple. And we have a absolute scourge of preventable bedsores, and avoidable malnutrition, and dehydration,</p><p end="6713" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="6656">falls, and avoidable infections. But let me say this, I think it's important to understand that rationing is not required in order for the health care system to remain solvent. That assumes the fallacy of only one alternative, that either we ration or we're going to go broke. That's not true. And that's why I brought up the point earlier in the debate,</p><p end="6713" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="6656">which Dr. Kellermann didn't seem to understand, that there are lots of places from which we can effect savings. But it's work to effect these savings.</p><p end="6773" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="6713">It's hard work to wrest resources from the hands of the special interests. We should not ration. We should not balance the budget on the back of the sick and the dying. We can provide good health care for all people through and including the end of life. We need to ask good questions. We need to ask, "Are the procedures necessary? Are they clinically indicated? Is the cost reasonable?" What we need is a rational approach to end-of-life health care, not the rationing of end-of-life health care. Thank you.</p><p end="6773" is_meta="false" speaker="Ken Connor" start="6713">John Donvan Thank you, Ken Connor.</p><p end="6773" is_meta="true" speaker="Ken Connor" start="6713">applause</p></transcript></debate>