<debate duration="5931" url="https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/special-us-saudi-relationship-has-outlived-its-usefulness"><speakers><speaker name="Madawi Al-Rasheed" position="for"><description>Visiting Professor, London School of Economics</description><bio>Madawi Al-Rasheed is a visiting professor at the Middle East Centre at the London School of Economics and former research fellow at the Open Society... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Mark P. Lagon" position="for"><description>Centennial Fellow &amp; Distinguished Senior Scholar, Georgetown University Walsh School of Foreign Service</description><bio>Mark P. Lagon is a Centennial Fellow and Distinguished Senior Scholar in the Walsh School of Foreign Service, Georgetown University and is the former... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="F. Gregory Gause" position="against"><description>John H. Lindsey Chair &amp; Head of the International Affairs Department, Texas A&amp;M University</description><bio>F. Gregory Gause, III is the John H. Lindsey Chair, professor of international affairs and head of the International Affairs Department at the Bush... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="James Jeffrey" position="against"><description>Philip Solondz Distinguished Fellow, Washington Institute &amp; Former Ambassador to Turkey &amp; Iraq</description><bio>Ambassador James F. Jeffrey is the Philip Solondz Distinguished Fellow at The Washington Institute where he focuses on U.S. diplomatic and military... Read More</bio></speaker></speakers><results><result against="26" for="28" submitters="live" undecided="46" when="before" /><result against="59" for="31" submitters="live" undecided="10" when="after" /><result against="8" for="60" submitters="online" undecided="28" when="before" /><result against="44" for="38" submitters="online" undecided="14" when="after" /></results><transcript><p end="347" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="288">Hello, John.</p><p end="347" is_meta="true" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="288">applause</p><p end="399" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="347">Thank you, John. It's true that my family had fought battles with the Saud, but I can't claim that I personally participated in this battle. Yes, this is precisely the kind of answer or question that I get from Saudi apologists who don't have actually a legitimate response to what I have to say or write.</p><p end="399" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="347">Yes. My partner in the debate, Mark --</p><p end="399" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="347">Ambassador Mark Lagon.</p><p end="581" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="521">Jim is fine.</p><p end="581" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="521">Not at all, John. He's got the best job in the world. I've had the privilege of working with him at times and he's going to do great.</p><p end="642" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="581">Ladies and gentlemen, good evening. I'm very happy to be here and present the motion.</p><p end="704" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="642">I will argue that the U.S.-Saudi relationship has indeed outlived its usefulness. In support of the motion I will cover the domestic and regional considerations, and my partner, Ambassador Mark Lagon, will cover the subsequently the international and global aspects of the bilateral relationship. Before I get started I'd like to make an important point. The domestic consideration that I will consider today cannot be discussed in isolation as some would have it, internal matters of for Saudi Arabia are not really for the country itself. We live in a global world and so many things are interconnected from terrorism to oil. We can't isolate the domestic from the international; however, we have a very good division of labor between the two of us and I will cover the first part of this debate and it deals with internal dynamics.</p><p end="760" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="704">So, one thing to remember is that whatever happens inside Saudi Arabia does not stay within the borders of Saudi Arabia and has implication for the U.S. and also for that matter the whole world. The U.S.-Saudi relationship was dubbed from the very beginning as a special relationship. From the moment American President Roosevelt met King ibn Saud, the founder of Saudi Arabia on the 14th of February 1945. At the core of this relationship were two issues. First, oil and second one is security. The special relationship meant that the U.S. offered Saudi Arabia uncritical, unequivocal, and unconditional support for more than seven decades.</p><p end="819" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="760">We will argue that this is no longer in the U.S.'s best national interest. Let me just explain how this relationship developed. In the 1960s, Saudi Arabia was a very useful ally during the cold war. Its oil wealth, its strategic location -- and believe it or not, its conservative Islamic tradition -- all helped to defend against, and ultimately defeat, nationalism and communism, not only in the Arab world, but also in the Muslim world in general. This special relationship meant that Saudi Arabia became important for the U.S., and even more so, after 1979. So, why 1979?</p><p end="888" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="819">Remember, in 1979, the main ally of the U.S., the Shah of Iran, was toppled. And we get to the establishment of the Islamic Republic of Iran. And at that moment, U.S.-Iranian relations became extremely difficult and hostile. And in fact, they have never been resolved until the present day. It is still a troubled relationship. So, the U.S. decided to put all its baskets in the -- all its eggs, sorry -- in the Saudi basket. And therefore, this relationship became even more special. And we leave that moment to come to Afghanistan in the 1980s. And here, the U.S.-Saudi alliance became extremely important. And also, Saudi Arabia used its conservative Islam in order to start what is regarded today as the menace -- and the menace is the global jihadi movement that brewed in the caves of Afghanistan.</p><p end="941" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="888">But then it spread across the globe, and I do not need to remind you of the details. Today, this special relationship has become counterproductive. Unconditional U.S. support for this absolute monarchy is now against U.S. national interests. The absolute monarchy of Saudi Arabia has become difficult to sustain. First, this regime oppresses its own people, marginalizes women, discriminates against religious minorities, spreads lethal conservative religious ideology, interferes in domestic affairs of its neighbors, and aspires to become a hawkish regional superpower.</p><p end="1005" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="941">This doesn't help U.S. interests, but actually harms them. Unconditional U.S. support legitimizes the regime and authoritarianism, and makes the U.S. vulnerable to accusations of double standards -- supporting dictatorship in one country while promoting human rights and democracy in other countries. More than that -- since 9/11, many Americans have asked legitimate questions. Given that 15 out of 19 hijackers were Saudis, Americans began to ask, "Are Saudis our friends or foe?" This was a legitimate question, given that Saudi Arabia spawned more than three-quarters of the terrorists who perpetrated the most horrific acts against America in modern history.</p><p end="1851" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="1780">Thank you, John. Thank you all for coming. If there's one thing the recent presidential election showed is that it's a good thing to look at all of our assumptions and sunk cost ideas about foreign policy, domestic policy for that, and thus it's good to take a look at Saudi Arabia.</p><p end="1903" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="1851">Nonetheless, this motion as written is not only and I quote the moderator, John, "verbose." It's also not very clear. If I were here tonight debating either we should stop defending South Korea or we should continue, I could give you an idea of exactly what that meant and some idea of the risks racking and stacking them. This is different because we're talking about a special relationship which has no real definition. As a diplomat I know what it feels like because I've done it in countries like Germany, Turkey, Saudi Arabia, Japan, Korea, and a few other places that reached that level, but nonetheless, it is hard to pin down. But let me try to explain a little bit what a special relationship is and in particular what it isn't. Actually, I'll start with what it isn't. It isn't unconditional support.</p><p end="1973" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="1903">I don't know of a Saudi, and I've talked with most of the leaders, who would claim that Barak Obama gave Saudi Arabia unconditional support, but I would like to see the other side defend -- the point that he did. Nonetheless, a special relationship continued. We managed to maintain a good relationship with Saudi Arabia despite major disputes over Yemen, major disputes over Iran, because that's what special relationships do. They don't mean you agree on everything and they certainly don't mean you like each other's domestic policies. What they mean is that they're important players in a construct internationally that you share. So, that takes us to the key question, and it's a very dramatic question right now with a new administration with very new ideas, what is our national interest. From then we can deduce whether Saudi Arabia fits into them. The Trump administration is going back and forth with a lot of rhetoric and lightning bolts between a somewhat more colorful version of what we've been doing since 1945, which is a global security -- collective security system and a global order.</p><p end="2028" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="1973">On the other hand, some in the administration are pushing for a more muscular "America First" national interests approach, rather similar to what we saw -- and it didn't work well -- in the 19th century. But regardless of which way this administration goes, short of full isolationism, you're going to need friends and allies. We can't do whatever we want to do in the world alone. And that means we have to turn to countries that will help us. So, how does Saudi Arabia help us? Now, our colleagues gave us a wonderful example of how they helped us 20, 30 years ago. My first point is, they were certainly no more democratic or lovable then than they are now. In fact, on Mark&#8217;s scale, they would have been an 8, probably, 30 years ago -- [laughs] -- if we'd had an 8.</p><p end="2090" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="2028">But nonetheless, we managed to do a lot of very important things with them. We've got big business to do with them now. First, oil. Back when all this started, according to the other side, it was all about oil dependency, except back in the 1970s, we were in America only beginning to important major amounts of oil. The problem was not oil to America then, or for a while, and we did import a lot -- including from Saudi Arabia -- now, when we only import about 25 percent, and only a small part of that from Saudi Arabia. It's about oil to the world. And where does that come from? 25 percent of internationally traded oil comes from the region around Saudi Arabia, and it is the biggest swing producer. That means that Saudi decisions on oil have a huge impact on the international economy that we trade with and have a huge impact on the price of gasoline at your pump. We saw what happens when we get on the wrong side of Saudi Arabia on oil issues in 1974.</p><p end="2152" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="2090">That's a good example that close friends don't always support each other. The next things is, the threats we're facing in the region. It isn't quite the Cold War, I grant you, but between ISIS and Iran, we have really terrible problems. Have the Saudis killed inadvertently, to a large degree, 6,000 people in Yemen? I think that's a pretty accurate figure. The side they're struggling against, Iran and friends, have killed deliberately, as a policy, a hundred times that. Those are the kind of facts we have to deal with. It isn't a choice between who you'll take to the ball. You're not looking for a special partner, a special relationship -- someone -- a significant other for the rest of your life. This isn't a love affair. It's a question of transactional issues to accomplish common goals. Those common goals include fighting ISIS, fighting Al-Qaeda, and containing Iran in the area.</p><p end="2202" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="2152">And there, we need the Saudis. My opponents are absolutely right about the blackmail. But I'm here to tell you, I don't know of a major ally of ours who hasn't done similar blackmailing. And had I six more minutes, I would start with Turkey. Actually, I would probably end with Turkey.</p><p end="2202" is_meta="true" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="2152">laughter</p><p end="2202" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="2152">But I could throw in even the lovable Germans and some others that would surprise you. The Japanese and the Koreans, once. So -- and as far as us being more in danger because of Saudi -- as a guy who's had a bulls-eye on my back, literally, in the Middle East repeatedly, it's never been because of our relationship with Saudi Arabia. It's been from many other things. That's not the fault of the Saudis. Thank you very much. Vote against this bad, bad motion.</p><p end="2202" is_meta="true" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="2152">laughter and applause</p><p end="2387" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="2323">Saudi Arabia is a pressure cooker. And the more there is of oppression and sabotaging people's rights, the pressure is going to rise. And one day, it's going to implode from within. I just want to remind you of what Woodrow Wilson said about repression actually is so connected to revolution. And the U.S., by giving Saudi Arabia unconditional support, is actually sowing the seeds of revolution. It is unconditional. To give you two examples, if oil is important, those of us who are old enough, remember what happened in 1973 when the oil prices quadrupled-- or most-- because of the embargo.</p><p end="2444" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="2387">And with the U.S. support to Saudi Arabia it wasn't able to do anything, and it took six months for the oil prices to sort of stabilize, but at a very high price. The second point about this unconditional support is Yemen. We have --</p><p end="2560" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="2504">Well, everybody thought Mubarak of Egypt was very resilient, and he lasted 35 years.</p><p end="2630" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="2560">It doesn't mean that things don't just sort of implode one day. And our failure as social scientists is we can't really predict with accuracy when these implosions are going to take place. But this doesn't mean that we can say that Saudi Arabia is stable and so many people have forecasted its downfall. We're not talking about that. We're talking about the U.S.-Saudi relationship. And it is an unconditional relationship so far as we can see.</p><p end="2630" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="2560">John, Mark and Madawi are right, and I think that Greg reinforced that. But I'll say it too. You can't tell who's going to blow up or who can't. But so far you can look at experience. In the Arab world since 2011, we've had three really big meltdowns with war; Yemen, Syria, and Libya.</p><p end="2692" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="2630">Those aren't American allies. Those aren&#8217;t people who were pushed to melt down because America either did too much or didn't do enough. The countries that have survived it include Saudi Arabia, Egypt, albeit with considerable turmoil, and Iraq. Those are countries that America has maintained, at times holding its nose, a close relationship. I'll rest my case.</p><p end="2692" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="2630">Yeah. I think, you know, the example that comes to my mind is Yemen.</p><p end="2753" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="2692">Saudi Arabia, for the last two years almost have launched air strikes on Yemen under different guises and argued that they are doing this in order to restore the Yemeni regime in Yemen. But what had happened was all this is happening with the approval of the U.S. So the U.S. is helping Saudi Arabia to fight a war with its rival in the Middle East, using American weapons that it purchased from the U.S., and destroy a country in its -- on its southern border. So I don't understand how we could describe this relationship in other terms apart from being unconditional. The U.S. is supporting Saudi Arabia in destroying an Arab country. It supported Saudi Arabia in moving its troop to Bahrain where a pro-democracy movement was actually gathering momentum.</p><p end="2806" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="2753">And the interesting thing is that the U.S. -- the United States Navy is stationed in this small island. Saudi Arabia moved its troop to support a regime that oppresses its own people.</p><p end="2806" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="2753">You want me to talk about Syria. Let me talk about Syria!</p><p end="2806" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="2753">Well, directing -- directing the plane, giving them the ground intelligence to direct their plane and, unfortunately, the plane hit a mosque --</p><p end="2806" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="2753">-- and killed hundreds of people.</p><p end="2806" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="2753">Well, if it didn't have American weapons, it wouldn't have done it. It wouldn't have the capabilities.</p><p end="2868" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="2806">This is an argument I heard in Britain. Every time you tell the British, "Don't sell Saudi Arabia arms that kill people in Yemen," they say, "Well, if we don't, the French would." And now, Greg, you're telling me that, oh, if we didn't sell the Saudis the arms that they need to bomb Yemen, then maybe China or Russia would. But two wrongs don't make it right.</p><p end="2868" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="2806">Two wrongs don't make it right.</p><p end="2868" is_meta="true" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="2806">applause</p><p end="2868" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="2806">Leaving aside why the Saudis are in Yemen and the level of our support, because I would say under the Obama administration -- I won't say I know -- it was cut back to an absolute minimum. But leaving that aside, can friends tell us how many significant countries, other than total pariahs, have had weapons cut off by the international community in the last 30, 40 years? I can't think of too many so I don't think that the argument that if the Americans didn't give them nobody would give them weapons.</p><p end="3169" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="3111">Yeah, I think Mark may be confusing the European Union or maybe the Scandinavians with the world. This idea of the world all 180 nations complaining about Saudi Arabia and its behavior most of the world is kind of down there probably in the categories four, five, six, and seven with Saudi Arabia. How many countries of the 180 are in those last four categories?</p><p end="3169" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="3111">Thank you.</p><p end="3169" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="3111">No, what I'm trying to say is --</p><p end="3169" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="3111">You're trying to say that it's a liability to have such a, you know, stinking fish of an ally and that this one's trouble. I've never heard that.</p><p end="3226" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="3169">That's a good point.</p><p end="3226" is_meta="true" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="3169">laughter</p><p end="3226" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="3169">Yeah. Well &#8211;</p><p end="3226" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="3169">Jim, I would like to ask you, how could you justify sending your American troops to liberate the women in Afghanistan, while at the same time sending the same troops to protect a regime, such as the Saudi regime, who oppresses its women? We're not saying that the U.S. should interfere in the domestic affairs of countries. That's not acceptable in international law. What we are saying is resolve the contradiction. You cannot be liberating Afghan women and supporting the regime that oppresses me.</p><p end="3302" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="3226">You know, we've gotten a really big issue here. We've gone beyond the issue into one of the core things that probably deserves 10 Intelligence Squared debates. And that is the purposes of our foreign policy. We didn't send our troops to Afghanistan to liberate women. I'm --</p><p end="3302" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="3226">That was part --</p><p end="3302" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="3226">-- happy --</p><p end="3302" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="3226">-- of the discourse at the time --</p><p end="3302" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="3226">Wait a second.</p><p end="3302" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="3226">I do remember.</p><p end="3302" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="3226">Wait a second. I am not going to be responsible for the idiocy that our government has put out publicly, including what I said. I'm just going to talk about --</p><p end="3302" is_meta="true" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="3226">laughter</p><p end="3302" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="3226">-- I --</p><p end="3302" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="3226">I'm going to talk about why we went in there. We went in there because we lost 3,000 people one fine day in September 2001. That's why we went in there. And that's why we do a lot of other things in the world. This idea that our foreign policy is all about interfering in the internal affairs of very, very different societies that the best of us know very little about, for our purposes -- to make them look more like us -- is a mistake, as a guy who has been sent out there for decades to do it.</p><p end="3359" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="3302">I'm a reformed nation builder.</p><p end="3359" is_meta="true" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="3302">laughter and applause</p><p end="3411" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="3359">I think we tend to exaggerate the kind of reforms that we are witnessing in Saudi Arabia. Since the Arab uprising, hundreds of people went to jail -- bloggers, poets, historians, professors at universities. You can go to jail in Saudi Arabia if you write a poem about the king, criticizing his policies. You could go to jail if you Tweet 140 words.</p><p end="3469" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="3411">You can go to jail if you write a short article saying that perhaps there is a rivalry between the princes. You go to jail. So, basically, the -- let me just consider the issue of women. Mark mentioned the elections. We &#8211; don&#8217;t imagine that Saudis, men and women, are actually participants in elections. There are no elections in Saudi Arabia that bring an elected government. This is an absolute monarchy. What we have is a consultative council. Members -- the members are appointed by the king, and he appointed 30 women to this council. And its role is advisory. But appointing women to this council does not necessarily translate into empowering women. These are the king's women. They are not the women who represent the real women.</p><p end="3528" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="3469">So basically the reforms that we are talking about here are very, very cosmetic, superficial. Even the Vision 2030, that is supposed to transform Saudi Arabia into this liberal market economy away from oil is very myopic.</p><p end="3661" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="3597">Yeah, it's not a zero sum game. The U.S. can have good relations based on interests -- we're not talking about values -- with many countries in the Middle East at -- in the Persian Gulf, and it had actually started doing that. Stopping this unconditional support to Saudi Arabia doesn't mean that the U.S. shifts to Iran.</p><p end="3714" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="3661">The U.S. had other choices, for example, recently it had worked with Oman, another country in the Persian Gulf, to reach an agreement on Iran's nuclear program. So there is diversification. But to put all your eggs in one basket and give Saudi Arabia this unconditional support is counterproductive. It's actually -- I'm not arguing that, you know, the U.S. should intervene in Saudi Arabia to change the situation in favor of Saudis. Saudis have asked for reform and have paid a high price. Change is not going to come from the U.S. And the U.S. specifically has a very bad record at instigating political change in countries in a successful way. We have examples. And --</p><p end="3774" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="3714">That was a great question. We got a great answer because we've now gotten into, what do we do if we do pull back from Saudi Arabia. We'll replace Saudi Arabia with Oman. That is, we won't want to put all of our eggs in one basket. In terms of where we put our eggs, Saudi Arabia is a barn. Oman is an outhouse and not a very big one. [Laughs] We need to do serious foreign policy work, folks, all around the world for your security and the security for a lot of people outside of the United States as well. You don't do that with Oman.</p><p end="3774" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="3714">I'm sorry, it's not about size. More countries can have more impact when they don't have regional ambitions like Saudi Arabia and Iran. The reason why the nuclear agreement worked with Oman is because Oman is small and doesn't have regional ambitions like Iran and Saudi Arabia.</p><p end="3774" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="3714">I like Oman --</p><p end="3774" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="3714">So have equal distance -- equal distance.</p><p end="3954" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="3902">As our opponents have noted, there have been some very minor steps on human rights for women. In terms of human rights for women, Saudi Arabia is at the bottom of the barrel. On other questions of human rights it ain't good. We have Mark's scale. But in a lot of areas, it probably crawls up to the number four and number five in certain areas of openness of speech, although that's also limited. I disagree with you, partially because I've looked at a lot of other countries where it's a lot worse. And the question is, is that the purpose of a special relationship, to make countries -- now, this is a question to the audience, and specifically to you. Is it your belief that we are out there with all of our guns and all of our military and all of our importance -- power in the world to make these people follow our norms? I don't think so.</p><p end="4395" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="4335">Yeah. I --</p><p end="4395" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="4335">It's a good question, particularly the way John reformulated it.</p><p end="4395" is_meta="true" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="4335">laughter</p><p end="4395" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="4335">First of all, I may be violating John's rules. All in all, Mark has a point. If countries did look more like -- if not us, Denmark -- we would have a more stable world. The distance between us that has come into this is I don't know how to make that happen. And one reason for that is there is an international community that is up there in the U.N. It's in NGOs and such. And then there's the international community that I've dealt with for 35 years. That international community worries about the real security threats. Saudi Arabia, other than on the margins 20, 30 years ago with the Wahhabi outreach, was not on anybody's list.</p><p end="4455" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="4395">But it's a long list. And the main 911 to deal with that list has been -- ever since the 1940s -- the United States. We may like it--we may not like it. But that's what we've been doing all of that time. And what countries are motivated by is whether we stand by our allies. I myself didn't know if we did the right thing, abandoning Mubarak, from the standpoint of he was a total loser by the time he left, and it was clear he was going down. But what happened around the world was we got a hell of a lot more reaction and blowback around the world for letting a good ally go who put two divisions into Saudi Arabia in 1990 to stand with us against Saddam -- than we have ever gotten for our human rights cozying up with somebody who is violating them. That's the way the world works --</p><p end="4631" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="4577">I think the words "leave us" is not on the agenda of this debate. It is about changing what is called a special relationship, the unconditional relationship, into something that is more complicated. It is not a straightforward either-or situation. We are not asking the U.S. to intervene in Saudi Arabia's domestic affairs. But we are asking the U.S. to put conditions on the arms sales that kill people in neighboring countries -- in Yemen, for example -- or allow Saudi Arabia to become hawkish. We talked about Mubarak. And this is something that Jim mentioned, that the U.S. cannot just jump and save countries because it doesn't work.</p><p end="4687" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="4631">In 1979, the major ally of the U.S., the shah of Iran fell under the pressure of a mass revolution, and the U.S. couldn't do anything despite the fact that the U.S. had a close connection with intelligence services of Iran, with the -- with the Iranian government. And the same thing will happen in Saudi Arabia. If there is a problem, the U.S. cannot, and perhaps will not be able to save the regime. So it is time to switch that relationship from an unconditional support to the regime to a support of the Saudi people who are actually going to be there after the regime disappears. And the relationship will become stronger if the U.S. distances itself from the excesses of the Saudi regime.</p><p end="4820" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="4747">Yeah. That's a good question. And believe me, the last administration actually wrestled with that, and it came to the conclusion, "Saudi Arabia, you've got to learn to share the Middle East with Iran," and Iran that we thought -- encouraged by the negotiations for the JCPOA or the nuclear agreement would start behaving. 600,000 dead Syrians later, I think this issue is no longer on the table. Iran -- essentially, there are two kinds of countries in the world from a geopolitical standpoint: Those who are trying to change the global order in some kind of illegitimate and typically violent way -- that's the Soviet Union, it was Japan and Germany. It was Milosevic in the Balkans. It was Saddam. It's been Iran. It's North Korea. And there's those regimes, some of which are pretty deplorable internally, that basically are willing to live with and to one or another degree, halfheartedly in a goofy way often sometimes with full intelligence sharing, sometimes with signals, yes, human no, are willing to work with us to preserve that international order which benefits us all.</p><p end="4855" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="4820">Saudi is in the latter category. Iran is the former category. For me, that closes the case.</p><p end="4855" is_meta="true" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="4820">applause</p><p end="5024" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="4964">Yes, because Saudi Arabia --</p><p end="5328" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="5253">I go back to my original statement that this U.S.-Saudi relationship has outlived its usefulness and when talking about the domestic affairs I brought them up so that you are aware that suppressing the Saudi people is counterproductive and it is going to implode if not today, in the future.</p><p end="5375" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="5328">My colleague, Professor Gause, wrote on the back of one of my books and I quote "No one writing in English followed the Saudi political scene more closely and more critically than she does." He knows that he and I cannot be sitting in Riyadh, the capital of Saudi Arabia, debating this. And this is the problem. By oppressing Saudi people, by the depression that is so prevalent in Saudi Arabia, Saudi Arabia loses the brightest people who are actually the future of the country. Like today there are a hundred thousand or even more than that, slightly more than that, Saudi students studying in the U.S.</p><p end="5436" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="5375">If those people utter a word of criticism of the Saudi government they sabotage their scholarship and also they can get their passports confiscated or even their nationality withdrawn. Those people are going to seek asylum nowhere but in this country and if we, all our -- the Saudis who have been educated leave the country were again to leave in the space a vacuum that is going to be filled by people exactly the same people who perpetrated that horrible act on 9/11. So there will be a vacuum created and this vacuum is going to hit not only Saudi people, but the U.S. I just want to conclude by giving you one personal story and allow me to share it with you. I was in the process of publishing a book called, "A History of Saudi Arabia," and the Saudi -- their efficient intelligence services found out that I was writing this book in London.</p><p end="5514" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="5436">So they called my father. As a woman they don't want to talk to me so they have to go to my father to warn me. So, the Saudi ambassador in Paris calls my father and said to him, "If your daughter publishes that book --</p><p end="5514" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="5436">-- we are going to take disciplinary action."</p><p end="5514" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="5436">Okay.</p><p end="5514" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="5436">Thank you, John.</p><p end="5514" is_meta="true" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="5436">applause</p><p end="5514" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="5436">Mark's visit to Riyadh rings true because I've had a visit very similar to that on a somewhat different subject, with a somewhat similar response. But I want to talk about a third visit of American officials to Riyadh in the summer of 1990. Saddam had gobbled up Kuwait in two days, and everybody was worried that the whole Middle East would blow up. The Saudis were horrified and frightened of Saddam. They were also frightened about American possibly deploying troops, leading to upheaval in the Kingdom.</p><p end="5572" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="5514">The American delegation came out and said, "We'll stand by you, but you have to stand by us. We have to go all the way if we have to. This isn't just defending Saudi Arabia, although we'll do that. This is going into Kuwait and throwing them out if we can't get them out diplomatically." The Saudis thought long and hard, and they said yes. For 12 years, good things flowed in that region from that one decision: the defeat of Saddam, the liberation of Kuwait, a Kurdistan in Northern Iraq that is one of the real success stories of the Middle East, the Oslo Accords between Israel and the Palestinians, the peace between Jordan and Israel, and many other things as well. That's what the Saudis are there for. This president -- or the next one -- is going to get one of those famous calls at 3:00 in the morning. And it probably will be involving the Middle East.</p><p end="5627" is_meta="false" speaker="James Jeffrey" start="5572">He or she is immediately going to think, "Where is Saudi Arabia?" My argument tonight is we need that country. That country needs us. If we tamper with that relationship, for whatever superficial or secondary reason, they may not be there the way we need them, at a very, very dangerous moment for both them and for us. Thank you very much. Please vote against this.</p><p end="5714" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="5657">Yeah. I was just -- so, the ambassador, Saudi ambassador called my father and said that he's going to take the scary action if I publish a history book. And I was actually outside Saudi Arabia. Imagine what would have happened to me if I was in Saudi Arabia. So, basically, I went ahead and published the book.</p><p end="5775" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="5714">So, what I'm saying is that &#8211;</p><p end="5775" is_meta="true" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="5714">applause</p><p end="5775" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="5714">-- there are many Saudis, women and men like me, who would like to see a better future. And they get disillusioned when the U.S. supports this repressive regime.</p><p end="5775" is_meta="true" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="5714">applause</p><p end="5775" is_meta="false" speaker="Madawi Al-Rasheed" start="5714">We're not saying that -- it is those people that we lose because of this double-standard that applies in its relationship to Saudi Arabia. Then U.S. interests will be affected, simply because the people who have the prospect for change, who want to change in positive ways, would leave the country. And we've already seen so many Saudis, on scholarship in the U.S., asking for asylum in order to stay here. If all of those people don't go back, then there is no future. Not only for Saudi Arabia, but for a U.S.-Saudi relationship.</p></transcript></debate>