<debate duration="6409" url="https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/us-drone-program-fatally-flawed"><speakers><speaker name="Ahmed Rashid" position="for"><description>Pakistan-based Journalist &amp; Author</description><bio>Ahmed Rashid is a Pakistani journalist based in Lahore. He presently writes for Financial Times, International Herald Tribune, The New York Review... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="John Kael Weston" position="for"><description>Former State Dept. Political Adviser to Marine Units, Iraq &amp; Afghanistan</description><bio>John Kael Weston represented the United States for over a decade as a State Department official and political adviser. Prior to his war-time service&#151;seven... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="Admiral Dennis Blair" position="against"><description>Former Director of National Intelligence</description><bio>Dennis Blair was Director of National Intelligence from January 2009 to May 2010, leading sixteen national intelligence agencies and administering... Read More</bio></speaker><speaker name="General Norton Schwartz" position="against"><description>Former Chief of Staff of the U.S. Air Force</description><bio>Norton ("Norty") Schwartz retired as the Chief of Staff of the U.S. Air Force (CSAF) in 2012, after serving for over 39 years in the Air Force. Schwartz... Read More</bio></speaker></speakers><results><result against="34" for="24" submitters="live" undecided="41" when="before" /><result against="65" for="20" submitters="live" undecided="14" when="after" /><result for="50" submitters="online" undecided="50" when="before" /><result against="50" for="50" submitters="online" when="after" /></results><transcript><p end="419" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="358">Well, that's not entirely true because there is and there always has been a peace lobby within the Taliban. And they do talk to me still, but the hardliners, I agree, don't like me very much.</p><p end="419" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="358">Kael --</p><p end="481" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="419">Not really, not because they're --</p><p end="481" is_meta="true" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="419">laughter</p><p end="481" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="419">-- not because they're not great gentlemen, but, you know, I got star struck my first year and then realized that I would no more rather be with people in the military than with the gentlemen across the table but I have to say, that being said, you know, Ambassador Holbrooke used to remind me what Premier Clemenceau said about war, which is "It's too important to leave to military men." If they're feeling bad about that, they just need to Google what General Jack Rippersaid in response, which is even a better quote. So,</p><p end="481" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="419">thank you.</p><p end="540" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="481">Well, you can be over prepared for the task at hand.[laughter]</p><p end="540" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="481">One of the wise warriors of my generation in the armed forces, retired Air Force General Norty Schwartz.</p><p end="598" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="540">I have. And interestingly enough, it's harder than it looks. It's not a cartoon. The interesting thing, ladies and gentlemen, is that you don't have the sensations of flight that you actually have in an aircraft. And it makes a big difference.</p><p end="598" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="540">Is it -- well, it is a different piloting experience for sure.</p><p end="777" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="715">Thank you. And I want to say, it's great to be back in New York City. I was a resident here for four years, and I think it's one of the two most scrappy and resilient places in America. I won't say what the other one is, but you can probably guess.</p><p end="777" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="715">I also have to say that although our topic tonight is drones, I think in the back of our mind, we know that our nation is having a very important debate about Syria. And I justwant to say I'm grateful that we the people are leading our government on that issue,</p><p end="777" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="715">and at least we're pausing for a while, perhaps, before a decision is made.</p><p end="777" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="715">The issue at hand is the motion that Ahmed and I are going to spend seven minutes each -- as well as the rest of the evening, of course -- we believe strongly that the program is fatally flawed. Ahmed will cover some of the issues that I won't. We've divided the labor as follows: he's going to look at lot of the legality questions. He'll look at -- from his perspective in Pakistan and all the great books he's written -- how much recruiting has actually increased. And contrary to, I think, some of the conventional wisdom, how effective and how targeted some of these drone strikes are.</p><p end="840" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="777">My points are going to be based on having lived in interesting places like Fallujah, Khost,</p><p end="840" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="777">Helmand . I view my role tonight as being the ambassador for the people that don't get a voice on this debate, which are really the Afghans and the Pakistanis -- most of the people I sat across a table from and heard the stories after the drones launched the hellfire missiles. So, if I do that well enough, hopefully you'll get some of their voices,</p><p end="840" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="777">which is what motivated me mostly in this debate, is to not speak as a former State Department official, but to actually speak for the people. So, it's not a headquarters perspective. It's not a State Department official perspective. It's their perspective.</p><p end="840" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="777">One thing left out of my bio was that my mother is a fifth-grade schoolteacher, so if you'll bear with me, I'm going to ask you to do a couple things she taught me. I've got about 30 seconds to ask you for this, so, the first is show and tell, and the second is a pop quiz. I'm going to start with the show and tell because -- I think it reinforces, again,</p><p end="840" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="777">what's lost in the drone debate too often.</p><p end="903" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="840">This is a pakol, which is a wool cap that basically, the more rural parts of Afghanistan,</p><p end="903" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="840">you'll see the tribal people wearing. Again, I'm trying to give voice to these guys, some of my friends.</p><p end="903" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="840">It's a wool cap that kind of looks like -- I don't know how I'd explain it, but it's a pretty cool cap that's round and rolled up at the bottom. The --</p><p end="903" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="840">Worn by Afghans in the tribal regions. This sparkly cap is called a kandahari, which is what I consider the next generation of leaders that you'll see wearing a lot. And again, if we're listening to them, what they tell us is basically that the drone program is undercutting them and undercutting their future.</p><p end="903" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="840">And then finally -- and I'll be quick -- I think I'm speaking on behalf of the front-line troops, because contrary, again, to conventional wisdom, this Kevlar helmet -- which is a Marine helmet -- I think represents those of us who dodge more IEDs and dodge more bombs when these drone strikes actually don't hit their target.</p><p end="965" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="903">Okay. The quiz. If you could pull out a piece of paper, my mom will be proud. Or if you can take some mental notes -- I'm going to ask you two questions, and I think they're important questions, and they're relevant. The first is, after 12 years of constant warfare, which really started in the scarred city of New York with Lower Manhattan,</p><p end="965" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="903">what words or adjectives do you think Afghans or Iraqis or Yemenis associate with the United States of America? Nouns, adjectives, whatever comes to mind.</p><p end="965" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="903">And then secondly, what words would you associate with our nation, the United States of America, after 12 years of basically constant warfare? Second question is, why is May 1, 2010, relevant to this debate? Don't Google it. Don't use your iPhones. But if you happen to -- if that rings a bell with you, we'll come back to it. The two case studies I'm now going to focus on in about the -- half of the time I've got left are one from Iraq,</p><p end="965" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="903">Fallujah, and a couple basically from Afghanistan.</p><p end="1021" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="965">In 2004, drones were not armed. They were eyes in the sky. When drones became a fatally flawed program is really the X that I'm trying to hit here. The Fallujans would look up, they'd hear a flying lawnmower. The women would hang their clothes and get awkward and uncomfortable. The city leaders would come into our meetings and be irritated, but they weren't yet strategically against us. And, of course, this is the site of the largest battle of the Iraq war. When did they become fatally flawed, and who did they become fatal to? I will argue, and Ahmed will argue as well they became fatal to civilians, more than a few. And they became fatal, I believe, to all of us. In Afghanistan,</p><p end="1021" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="965">in early 2009, marine general Larry Nicholson and I were in a place called Tagaz, which is basically the southern reaches of our area of operation.</p><p end="1084" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="1021">We met a bunch of Marines who were alone and unafraid at the edge of the American military empire, overstretched. We all know the story. The next day, in the same location, a suicide bomber blew himself up, killed two marines and killed a corpsman. If anyone wanted revenge, I did. If anyone wanted revenge, General Larry Nicholson did.</p><p end="1084" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="1021">If anyone wanted revenge, the United States Marine Corps did. Within a few days, we identified some suspicious looking guys who were near the area from above. Two drone strikes landed a couple hellfire missiles. One of the men was killed right away. The other one was split in two. And we all watched as he tried to drag himself into the hole from the first strike. He couldn't hide. He bled out. He died. Was it a good guy?</p><p end="1084" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="1021">Absolutely not. But was he found out to be directly tied to the attack? No. That happens more than we'd like to admit. The next example is based on a New York Times article that just came out on Sunday. You may have read it, but I wanted to be as topical and as recent as I could.</p><p end="1141" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="1084">Reportedly 14 Afghans were killed. So I asked a friend of mine, who lives in Kunar, what he was hearing. And he quoted a villager who said this: "May Allah give me power for one day to use a single drone on the American people so that the American politicians understand how much it pains when a missile comes from the sky and kills your relatives in front of your eyes, and you can't revenge them any more." I've got another quote,</p><p end="1141" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="1084">but I don't have time to get there. In closing, I found a very convincing op-ed by a very senior former member of our government, highly experienced, wrote it brilliantly,</p><p end="1141" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="1084">brilliant perspective. And it was titled, "Drones alone are not the answer.&#8221; And it was a New York Times op-ed that came out on August 14th, 2011. He said, "the important question today is whether continued unilateral drone attacks will substantially reduce al-Qaeda's capabilities. They will not.&#8221; And I am pleased that he is on stage with us. It's Admiral Blair. And I look forward to hearing more comments based on the argument he made in the New York Times. So I'm out of time, but thank you.</p><p end="1201" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="1141">Good evening, ladies and gentlemen and our fellow debaters. On behalf of Admiral Blair, it's a privilege to be here to address with you a very, very important topic. And,</p><p end="1201" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="1141">Kael, I would argue that I'm representing the troops in the field tonight. And we can talk about the relative advantages. But I think it's important also to address the issue Kael mentioned of the strike on Sunday.</p><p end="1257" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="1201">It's important to know that that strike killed the individual who publicly admitted to kidnapping Sergeant Bowe Bergdahl of the United States Army who was still the only American service person who is incarcerated in Afghanistan today. Now, it may be that others were also injured and/or killed in this event. But I would argue that Afghanistan is a declared combat zone, ladies and gentlemen. And under the rules of armed conflict,</p><p end="1257" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="1201">that this individual was a legitimate target and clearly a combatant. And he will kidnap no more American servicemen.</p><p end="1316" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="1257">But let me go back to a bit more balanced discussion. What I want to do tonight -- and I submit, ladies and gentlemen, that the employment of U.S. strike-capable systems is a viable and a rational response to a vexing battlefield problem, one that must be calibrated, used with care, synced withpolicy. But nonetheless, one that allows us to pursue our objectives in a fashion that minimizes loss of life for friendly forces and maximizes the opportunity to avoid needless casualties of friendlies; in other words,</p><p end="1316" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="1257">collateral damage.</p><p end="1378" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="1316">Simply remotely piloted aircraft, or drones, permit more considered and more accurate and, as a result, more proportionate application of lethal force than any other comparable weapon system. Because they can spend longer time over the target than equivalent manned aircraft, they give their operators the time to maximize the certainty but not necessarily achieve absolute certainty that they are engaging the right enemy combatants and that they have the time and the means to confirm the presence of noncombatants in the presence of the intended target. Thoughtful observers like our partners tonight have mentioned a number of criticisms. Let me talk quickly about a couple of them.</p><p end="1442" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="1378">One is that the absence of physical risk to the operator encourages our political leadership to use remote systems more often than they would if they had to put American troops in harm's way. I would counter by asking whether those who use this argument would prefer for the American military to absorb casualties just for the purpose of making war less numbing to the political leadership. In addition -- that's a tactical level -- is the ability of remote systems to maintain surveillance of target areas with remote operators carefully and deliberately evaluating potential targets against the criteria that allows them to shoot, that makes this system so discriminating and effective.</p><p end="1501" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="1442">Soldiers and airmen under fire on the ground I think you would agree, Kael, are far more likely to shoot back at the sources of fire aimed against them, with greater danger to noncombatants than are remote operators whose safety and lives are not at immediate risk. There's also a concern that nonstate or state actors will use these technologies against us in a more crude and indiscriminate fashion than do we. And well, they might.</p><p end="1501" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="1442">But the reality is is that this technology is proliferating, and not because we chose to use it. It is a fact of technology advancing. And our lead was and remains significant.</p><p end="1568" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="1501">So, let me go to a quick summary of some data. This goes back to 2011 in Afghanistan during the surge period. There are about 150,000 Air Force flights in Afghanistan in 2011. Sadly, about 3,000 of those flights were medical evacuation sorties of our wounded, and our dead. Compare that total to 25,000 close air support sorties and support of ground forces, your Marines, of which 1,400 had at least one weapon release. So what this means is, is out of 25,000 sorties, 1,400 actually released a weapon. There were many sorties that flew with no weapon release at all. That's what a professional Air Force does. Ready, finger on the trigger, but extremely careful and deliberate about applying lethal force in practice and in principle.</p><p end="1621" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="1568">333 of those 400 weapon releases were by remote systems. Now, I ask you, were those releases -- the three quarters of the releases -- from manned aircraft somehow more practical, less immoral, less unfair than those 25 percent that were released by unmanned aircraft? I think not.</p><p end="1686" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="1621">The first thing I think to make clear is that unfortunately drones -- which is -- it's a weapon, it's a tool, it's a tactic -- has almost become a strategy in itself, and this is how foreign governments and countries where drones are being used see it. All the good of U.S. foreign policy, aid, foreign aid, training of security forces, bank loans, et cetera, et cetera, all are demolished when at the same time the U.S. uses drones. So in fact drones are undermining U.S. foreign policy. They become the only symbol of foreign policy which people abroad remember when they are -- when those countries in particular are targeted. And some of the countries like Yemen, like Pakistan are in fact allies of the United States and drones are being used against allies, naturally that is infuriating the population even more.</p><p end="1731" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="1686">Secondly, how badly have drones affected the counterterrorism strategy, the much more sophisticated strategy that has emerged from the U.S. in the last few years, where the whole strategy is made to protect population, to provide economic incentive,</p><p end="1731" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="1686">development, et cetera. Again, here we see the counterterrorism strategy being undermined completely by drones because the people are very scared of them, and they do take out civilian targets just as much as they take out al-Qaeda. The other question which I think has to be agitating the minds of many Americans is how legal is this?</p><p end="1797" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="1731">How legal is it to bomb and kill individuals in another country with which you are not at war, with which nothing has been disclosed, there's no transparency involved, nobody is informed as to why and how these people are being killed, and often this is, again,</p><p end="1797" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="1731">taking place in countries, you know, that are allies of the U.S. The lack of transparency is not helped by the fact that the CIA has been mostly involved in using drones,</p><p end="1797" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="1731">especially in Pakistan. If -- and certainly there's a move now to move some of these drone attacks to the defense department, but -- and that could increase transparency,</p><p end="1797" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="1731">but at the moment the CIA's running it and nobody knows how these targets are chosen or whether killing these individuals are justified or not. Now, what all this is leading to isan enormous buildup of hatred for the United States, and that is not just affecting people in the target countries but people all over the Muslim world in particular.</p><p end="1857" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="1797">It's quite shocking to see the figures in Pakistan. One poll puts 74 percent of Pakistanis now hate the U.S. more than India, and remember, Pakistan has fought three wars against India, and India is the proverbial enemy. Another poll that I just read recently in Chicago, yesterday, put it at 94 percent. And here, as I sit, we're talking about a so-</p><p end="1857" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="1797">called ally of the United States.</p><p end="1857" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="1797">Now, what should also be worrying is the precedent that is being set. What happens when another country will start using drones? First of all, what happens if a European country, or Russia, or a so-called ally of the United States uses drones? What is the U.S.</p><p end="1857" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="1797">strategy going to be? How is that going to affect U.S. foreign policy? Are you going to slap that country down? Are you going to tell that country to behave itself and say, "No,</p><p end="1857" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="1797">only we have the right to kill people in other countries. You don't have that right."</p><p end="1925" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="1857">Even more dangerous, what happens when an enemy of the United States uses drones?</p><p end="1925" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="1857">What happens if North Korea, tomorrow, uses drones to kill South Koreans? What happens if Al-Qaeda itself develops drones? What happens if any -- if the Syrians or any of the problematic regimes, dictatorships, start using drones? So, what will be the U.S.</p><p end="1925" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="1857">policy then? Are you going to go and bomb those countries? What is the U.S. strategy policy going to be? There's a complete vacuum here. There's no thought being given to this. But this could happen tomorrow. Drones now are everywhere. Drones are being used for all sorts of other, peaceful projects. And any of those drones can be bought on the market and they could be converted into drones that kill people. And I think that the idea that somehow, the U.S. is going to have a monopoly over this instrument forever is very short-sighted.</p><p end="1982" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="1925">I think the other thing that is -- that I must answer, the issue of civilian casualties. There is, for example, a drone strategy now, where drones fire what are called signature strikes. That is if a bunch of militants are seen or one or two militants are seen in a group of civilians, or sitting in a bus or sitting in a truck, or something like that, drones are used -- can be used to kill that militant. But of course, they kill everyone else in the truck, too. Women, children, men, civilians. Now, the last drone strike, actually, on Sunday, was not the one that the general mentioned, but was one in which 16 civilians were killed. And President Karzai just complained to the Americans. And they were killed by a drone, because there were a couple of militant guys in the midst of these people.</p><p end="2046" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="1982">I think they were in a bus or a truck or something like that. So, the fact is -- I mean, the issue of civilian casualties is very controversial. The Americans do not tell us what -- you know, how many civilians have been killed. But estimates from other groups put the casualties in Pakistan alone somewhere between 500 and 1,000. I mean, that's the level of inaccuracy that we have, because we really don't know. These areas are inaccessible or -- and the people who would know, certainly, by watching the video screen, the drone firer, that kind of information is available. And lastly, I think we have to understand how drones have been a recruiting poster for Al-Qaeda and global jihad.</p><p end="2046" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="1982">Even local groups -- local militant groups in countries which have nothing to do with Al-</p><p end="2046" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="1982">Qaeda, nothing to do with global jihad -- if they have been droned, they become global jihadists.</p><p end="2100" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="2046">They want to strike back at America. They want to kill Americans. And that is really what is very dangerous, that more and more groups who are really fighting local wars and conflicts are becoming militarized and wanting to strike back at the United States and those other countries.</p><p end="2584" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="2519">The best information we have, one of the best sources, is the Long War Journal. And it's -- it estimates that civilian casualties versus legitimate combatants in the Afghan theater is about one to seven; in other words, one civilian casualty to seven legitimate combatant casualties. In Yemen, the numbers are somewhat different, about one civilian casualty to five. Now, you can question whether Long War Journal's analysis is accurate. It's consistent with some of the UN reporting as well.</p><p end="2643" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="2584">I would argue again that any loss of life, any civilian loss of life, is not what uniform personal strive for. They strive to avoid that outcome.</p><p end="2643" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="2584">Well, we really don't know. I mean, but certainly there's enough evidence in countries like Pakistan and Afghanistan that civilians have died in considerable numbers. Now,</p><p end="2643" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="2584">that's probably getting less and less as drones become more and more accurate. But as long as things like what I described, the signature strikes continue, where it is justified for a controller to drop a bomb on a group of people in which some of them may be militants and others not, obviously, you are going to get civilian casualties.</p><p end="2703" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="2643">And as the admiral said this is a war zone. And, in a war zone, you're going to get civilian casualties. The fact of the matter is that this is really undermining and destroying everything else that the U.S. is trying to do in these countries.</p><p end="2761" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="2703">Well, I think you have to say compared to what? And when one compares the accuracy and the killing and wounding of bystanders from drones compared to, for example,</p><p end="2761" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="2703">artillery which is another means of close air support from a manned aircraft. Then it has fewer innocent casualties. That doesn't mean it's zero, and everyone as General Schwartz said is to be greatly regretted, but it is a -- I can tell you, your regrets are fewer if you're operating drones than if you're shooting artillery or having manned aircraft being called in.</p><p end="2823" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="2761">No, I think that the key part of the ratio of one to seven and one to five is the equals sign behind, and that equals sign is a factor of two, three, four, five. What basically I think we're losing focus of is what kind of reaction are you getting in village, after village, after village, and how many more enemies and how many more targets are you creating even if one Afghan or one Pakistani is killed.</p><p end="2823" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="2761">I think that the numbers --</p><p end="2823" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="2761">-- the body count, yeah, I haven't been close to these drone strikes. You know, we tell ourselves often what we want to hear, and that gets translated into memos in Washington, but the Afghan and Pakistani stories that I have heard is that it's -- whether it's one to seven or one to five, it's a lot more than any of us would like to admit to each other. So I don't want to argue numbers. I think it's a strategic equals sign at the end of the ratio that is the real problem.</p><p end="2884" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="2823">I understand the argument, but I -- but the counter to it is the reality that the U.N.</p><p end="2884" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="2823">reports that 80 to 84 percent of the civilian casualties in Iraq and Afghanistan were caused by the insurgency.</p><p end="2884" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="2823">John Kael Weston:General, I -- absolutely. I think Muslims are killing more Muslims than Muslims were killing me, or the Marines, or the generals that I worked with. They wanted to kill us.</p><p end="2884" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="2823">We're hard to get. I think the issue --</p><p end="2884" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="2823">I -- you make my point.</p><p end="2884" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="2823">Well -- but drones, you've made a point earlier on about pilots being somehow more rational, being removed from the battle, operating out of Nellis Air Force Base in Nevada or wherever they're operating out of.</p><p end="2947" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="2884">I would disagree. We don't give medals for restraint, we give medals for combat valor,</p><p end="2947" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="2884">but I saw a lot of restraint on the front lines.</p><p end="2947" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="2884">Look, your Marines were rigorous about applying the rules of engagement, and so are our pilots, Kale. The bottom line is this is about discipline, and I agree. Civilian casualties is the equals sign, and everyone knows that. And are mistakes made from time to time? Yes, but that is not the policy, nor is it the training, nor is it the supervision of those assets.</p><p end="2947" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="2884">Look, I -- if I can just make one point, neither of you two, with all due respect, have addressed this whole issue about U.S. foreign policy and the use of drones. The fact is that today, you know, you are throwing technology at foreign policy conundrums where you should throw aid, or diplomats, or peacekeepers, or whatever it is.</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="2947">What we are seeing today in many parts of the world where drones are being used, that foreign policy is being subsumed by technology. We've never had this before. I mean,</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="2947">how can you allow technology to determine what your foreign policy --</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="2947">I'm saying that this is the impact that they are having in the countries that received these drones. This is what the public thinks. This is why there's so much --</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="2947">No, it's about drones because drones are a very sinister way of of killing people. I mean,</p><p end="3001" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="2947">they're not accepted as a normal --</p><p end="3059" is_meta="true" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="3001">talking simultaneously</p><p end="3059" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="3001">-- by saying the drones are going to come after you. [laughs]</p><p end="3059" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="3001">Let me --</p><p end="3059" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="3001">Let me talk about Yemen and just take us a little bit out of Pakistan here for a while. In the last two years, we have given $200 million in assistance -- $600 million in assistance to Yemen. Of that, virtually two-thirds has been economic assistance, humanitarian assistance, and governance assistance. Roughly one-third has gone to security assistance. That is, to Yemen. And so, we do have a broad-based program in places like Yemen. We are trying to work on places. The media impression, however, is fascinated</p><p end="3059" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="3001">with the drones. They're sexy. They're sinister. They're so on. So, I'm sorry, but thereality is that it is a broad-based program of which drones are a part and used very selectively.</p><p end="3122" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="3059">And the people who look carefully can understand that. The people who just want to read the first headline and say, "That's all of American policy" are going to stop there.</p><p end="3122" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="3059">You know, there are two narratives --</p><p end="3122" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="3059">-- at work here. There's the American narrative and there's their narrative. We spent a lot of time talking to each other about our narrative, but if you listen to the future leaders of Afghanistan, you listen to the next generation -- drones is a big issues,</p><p end="3122" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="3059">because it is about the legalities. The law students at Khost University used to ask me,</p><p end="3122" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="3059">"What is your case for drones?" Just like Guantanamo, just like the language of these wars that we're in. They are very, very big on how we're doing our wars. So, if we lose that narrative to Al-Qaeda, I think that ratio is actually the equals sign. And if I lined up a bunch of Afghans on this stage, I can tell you, what they tell us is probably what we don't want to hear but we need to hear, and that's really the goal for me tonight, is to bring their voice into this debate. Back on the issue, though, of whether -- you know --</p><p end="3122" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="3059">-- it's back to, you know, dropping bombs from Nevada in Pakistan.</p><p end="3186" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="3122">I -- it's pretty --</p><p end="3186" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="3122">-- straightforward, actually. And that is that the reality is that we have a scenario where the weapon -- the platform is not the issue.</p><p end="3244" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="3186">It's the legitimacy of the target. And the targeting methodology that goes along with it.</p><p end="3244" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="3186">Could I put on the table the issue of double and triple tapping? There --</p><p end="3244" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="3186">-- are a number of cases where -- and I've lived this -- where -- especially in Khost Province, where Mohammed Atta was trained. This is territory directly tied to 9/11,</p><p end="3244" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="3186">unlike Iraq. When you double and triple tap, you're not even going after the initial target. You're actually dropping bombs on the people that come after Round 2 or Round 3. What's the rationale? What's the intelligence? What's the argument that you would make to a law student sitting at Khost University.</p><p end="3297" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="3244">Family members --</p><p end="3297" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="3244">-- community member, whoever it is. They --</p><p end="3297" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="3244">-- get bombed, too.</p><p end="3297" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="3244">But just to --</p><p end="3297" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="3244">-- set the stage, when I became the chief in 2008, we had 32 24/7 orbits of remote aircraft. When I left, we had 58. Now, we didn't do that because we're sort of generous. The reason we did it is because there was a demand signal from the supportive forces, the Marines and the Army --</p><p end="3297" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="3244">Could I --</p><p end="3297" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="3244">Let me finish. To provide the kind of overhead surveillance and strike capability that minimized the risk to their forces. And I would argue, Kael, that this was not just some perception in Washington, but this was real down on the ground.</p><p end="3355" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="3297">No. I -- General, you know, I have the greatest respect for you. My sand is still deep in my shoes, and so I bring baggage with me. However, I found that the commanders on the ground are the 12 to 14 Marine generals I worked with -- the closer they were to the drones, the more skeptical they were. Doesn't mean that all of your arguments are false. It doesn't mean I think every drone needs to be, you know, eliminated from the battlefield. But the closer you are to where the strategic effect is with the people, the more critical I found the marine commanders to be. I don't want to speak for all of them, but it was -- it was a pretty clear pattern</p><p end="3355" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="3297">They should probably speak for themselves.</p><p end="3426" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="3355">no, I don't dispute their effectiveness. Obviously, this is a military weapon that has been developed to do a certain thing. And it is going to be further developed, and it's going to be used even more. I think the point is that it is being -- it is being used very indiscriminately and without any kind of scrutiny or self-knowledge even amongst Americans. The whole issue of legality, the whole issue of the precedent that it sets for other countries to follow, there are a whole range of political issues and political answers that are needed in order for this weapon to be really legal, be legitimate and be justified. And that is the point. I don't dispute at all that certainly many senior members of al-Qaeda have been killed. But this is a weapon that has opened up aPandora's box of questions, especially for those countries who are in receipt of this weapon, you know, at the receiving end. And I think we need -- we need answers. I think this question of precedent is absolutely paramount at the moment with what -- if Syria is using --</p><p end="3482" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="3426">Just because you've discovered the drones doesn't mean that this is the first time that anybody has ever thought about these questions. This is a weapons system which combines the capabilities of surveillance and attack, and it is operated according to the rules of law, the control procedures, the follow up procedures that the U.S. armed forces use for all of the weapon systems that we have over the years. We know how to take new weapon systems, use them for mission purposes, control them so that they're done legally, with lawyers in the command loop to a much greater extent than they are for most any other weapons, and you use them for your purpose, and you try to minimize the harmful side effects of which there are many, as there are for any weapon systems in order to get the mission done. And that's how we do it.</p><p end="3545" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="3482">Just briefly, I want to actually give voice to a real live Afghan. And I'm going to read a quote. When that incident happened that the New York Times covered, a friend of mine went to a tribal elder, and this is what the tribal elder said. &#8220;Siraj Haqqani, the senior most leader of the Haqqani said that since the USA is using drones against people, the people will use Patriot missiles against the U.S.A. Someone in the village asked what he meant, where are the Patriot missiles? Siraj replied, &#8216;Suicide bombers are our Patriot missiles.&#8217;" The question I don't think we still had answered, for example, on the legality question -- and I know we're not in a law seminar, but it's an important one because it's what motivates terrorists to hurt us. Because at the end of the day, I think everyone inthis room needs to ask fundamental question, which is, are you and your family safer because of the drone program as it's currently structured, or not?</p><p end="3603" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="3545">What is the legality of the third wave of drone strikes in terms of the triple tap? What is the legality of that? What are the lawyers in Washington arguing? They're not the initial targets. There's not intel tied to them.</p><p end="3603" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="3545">If you are in a declared combat area, as was the case in Fallujah or in other areas that you're familiar with, if you have combatants that depart that initial strike area, this is not unlike what happened with Zarqawi. The bottom line was, now, that was a manned strike. And hopefully, I make no apologize for that either. But the bottom line is that we have a situation where you have people that depart a site that -- that had combatants, that was identified as a location.</p><p end="3659" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="3603">And they depart that area, and you reengage. This is what happens when people leave a foxhole or when people depart a tank in a tank battle. The bottom line, Kael, I think is that you argue for discretion. I believe in that too. But on the battlefield, the principle is to engage the enemy. It is that.</p><p end="3659" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="3603">Well, we went through a phase in Fallujah where everyone was a military-aged male.</p><p end="3659" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="3603">And I finally told the generals in Baghdad -- at that point, I was young enough that I was still a military-aged male according to our definition. We then switched that definition because we started to treat every Iraqi as a potential threat. And I'll be honest with you,</p><p end="3659" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="3603">if you're a Taliban member, and you're living in a community around family and friends,</p><p end="3659" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="3603">with all due respect, I don't think that that makes you a legitimate target. And that's in effect what's been happening.</p><p end="3718" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="3659">I agree with that. I agree. But if you're carrying an arm, if you have a weapon, I would argue in a combat zone, that makes you a legitimate target.</p><p end="3718" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="3659">And the point is you can see the weapons from these platforms.</p><p end="3718" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="3659">Yes and no.</p><p end="3787" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="3718">No, it is a drone. The drones are an issue because as I said, this is the most sinister weapon that has come into the marketplace, that, you know, there's no individual behind it. There's no judgments being made. And people are very, very scared.</p><p end="3787" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="3718">well, this is what people presume, that somehow, these automatic weapons come up into the sky, and they shoot at will, and they shoot down whatever is on the ground. I mean, there are all sorts of stories and mythologies about drones which, unfortunately have been created. And -- and as I said, this is why this weapon -- the chances of this weapon getting out of hand, getting into the wrong hands and being used indiscriminately in many other parts of the world is -- you know, we should take the example of what the reaction already we are seeing in Pakistan, Yemen and other places.</p><p end="3840" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="3787">I'll briefly -- rules of engagement are pretty tight in marine combat units. And so, yes,</p><p end="3840" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="3787">there's going to be blowback. It's a good question. It's a very legitimate question. The drones are being used in Pakistan, northwest province basically, outside [unintelligible],</p><p end="3840" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="3787">which is a very different arena than in the conventional side, on the Afghan side of the border. Bottom line is, though is it's what the rules -- the lack of the rules actually, I believe, in our drone program that is the biggest problem. There is not, for example, a marine general necessarily that technically can command where those drones go because they're operated in a different chain of command. And we don't need to get too technical, and that may be changing. But, yes, Afghans are going to respond to a cluster bomb going off or an RPG being launched in the wrong direction. But I have faith that our forces, if one thing over 12 years have learned, is they've learned quite a bit of restraint. And then the rules of engagement have gotten a lot tighter.</p><p end="3969" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="3906">That wasn't going to be my dodge.</p><p end="3969" is_meta="true" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="3906">laughter</p><p end="3969" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="3906">It's a judgment. It's a judgment. If there were a wonder weapon that would only kill al-</p><p end="3969" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="3906">Qaeda, dedicated card carrying members, would touch no one else, could be deployed from this room by pressing this button, I'd be all for it. We'd use it. We'd invent it first,</p><p end="3969" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="3906">and then we'd use it. It doesn't. We have a set of imperfect tools that we use to try to deal with this group of people who has declared war on us and who is far less discriminate, more ruthless, more killing in their approach than we are.</p><p end="4017" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="3969">And you have to make a call as to just how hard you use that weapon because it kills other people and it causes other effects which our opponents have ably said. I think that judgment has to be made to continually reevaluate it as you go, and I'm sure that there have been times in the past in which we have erred on the side of using it too much. I think we learned from those, and as the president has said in his opening statements, or his statements, in recent weeks, we've decided to cut it down so I think it's a judgment, and I think we're making it in the right direction.</p><p end="4017" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="3969">I think [unintelligible] a different --</p><p end="4085" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="4017">I think the only overall judgment we can make is that al-Qaeda is far less capable of the sort of attacks that it was in the past than it is now. Drones have been a part of reducing it in that capability and, therefore, overall the balance is in favor of the sort of campaign the United States has conducted.</p><p end="4085" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="4017">And I would only amplify by --</p><p end="4085" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="4017">John Donvan:Norton Schwartz.</p><p end="4085" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="4017">-- if I may, by suggesting that you have a situation where you want desperately to avoid having a larger military presence, which I -- , clearly would have its own negative effect on local population perceptions.</p><p end="4138" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="4085">So my counter question would be, "What's the alternative? What is the least intrusive,</p><p end="4138" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="4085">invasive alternative? That, we have been seeking for some time. And all I can tell you is that every flag -- senior flag officer on the military side that has looked at this problem,</p><p end="4138" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="4085">has sought that solution.</p><p end="4138" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="4085">My view has always been the most important battle going on does not include U.S.</p><p end="4138" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="4085">Marines versus Taliban. It's inside the mosques, inside the madrasas, it's inside the communities. And actually our best allies are the ones that are most critical of this program. So if we're undercutting --</p><p end="4206" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="4138">Well, no, no. I -- yeah, I'm not a person that says, "All drones need to be taken off -- out of the sky." But what I am saying is that we've lost the strategic narratives so that General, I'm all in favor of not sending in the first Marine division anywhere again for the most part. However, I think that we've lost sight of who the best fighters are in these battles. And it's actually not an American anywhere. It's an Afghan. It's a Yemeni.</p><p end="4206" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="4138">It's a Pakistani. So when you listen to our allies who want us to succeed, who want us to be safe, they are pretty uniform in their indictment of drones, and --</p><p end="4206" is_meta="true" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="4138">talking simultaneously</p><p end="4206" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="4138">Well, that's a government to government discussion. I agree with that. As far as the tactic, it's what Ahmed my well spoken and famous colleague here at the table have said, which is that the tactic can't be the strategy. We've enabled the tactic to become a failed strategy and a failed narrative.</p><p end="4263" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="4206">Well, I think there's no doubt that there are obviously ungoverned areas and the Pakistanis have not been active enough in undermining and destroying Al-Qaeda. But I also think that U.S. policy has -- there's been enormous tension between the U.S. and Pakistan over the years, as there has been between Yemen and the U.S. Now, it's not all centered around drones, but it's centered around, frankly, a lack of long-term strategy and vision by both countries. And both are to blame. Now, I think what we need is much greater diplomacy and, you know, diplomatic efforts to strike better relationships.</p><p end="4263" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="4206">We had a situation where -- as you know --</p><p end="4320" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="4263">No. I think they should continue trying to kill them. They should be urging the Pakistanis to do much more to do this. This is the problem, you know?</p><p end="4320" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="4263">Well, yeah, there's a lot of mythology about what seals and drones can do together.</p><p end="4382" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="4320">I think it's a great cause. Thank you.</p><p end="4382" is_meta="true" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="4320">laughter</p><p end="4382" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="4320">That's an easier debate for you to have, that's for sure.</p><p end="4382" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="4320">Right. The decision on what is a target can be struck either by a military or by an intelligence CIA drone is made under criteria that are approved by the White House,</p><p end="4382" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="4320">that are then promulgated.</p><p end="4438" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="4382">And a series of officials, including lawyers, officials in each of those agencies and the chains of command, then apply them to actual names of Al-Qaeda and other combatants. Once they satisfy that criteria, then they are a legitimate target at that point. The question is, can you truly tell -- is that a person that you found and can strike,</p><p end="4438" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="4382">and is there a relatively small level of collateral damage? That is, innocent people around that person before you make the strike. That's how it's done.</p><p end="4499" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="4438">It is.</p><p end="4499" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="4438">It certainly is. Now, signature strikes in a declared combat area are different than those that occur outside declared combat areas. And I -- and the criteria are different. But the bottom line is, if in a combat area, if the individual or individuals appear to behostile, you can engage them in the context of that signature of hostility. On the other hand, activities in non-combat areas -- and this does apply to Pakistan, I would argue --</p><p end="4499" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="4438">it is much more problematic to conduct signature strikes there or elsewhere, where it's not a declared combat zone.</p><p end="4499" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="4438">Yeah. I can talk about those, because I received the phone calls every --</p><p end="4564" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="4499">-- time we conducted a strike. This is up to the middle of 2010. And I think that the administration has been really derelict in not talking about these, because they are based on the self-defense of American and Afghan forces. The signature strikes that were conducted in Pakistan, all of them during my time, and the great majority over all,</p><p end="4564" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="4499">had to do with armed groups of men who were coming out of known Taliban, TTP areas on road headed towards Afghanistan. And we knew that they were not friendly. They were armed. We know what their arms were. And we knew that they were coming to attack Afghans and Americans and others. And we killed them before they could do that</p><p end="4621" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="4564">I just want to answer the question which the lady posed, which I think we should go back to. And I think you're absolutely right. For the admiral to describe the individuals who are involved in this decision making doesn't give us the criteria. I mean, what is the criteria for choosing who's going to live and who's going to die? The fact is the U.S.</p><p end="4621" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="4564">media itself has portrayed that, the president is sitting there ticking off on a list as to who is going to live and who is going to die, or today, who is going to be drone or not.</p><p end="4679" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="4621">Well, could I add, I mean, it became a live issue in the United States only when an American citizen was killed. So all my Afghan and Pakistani friends are like, well, you guys care when it's an American kid named Awlaki that's killed, but not when our cousins and brothers are killed.</p><p end="4679" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="4621">Awlaki was a self-declared combatant.</p><p end="4679" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="4621">The son of -- I mean the 16-year-old. And again, that still hasn't come out. But all I'm saying is that, again, the battle is a battle that involves them more than us. And it's a narrative that I think is really the challenge here. And I think in some ways we agree more than we disagree on who's winning and who's losing that narrative.</p><p end="4679" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="4621">So the adverb here is important, fatally.</p><p end="4743" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="4679">Well, yeah, I should have defined ally. I'm talking about the people that I dealt with on the ground. So whether they were in Khost or in Helmund or even in Fallujah, although the drones weren't armed then, I'll let Ahmed take the bigger issue of the Pakistanimaybe duplicity. And I'm sure there's a lot of double winks that go on every day of the week over there.</p><p end="4743" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="4679">But my concern is the allies that actually are the future leaders of Afghanistan, the university students, the Madrasa students, the tribal elders, the Mullahs, the whole host of people that get killed in these drone strikes when they go wrong. Because I don't think the Taliban hold up a red flag. I know they don't, and say, "I'm Taliban. What happens is there's a bad guy in the family or a bad guy in the village, and we identify maybe he's a bad guy, and we drop a hellfire, and then you turn three villages against us.</p><p end="4797" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="4743">It goes to the ratio and the equal sign. I'll come back to it. Yes to the woman I thought who asked a very good question, elaborated on by you, our moderator, is the number of enemies we're making and the number of targets we're making. And I'll defer to you,</p><p end="4797" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="4743">Ahmed, on the question about his point on as far as the Pakistan government or the Pakistan --</p><p end="4797" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="4743">Can I just say one thing first? And that is that most allies of the U.S. in Europe, are against drones. As far as I know, only the British have openly -- support the U.S. policy of drones. Most of the Europeans, European governments and European parliaments,</p><p end="4797" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="4743">are against it. And they've been --</p><p end="4797" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="4743">Sorry?</p><p end="4797" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="4743">Yes. I mean --</p><p end="4867" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="4797">They do. Or they want greater transparency, or they want greater information as to, --</p><p end="4867" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="4797">but in other words, nobody in the world basically is backing the U.S. use of drones. And I think that's very -- that's a point that is often completely forgotten in -- the American media and --</p><p end="4867" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="4797">Well, I mean, what's your evidence, Mr. Rashid? No one in the world --</p><p end="4867" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="4797">-- use of drones. I mean can you be a little more specific?</p><p end="4867" is_meta="true" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="4797">laughter</p><p end="4867" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="4797">Well, you look at the --</p><p end="4867" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="4797">Can you give me resolutions by legislatures in other countries? Can you give me --</p><p end="4867" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="4797">Well, with all due respect, I haven't heard a lot of, "rah, rah, drones." And I've been in the State Department for 12 years. So I'll help my friend out here; that whether NATO raises their arm and says, we approve the drone program, I know General Dunford and his political adviser, Carter Malkasian have their hands full all the time on these issues.</p><p end="4867" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="4797">But is it a popular thing? I highly doubt that. I don't know any --</p><p end="4918" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="4867">And it's not a popular thing in the United States. We don't like killing people, but we only do it when we have to.</p><p end="4918" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="4867">John Kael Weston:Well, I'm not sure we only go when we have to. I think it's actually, I think, easier for the American people to think it's joystick warfare and send in seal team 6. And that's also another issue that we could get into.</p><p end="4918" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="4867">Well, I would simply -- I would simply say that the drones are handled with the same care, concern, discrimination that the armed forces, the United States and other American agencies handle all other weapons, which they know can kill the innocent as well as the enemy. And drones are used with the same set of procedures. And I think their inherent characteristics allow them to be more on the side of killing those who they intend to kill with fewer others.</p><p end="4979" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="4918">I'll -- I mean, General Schwartz was involved in it much more closely than I was. But I was pretty close to it. There is a novelty factor. Anything that's new and long range and all is -- seems inherently more fascinating, sinister and interesting. We've seen that with new weapons over the generations as they come along.</p><p end="5044" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="4979">Certainly, the sort of media discussion centers on drones. I mean, we're not having an Intelligence Squared debate about overall U.S. policy against Al-Qaeda. We're talking about drones. Why? Because it's sexy, and it's new, and it has a lot of [unintelligible].</p><p end="5044" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="4979">But, no, I think the media effect is important in this, John.</p><p end="5044" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="4979">John Donvan:Yep, okay.</p><p end="5044" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="4979">I think novelty, media, it tends to give it that overwhelming force that Mr. Rashid has talked about. I think we have to get beyond that to what are the actual facts about what's going on on the battlefield. Are we achieving our objectives? Are we -- are we not? Narrative, shhmarative. You know, it's are you getting to your objectives, which are to be able to defeat the Taliban --</p><p end="5044" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="4979">And protect Americans.</p><p end="5044" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="4979">And protect Americans, yeah.</p><p end="5092" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="5044">It's a question of who's more credible.</p><p end="5092" is_meta="true" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="5044">laughter</p><p end="5092" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="5044">Seriously, though, I take your point. Based on the available numbers, again, I would go back to that, you can question Long War Journal, you can question the UN studies and --</p><p end="5092" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="5044">and so on, the New America Foundation is another organization that monitors this.</p><p end="5158" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="5092">But the number -- from 2006 to the present time in Afghanistan, the estimate is that drones have engaged and killed some 2600 al-Qaeda and Taliban combatants. Out --</p><p end="5158" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="5092">the same organization estimates 330 civilian casualties. Now, once again, please don't take the -- that my view is that it doesn't matter. It matters a hell of a lot, and I think Kael is -- and Mr. Rashid have made this point. It matters a lot, but you have to keep this in perspective, and the numbers are pretty clear, one to seven, one to five, you know, you can say that that's anecdotal, but it's the best we have. And my point is, is that I know what the kids do.</p><p end="5219" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="5158">And I would ask all the parents in here if your youngster as we were talking out in the reception earlier was on the ground, what would you prefer to have in the air,</p><p end="5219" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="5158">something that passes over in 30 seconds and goes away or something that is overhead constantly and provides surveillance and an ability to engage the enemy that might well keep that soldier, sailor, airman, Marine safe? I know what my answer as a commander is.</p><p end="5219" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="5158">Well, again --</p><p end="5219" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="5158">-- General, I get that point to an extent. I had lived five out of my seven years in these wars with Marine grunts. Surveillance overhead is a part of war. The issue is when the drones strike, what the net effect is. In [unintelligible] Province on the border with Pakistan I can tell you when those one to five, one to seven -- I think numbers to me is not an issue I like to get into because it's that equals sign.</p><p end="5285" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="5219">Which is how many family members, tribal members, community members are affected by one loss of life? The IED strikes are where most of our guys are losing their legs. So do the IEDs go up when an operation like that goes wrong, and you've got a cousin in Miranshah, you've got brothers in Miranshah, and you live in Khost? I would argue with all due respect that the odds of getting a Marine or a soldier's legs blown off go up because of this program, not go down.</p><p end="5285" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="5219">General Norton Schwartz:Okay, that's your view. My view --</p><p end="5285" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="5219">Yes.</p><p end="5285" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="5219">-- is killing bomb makers makes the numbers go down.</p><p end="5285" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="5219">Fair enough, it's two sides of a --</p><p end="5349" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="5285">It&#8217;s intended to kill Taliban so that they don't keep the nation builders from going and doing their job.</p><p end="5349" is_meta="true" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="5285">applause</p><p end="5401" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="5349">It -- look, I mean, this is --</p><p end="5401" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="5349">-- this is the fundamental question. Remember, that is not a military call. That is a call for civilian leadership, where we go and what we do. And there is an argument that fewer American casualties might encourage political leadership to be more aggressive or more reckless. There is that potential, but that's what best military advice is all about.</p><p end="5401" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="5349">Remember, we have a chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff who is the president's principal military advisor. And if you've watched Mike Mullen, or Marty Dempsey, or in his day Denny Blair, offer military advice, it's not to encourage political leadership to be reckless.</p><p end="5463" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="5401">Ultimately, we salute, but the key thing here is that, that is a legitimate concern, but it is one that the military, the uniforms feel personally.</p><p end="5463" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="5401">And I'd say, if you see a political candidate who thinks a few American casualties are okay, but a lot or not, I wouldn't vote for him.</p><p end="5463" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="5401">Yes. I think so -- I think that's very true. And I fear very much that given the turmoil going on now in the Middle East and other parts of the world, the reluctance of the Americans and the Europeans to want to get involved in by putting troops, orpeacekeepers, or anything on the ground -- we're going to get more and more of this,</p><p end="5463" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="5401">that we throw technology at the problem.</p><p end="5523" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="5463">We throw drones at the problem. And that, I think, is going to be a very, very dangerous world to live in, frankly.</p><p end="5523" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="5463">Hi. Denny wishes I was an admiral.</p><p end="5523" is_meta="true" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="5463">laughter</p><p end="5581" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="5523">Maybe some people in the Air Force would&#8217;ve, too. I don't know.</p><p end="5581" is_meta="true" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="5523">laughter</p><p end="5581" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="5523">Let me just say that I think that our partners here in the debate tonight have expressed absolutely legitimate concerns. And while we've jousted a bit, it's been done with respect and an appreciation for their passion and their conviction on this issue. I'd just like to relate a quick vignette. In earlier days, when I was flying airplanes, I flew a gunship -- a C1 -- it's a C-130 with guns on it. And there was one occasion when I remember the following call came from the ground. And it was this -- &#8220;troops in contact need help now.&#8221;</p><p end="5638" is_meta="false" speaker="General Norton Schwartz" start="5581">When an airman hears -- no matter what service -- Navy, Army, Marine Corps, Air Force -- hears "Troops in contact need help now," there is an immediate response. And it is visceral, but not necessarily as accurate or as coherent as you might like it to be if you were -- if you could have been there for hours prior, and will remain there for hours after, which is the case with the remote aircraft or the drone technology today. I would just conclude by saying that use of drones is neither sport nor a failed tactic. And you must vote against the proposition and the adverb "fatally." Thank you.</p><p end="5698" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="5638">Thank you. And I would echo what the general just said. I -- this is raising the level of debate and we should all be grateful for that. I've got two minutes and I'm going to run through these pretty quickly. I opened with a quiz about what words or nouns,</p><p end="5698" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="5638">adjectives you think they associate with the United States of America after 12 years of constant warfare. I don't have time to ask you what those words are, but occasionally I would hear words like Apple -- they had the Apple phone -- Obama, money. But unfortunately, toward the top of that list was D for drones. It wasn't D for democracy.</p><p end="5698" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="5638">It actually, to be frank, wasn't the nation-building. It was the CT. It was the counter-</p><p end="5698" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="5638">terrorist platform. And I think we should think about that.</p><p end="5761" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="5698">Do we want that to be kind of at the top of the list of what they think about us after 12 years, billions of dollars, thousands of Americans killed, over 100,000 Iraqis, et cetera, et cetera?</p><p end="5761" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="5698">The second point I'm going to now just cite to the question of what happened on May 1st, 2010? I think it was Admiral Blair who referenced this. And I'll add a little detail. Itwas Faisal Shahzad, who just a few blocks from here tried to blow up the blue 1993 Nissan Pathfinder. In that Pathfinder was three 20-gallon propane tanks, a big green metal gun locker that contained a metal pressure cooker pot, 250 pounds of urea based fertilizer, and eight plastic bags with 120 M88s. The New York City police commissioner,</p><p end="5761" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="5698">Ray Kelly, said the bomb would have killed many. The police later on said it would have had shrapnel and probably killed mostly tourists but a number of people. What did Faisal Shahzad say? New Yorkers get that.</p><p end="5761" is_meta="true" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="5698">laughter</p><p end="5761" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="5698">What did -- I used to ride my mountain bike through there, but I didn't go very often --</p><p end="5820" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="5761">Faisal Shahad was asked by a judge what motivated him to try and blow up that Nissan.</p><p end="5820" is_meta="false" speaker="John Kael Weston" start="5761">Here's what he said, "Well, the drone hits in Afghanistan and Iraq," he said finally, "They don't see children. They don't see anybody. They kill women, children. They kill everybody. It's a war. And in war they kill people." One final point, Boston Marathon bombing, April 15, 2013, I don't have time to read what Dzhokahar Tsarnaev said, but basically he said the same thing, "We Muslims are one body. You hurt one, you hurt us all. The U.S. government is killing our innocents."</p><p end="5820" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="5761">I've listened closely to our debaters on the other side. And there are an awful lot of anecdote and generalization there.</p><p end="5886" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="5820">Let me tell a quick story from November 2011, a U.S. patrol that was on the eastern border of Afghanistan, on Pakistan, thought it was being fired on in the night, called for close support fire. A U.S. manned armed helicopter came up, under direction of these ground units fired at the units they thought were threatening them, and ended up killing 24 Pakistani soldiers. Things happen that are bad in war whether you have manned systems or unmanned systems. Things happen that affect U.S.-Pakistani relationswhether you have manned systems or unmanned systems. This is the nature of combat and you have to make a balanced judgment about it. I do find it ironic to be on this side of the motion because as Mr. Weston said I was one of the first people who came out in public against some ways in which the drones were being used in Pakistan well over two years ago.</p><p end="5942" is_meta="false" speaker="Admiral Dennis Blair" start="5886">However, I was not against the technology itself. I was against the way it was being used at that time. I think we've adjusted since that time. I think that's the nature of this dynamic campaign against a group that's shown it's wanted to kill us, and has killed us in the past, and wants to kill us in the future. So I believe you have to vote against this motion. That doesn't mean that you like all of the drone program, doesn't mean you think it needs to be adjusted, changed, and the narrative needs to be improved, but I don't think we should take it out of the hands of those who are trying to defend the United States. Thank you.</p><p end="5999" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="5942">I would just hope that you would consider the long term implications of what drones mean -- will mean in the future for the United States, the day that your enemies get hold of drones and use drones against Americans. The day that even your allies, that drones become a kind of free for all in this world. After all, the whole crisis that we are facing today over Syria is that the danger of chemical weapons becoming a free for all.</p><p end="5999" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="5942">Because so many rogue states hold chemical weapons, and if you allow this one to get away then others can follow suit quite easily.</p><p end="5999" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="5942">And the other thing I'd really like to mention here is that the use of drones has immensely complicated America's relations with its allies. You look at the situation in three countries where drone bases have been set up secretly, Pakistan, Saudi Arabia,</p><p end="5999" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="5942">and Yemen.</p><p end="6059" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="5999">The U.S. set up drone bases with the help of the local regime, which were invariably dictatorships of one kind or another. They lied to their own people, these governments.</p><p end="6059" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="5999">They lied and said, "No, no, there's no such thing as U.S. bases here. There're no drone bases here at all. These are -- people are being killed by artillery shells, or by bombing,</p><p end="6059" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="5999">or something else. And what happened was that the public became more and more anti-regime and anti-American, which led to political crises in certainly two of these three countries. And it could well still lead to a political crisis in Saudi Arabia. So, you have now such a complicated scenario operating, where drones are creating -- I mean,</p><p end="6059" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="5999">one weapon, one weapon, and the use of this weapon is delegitimizing regimes in the region and also creating immense hatred for the United States.</p><p end="6119" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="6059">Now, this is just one aspect of what I see as a future fraught with immense problems related to drones, which we are not even beginning to think about and I --</p><p end="6119" is_meta="false" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="6059">Thank you very much.</p><p end="6119" is_meta="true" speaker="Ahmed Rashid" start="6059">applause</p></transcript></debate>